<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voyage to Mount Libanus wherein is an account of the customs, manners, &amp;c. of the Turks : also a description of Candia, Nicosia, Tripoly, Alexandretta, &amp;c. : with curious remarks upon several passages re[l]ating to the Turks &amp; Maronites / written originally in Italian by the R. F. Jerome Dandini.</title>
            <title>Missione apostolica al patriarca de' Maroniti del Monte Libano. English</title>
            <author>Dandini, Girolamo, 1554-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13106003</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13106003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 413:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voyage to Mount Libanus wherein is an account of the customs, manners, &amp;c. of the Turks : also a description of Candia, Nicosia, Tripoly, Alexandretta, &amp;c. : with curious remarks upon several passages re[l]ating to the Turks &amp; Maronites / written originally in Italian by the R. F. Jerome Dandini.</title>
                  <title>Missione apostolica al patriarca de' Maroniti del Monte Libano. English</title>
                  <author>Dandini, Girolamo, 1554-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 133, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Orme for A. Roper ... and R. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Missione apostolica al patriarca de' Maroniti del Monte Libano.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maronites.</term>
               <term>Middle East --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VOYAGE TO <hi>Mount Libanus,</hi> Wherein is An Account of the Cuſtoms, Manners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a Deſcription of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Candia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nicoſia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tripoly,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Curious Remarks upon ſeveral Paſſages re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating to the <hi>Turks</hi> &amp; <hi>Maronites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written originally in <hi>Italian,</hi> by the R. F. <hi>Jerome Dandini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>J. Orme,</hi> for <hi>A. Roper</hi> at the <hi>Black Boy,</hi> and <hi>R. Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>Mitre</hi> within <hi>Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>TO <hi>William Aglionby,</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Perſon of no ſmall Character, who has left <hi>England,</hi> to make a Tour in <hi>France,</hi> was pleas'd to favour me with this Tranſlation. I thought my ſelf oblig'd, both in Juſtice and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to that Worthy Gentleman, not to confine it any longer to Manuſcript, preſuming it may reaſonably deſerve no worſe a Reception, than moſt of our Modern Travels. Nevertheleſs, being jealous of my own Opinion in things of this nature, I reſolv'd to prefix a Name that might ſhelter it from the Cavils of Some, who contemn every thing that bears the Title of a <hi>Voyage;</hi> not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the great Advantages extracted therefrom, eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> which are very uſeful, to unravel
<pb facs="tcp:199363:3"/>the Difficulties that occurr in Ancient Hiſtories. Whoſe can be ſo proper as that of the Judicious <hi>Aglionby?</hi> A ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Paſport for a leſs correct Piece than what is here offer'd.</p>
            <p>Under Your Patronage, Worthy Sir, we may ſecurely deſpiſe the Frivolous Cenſures of the Over-captious, if any there are ſo maliciouſly ill-natur'd, as to attack what You are pleas'd to protect.</p>
            <p>Your large Experience in theſe Affairs, and Your profound Judgment in matters of State, which has on many accounts ſo eminently appear'd, does indeed wholly deterr me from this Preſumption: but then the Extraordinary Candour and Goodneſs of your Temper, of which I have receiv'd ſuch Subſtantial Proofs, encourages me to indulge the Ambition I always entertain'd of demonſtrating how very much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honour'd Sir, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Obliged and moſt Devoted Humble Servant,</hi>T. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:3"/>
            <head>THE HEADS OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. I. <hi>THE Occaſion of the Voyage, and what paſſed at</hi> Rome <hi>with the Pope.</hi> Page 1</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>Journey from</hi> Rome <hi>to</hi> Venice, <hi>and from thence to</hi> Candia. 6</item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>Of the Iſle and City of</hi> Candia. 9</item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>Paſſage to</hi> Cyprus <hi>and</hi> Nicoſia, <hi>with an account of the City of</hi> Nicoſia <hi>and its Churches.</hi> 13</item>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>Of the Iſle of</hi> Cyprus. 21</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:199363:4"/>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>Our paſſage into</hi> Syria: <hi>of the City of</hi> Tripoly. 25</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>The faſhion of the Turks Habits.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>Of the Belief of the Turks.</hi> 33</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. <hi>My arrival at Mount</hi> Libanus, <hi>and how I was receiv'd by the Patriarch,</hi> &amp;c. 36</item>
               <item>Chap. X. <hi>Of the Cedars of</hi> Libanus, <hi>and the holy River, and of the nature of the Ground of Mount</hi> Libanus. 41</item>
               <item>Chap. XI. <hi>Of the Cuſtoms of the</hi> Maronites, <hi>and their manner of living.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>Chap. XII. <hi>Of their Sciences and Books, and of their Money they pay to the Turks.</hi> 48</item>
               <item>Chap. XIII. <hi>Of their Eccleſiaſticks and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>Chap. XIV. <hi>Of the Errors that have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon them.</hi> 57</item>
               <item>Chap. XV. <hi>Of the aſſembling of a Synod, and of the Profeſſion of Faith that was made there.</hi> 59</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:199363:4"/>
               <item>Chap. XVI. <hi>Of the</hi> Maronites <hi>that were to be ſent to</hi> Rome; <hi>and of thoſe that ſhould return from thence into their own Country.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>Of the Death of the Patriarch, and of the Election of another.</hi> 67</item>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>My Return from</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to</hi> Tripoly, <hi>and thence to</hi> Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dretta, <hi>with an account of</hi> Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xandretta. 71</item>
               <item>Chap. XIX. <hi>Of what happen'd to us in</hi> Cyprus. 74</item>
               <item>Chap. XX. <hi>Voyage from</hi> Cyprus <hi>to</hi> Venice. 78</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 4th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 82</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 8th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 9th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 11th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 12th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 117</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:199363:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 13th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 125</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 14th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 128</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remarks on the</hi> 17th <hi>Chapter.</hi> 132</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199363:5"/>
            <head>A VOYAGE TO Mount Libanus.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Occaſion of the Voyage, and of what paſſed at</hi> Rome <hi>with the Pope.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS I taught Philoſophy at <hi>Peruge,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbria,</hi> the <hi>F. Claudus Aquavira,</hi> our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, writ unto me, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the reſolution his Holineſs had had to ſend a faithful Perſon to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> living in <hi>Mount Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> now call'd <hi>Sorie,</hi> I had been choſen for that purpoſe; and if I found no repugnance within my ſelf to undertake that Voyage, I ſhould ſet forward as ſoon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199363:6"/>as poſſibly I could. I was gone then from <hi>Peruge</hi> to take the Air, and give ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation to my ſpirits, being reſolved to go viſit our Lady of <hi>Agnes,</hi> and ſome other Religious places adjacent to <hi>Peruge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At my return I was preſented with our Generals Letter, and when I had finiſh'd the reading of it, I render'd God thanks for his favour towards me in the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Voyage, and for the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offered me to go render my devoirs in Perſon to the glorious Sepulchre of his Son, and to other Sacred Places of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> ſince they were not far diſtant from the Place I was to be ſent unto.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I returned anſwer, That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I found ſome difficulty in the undertaking of this Voyage, principally by reaſon of a long and dangerous Navigation, as being not well accuſtomed to the Sea, yet I would purſue, with all diligence, that which was deſired of me, and put my ſelf upon the Road as ſoon as poſſibly, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be at <hi>Rome</hi> the 15th of <hi>May,</hi> for to wait upon his Holineſs, and receive his Commands; which I punctually execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For after having taken my leave of my Friends at <hi>Peruge</hi> I took Horſe, and by the way of <hi>Boligni,</hi> rendered my ſelf at <hi>Rome</hi> the day I had appointed, about two hours before Sun-ſet; inſomuch, that I had nothing to hinder my ſetting forwards on my Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney but to ſee his Holineſs, for to receive of him the neceſſary Inſtructions, and his Benediction.</p>
               <p>But as the Feaſt of Pentecoſt approach'd,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199363:6"/>and that his Holineſs was wholly taken up with thoughts of the creation of ſome Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, I was retarded ſome days at <hi>Rome,</hi> till a buſineſs ſo important to the Church was finiſhed. In the mean time, I failed not to confer with the Cardinal <hi>Paleoſe,</hi> Protector of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> and with our Father-General, who informed me of the intentions of his Holineſs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Maronites</hi> had now, for a long time paſt, been ill repreſented to the Pope and Cardinals; they were alſo accuſed of divers Errors, and conſiderable Hereſies: and thoſe of that Nation, which were then at <hi>Rome,</hi> uſed all their Efforts for to juſtifie them. But as ſome denied that which others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, the verity of their circumſtance could not be known with any certainty; however, they have been at the expence of founding of a College for them in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where they are inſtructed with much Pains and Induſtry. They have alſo ſent, not long ſince, for a conſiderable number of young <hi>Maronites,</hi> out of their own Country, the major part of whom were not yet of Age to Study; which has been very expenſive, not reckoning the hazards they run, in reſpect of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure they conceived to underſtand, that ſome of the young <hi>Maronites,</hi> ſent back laſt year, were yet without Imployments, altho they had run through all their Philoſophy, and Theology, and that the Inhabitants ſtood in great need of the like Artiſts for the eſtabliſhing of Religion, in a Country where they ſpared no Induſtry to effect it.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199363:7"/>
               <p>All which conſiderations together, moved his Holineſs to ſend into thoſe Parts a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who at his return would make him a faithful Report of the Belief of thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; who ſhould treat fairly with them, and put their Affairs into that poſture he judged convenient, conformable to the end propoſed unto him. Who ſhould regulate alſo the Age and Capacity of thoſe that ſhould be ſent, for the time to come, to the College at <hi>Rome;</hi> who ſhould give Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for their coming by ſafe ways; who ſhould find profitable and proportionable Imployments for them who were already returned, and to others that ſhould return for the future; and for that purpoſe he ſhould eſtabliſh, if it were neceſſary here, Pariſhes, wherein he might aſſign them Churches, to which they ſhould apply their Cares.</p>
               <p>The ſacred College being augmented with ſix Cardinals, by the laſt Promotion, I preſented my ſelf on the eleventh of <hi>June</hi> before his Holineſs, who received me kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: After he had given me an account of that which he would have me undertake, I promiſed to ſerve him with all Fidelity in every thing he was pleaſed to order me, and pray'd him to tell me if he would add any further Inſtructions. Moreover, as great difficulty muſt be rencountred with in the execution of what he had communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto me, particularly, for to aſſign Imployments unto them that were already returned, and that theſe difficulties would not be removed but by his Holineſs, I ſpoke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199363:7"/>to him hereof, to the end, that theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſurmounted, the way might remain free and facile, for to render the reſt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſucceſsful. I demanded of him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, what power he was pleaſed to give me amongſt the <hi>Levantines,</hi> as well to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge Caſes and Cenſures, which his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reſerved for himſelf, as to diſpence with the irregularities I ſhould rencounter with; and as I was to go into a Country adjacent to that of the Land of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> I entreated, with a profound reſpect, that his Holineſs would grant me leave to go render my devoirs to the Sepulchre of my Saviour. He gave me favourable Audience, and when I had done ſpeaking he made me anſwer: <hi>As for the Journey you deſign to make to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>we can no leſs than bear you envy, and if it were in our Power we would undertake it with all our heart! Go then, purſue it with the Grace of God, and pray for us.</hi> After I had render'd him thanks, I put him in mind of my firſt requeſt, wherein I received ſatisfaction; however, he found ſome difficulty touching a kind of irregularity to be diſpenced with, and gave me Orders to treat about it with the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal St. <hi>Severine</hi> Grand Penitenciary, who made him afterwards a report thereof, that he might determine it himſelf, whereupon I had alſo granted me a very large Power, and without Reſervations as to the matter of Irregularities. Finally, his Holineſs had the goodneſs to grant me all that I deſired, in order to facilitate this Enterprize; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I took my leave of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199363:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Journey from</hi> Rome <hi>to</hi> Venice, <hi>and from thence to</hi> Candia.</head>
               <p>THE Pope's Brief, whereof I had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, being diſpatched, I departed from <hi>Rome</hi> on the fifteenth of <hi>June</hi> for <hi>Peruge,</hi> where I arrived the ſeventeenth about Noon; the Father <hi>Fabio Bruno,</hi> who was to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany me in this Voyage, joyned me next day. On the 19th we took the way for <hi>Florence,</hi> and from thence Journying along the Mountains, we diſcovered <hi>Bolonia</hi> the 23d, <hi>Ferrara</hi> the 24th, and <hi>Venice</hi> the 26th. After we had Travelled almoſt four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Miles, I ſaw our deſign in a manner overthrown, for that having imprudently informed a Friend of this departure from <hi>Rome,</hi> who was to go to the <hi>Levant,</hi> my deſign was not only divulged at <hi>Venice,</hi> but came alſo to be known by 54 <hi>Jews;</hi> as much as to ſay, So many Spies, ſworn Enemies to Chriſtians, who were alſo bound for <hi>Smyrna,</hi> in a new Ship named <hi>Moſta.</hi> Beſides, our Fathers believing that it was dangerous for an Envoy, of the Pope, to paſs at ſuch a juncture of time into thoſe Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where the War was ſo violent between the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> writ to our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral about that matter; he returned them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That he ſeriouſly deliberated upon it,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199363:8"/>and that if there was any danger in it, we ſhould advance no further. The fruit of my Miſſion being no ways augmented ſince our arrival, I eagerly demanded Permiſſion to continue my Voyage, and to change my Ship, to the end I might perform the thing more exactly, and with as much ſecreſie as I could; all which I had granted unto me, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Information, with all diligence, of what was neceſſary for that Voyage. I changed my habit of Jeſuit into that of a Pilgrim, and made no ſeruple to take the Name of <hi>Rene Bucy,</hi> a French-man, upon me, my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion changing his for that of <hi>Fabio Daverto,</hi> a Venetian. I took along with me a young <hi>Maronite</hi> named <hi>Joſeph Eliam,</hi> for my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick and Interpreter; nevertheleſs, as our Ship protracted her departure, we reſolved to go for <hi>Padua,</hi> to pay a Viſit to ſome of our good Friends there, and to divert our ſelves with their company for two or three days.</p>
               <p>At our return from <hi>Padua,</hi> we paſſed to the Port of <hi>Malomocco,</hi> which is 18 Miles diſtant from <hi>Venice;</hi> it was there we imbark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed merrily on the 14th of <hi>July,</hi> in a Ship called the <hi>Torniell,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtina.</hi> It was a Veſſel of 900 Tun, well Mann'd, and had a brave Commander; it ſeemed probable we had no occaſion to fear any damage from the Sea or <hi>Corſairs.</hi> Nevertheleſs, we could not ſail before the 17th, for that the Weather was not auſpicious unto us. The Seamen carry'd us that ſame day out of Port, by the means of Shallops, wherein they Rowed us; but as there is nothing ſo unconſtant as the Wind, it failed us forthwith, and as we were ſolicitous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199363:9"/>to repoſe our ſelves, after all the fatigue we had had in a ſeaſon ſo hot, there happened ſo great a Calm that we could not poſſibly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance any more than 100 Miles in four days time. We had afterwards a back Wind, which helped us in a ſhort ſpace to finiſh our Voyage: We diſcovered many Iſlands and Rocks on either ſide, which we left behind in a moment; and which rendred our paſſage very delightful.</p>
               <p>We diſcovered <hi>Iſtria</hi> forthwith upon the Left, which is under the Dominion of the States of <hi>Venice,</hi> and on the Right the high Mountain of <hi>Arcona,</hi> which is on that ſide the Boundary of the Eccleſiaſtical Eſtate. A little further we perceived on the Left two inhabited Rocks, the one called <hi>Pomo,</hi> and the other St. <hi>Madre;</hi> the firſt is ſubject to none, the other is under the <hi>Venetians.</hi> There is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo on the ſame hand <hi>Buzo</hi> and <hi>Eliſa,</hi> which are inhabited by Chriſtians, and belong to the ſame <hi>Venetians.</hi> We diſcovered afterwards on the ſame ſide <hi>Gaza, Ariſta, Meleda,</hi> which belong to the Republick of <hi>Raguſa; Caſaro</hi> and <hi>Budua,</hi> ſubject to the <hi>Venetians.</hi> And we ſaw alſo, at a great diſtance, the famous City of <hi>Raguſa;</hi> further are <hi>Cluticari, Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igno, Durazzo, Saſamo, Vallona</hi> and <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marra,</hi> governed and inhabited by the <hi>Turks.</hi> A little further is alſo a Rock called <hi>Fano,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inhabited, belonging to the Signiory of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice;</hi> as well as <hi>Corfu, Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alonia, Zant, Strivalli:</hi> All theſe places are inhabited by Chriſtian <hi>Greeks.</hi> A little further we diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Navarino, Sapienza, Cavogallo</hi> and <hi>Camatapano,</hi> which are ſubject to the <hi>Turks:</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199363:9"/>And further again, upon the Left is <hi>Cerigo,</hi> and on the Right <hi>Cerigoſo,</hi> depending upon the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi> Finally, as we continued to look on that ſide, we diſcovered the Iſland of <hi>Candia,</hi> which we had longed to ſee, and where we arrived ſafe a little while after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Iſle and City of</hi> Candia.</head>
               <p>IN all the courſe of our Sailing, we caſt Anchor no where but here, and that we were obliged to do, becauſe our Ship carry'd 60 <hi>Venetian</hi> Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers which were to be put there on ſhoar; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therefore the <hi>Cape</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Cape Lion,</hi> to the South, and following the Cape <hi>Spada,</hi> which is to the North, ſometime called <hi>Cimario,</hi> we Anchored at <hi>Fraſhia</hi> on the 13th of the ſame Month, half an hour after Sun-ſet, being 8 Miles diſtant from the City of <hi>Candia,</hi> and as we were obliged to ſojourn there for ſome time, we went aſhoar next day in a Galley that came to fetch the Soldiers.</p>
               <p>This Iſle, called by the Ancients <hi>Creet,</hi> is much ſamed for its bigneſs, for it is 560 Miles in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, 250 long, and 60 Miles over where 'tis broadeſt; it is much celebrated by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, who believed, as did their Poets, that it was the Country of the Gods, and that <hi>Jupiter</hi> was Nurſed up there on <hi>Mount Ida,</hi> not to mention its famous Labyrinth, which they hold to have been near to the ancient City of <hi>Cortina,</hi> and of the excellent Laws of <hi>Rodamanthus</hi> and <hi>Minos,</hi> who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199363:10"/>governed the People after <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and founded the Republick of <hi>Creet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Iſland had once an hundred Cities, altho' <hi>Homer</hi> in his <hi>Odyſſees</hi> allows it but 90; there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains not at this day but four, which are <hi>Canea, Retimo, Candia</hi> to the Weſt, and <hi>Sittia</hi> to the Eaſt: <hi>Candea</hi> and <hi>Canea</hi> are the beſt; beſides that, there are in it two Ports, called <hi>Spina Longa,</hi> and <hi>Sude,</hi> not to ſpeak of other Places fit for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorage.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Candia</hi> ſtands in the middle of the Iſland, a dozen Miles diſtant from the Grot of <hi>Minos,</hi> and very near to <hi>Mount Ida;</hi> it is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a very great and ſpacious City, but much ruined by Earthquakes. The Houſes are almoſt all built with Gravel, yet the Buildings are not unhandſome; they have no Tiles, but there, and in all the <hi>Levant,</hi> except at <hi>Antioch,</hi> have Terraſſes of Lime, or of ſome other Matter well made, with Spouts on the ſides for to let the Water run out. Probably they uſe ſuch ſort of Buildings, becauſe they are not ſo Curious and Induſtrious as we; however, I believe they cover their Houſes in that manner out of frugality, to the end they may as well ſpread Cloth and Linnen there for to be whitened, as to ſleep in Summer Nights thereon, for the coolneſs of the Air, when the exceſſive heat hinders them to remain in their Houſes. When they would repoſe themſelves upon the Terraſs, they ſpread thereon a Mat, and ſometimes over that a Carpet, and ſleep in that manner expoſed to the Air, which is very ſweet in thoſe Parts, and no ways injurious to health. The uſe alſo of their Terraſſes, might proceed in that they have ſeldom any Rain, for there falls not often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a drop of Water for ſix Months together;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199363:10"/>and I underſtood that they had had no Rain ſince the ſecond day of <hi>February,</hi> neither did they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any till <hi>November.</hi> The Streets of that City are ſtreight, but very naſty; the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> kept a Gariſon of 2000 Soldiers about it, part of which were Poſted in a Citadel upon the Sea-ſide, and the reſt diſpoſed in other Places. There is alſo ſome Gariſon in <hi>Canea.</hi> The reſt of the Inhabitants are almoſt all <hi>Greeks,</hi> amongſt whom there remains yet ſome noble <hi>Venetians,</hi> for that <hi>Boniface,</hi> Marquis of <hi>Montferat,</hi> having ſold them that Iſland in the Year 1194. they tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported thither ſome Families of the Nobility, and Citizens, for to inhabit the Place. It was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards retaken in 1349. after a Revolt, and ſince that time they have enjoyed it peaceably. The Country is very Mountanous, and almoſt Barren; one can ſee there alſo but few Trees and Herbs, but yet it follows not but that it hath Plains of many Miles extent, fertile in Grain, Trees, Olives, Oranges, Lemons, and all other ſort of Commodities: Moreover, there grow Berries for to dry Cloth withal, much Wax there is, and Honey, Cheeſe, and Medicinal Herbs; ſo that 'tis very good Living there. There is alſo a great quantity of excellent Wines, whereof the moſt eſtimable is <hi>Muſcadine,</hi> inſomuch that thoſe that know it not take it for <hi>Malmſey,</hi> but they are miſtaken, for it comes from a little Iſland that bears the Name of it. The goodneſs of the Wines of <hi>Candia</hi> renders the Natives great Drunkards; and it happens ſometimes, that two or three great Drinkers will ſet themſelves at the head of a Tun of Wine, from whence they will not ſtir till they have emptied it. There is no venemous Animal to be found in that Country, ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199363:11"/>that they are not afraid of Scorpions, Serpents, Toads; neither can you ſee there a Wolf, Tyger, nor any other the like Beaſt, ſo that they live there in great repoſe both Night and Day. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of approved Faith have told me a remarkable thing there, which hath alſo been written of by good Authors; to wit, That there is growing upon <hi>Mount Ida,</hi> which hath been ſhewed me at a diſtance, an Herb whoſe Vertue was to gild the Teeth of thoſe Animals that eat of it: one may believe, and with good reaſon, that that proceeds from the golden Mines which are in that ground. There grows alſo a certain Herb called <hi>Alincos,</hi> which being bitter, preventeth ones being hungry for a whole day; but that which is wonderfully ſurprizing, and beyond the force of Nature, are certain pieces of Money which they call St. <hi>Helens,</hi> that are found up and down the Fields, where there is alſo Braſs, and other Silver. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that that Saint happening to be in that Country without Money, made ſome of Braſs, which in paſſing of them changed into Silver; this Money, they ſay, hath the vertue to this day, to cure the Falling-Sickneſs in them that hold it to their Hand, or apply it to their Fleſh.</p>
               <p>The Cuſtom of the Women of this Iſland, is not to go out of their Houſes in the day time; no, not to go hear Maſs or Sermon: nevertheleſs they run in great Troops along the Streets all Night, and for the moſt part with Men, enter into the Churches which they leave open on purpoſe for them. This Cuſtom is blame-worthy, not only becauſe theſe Women perform not their Duties towards God, but alſo, becauſe it is againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and good Manners; for it would be a far more laudable thing for them to go civilly by Day
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199363:11"/>to Church, than tumultuouſly in the Night Seaſon.</p>
               <p>I ſhould have work to do to reckon up all the Impurities of the Prelates, Prieſts, and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks of this Nation; their Separation from the <hi>Latine</hi> Church, their Maledictions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications they fulminate upon the moſt ſanctified Days againſt it, when we pray for their Welfare. I ſhall alſo ſay nothing of their Right, Pride, Obſtinacy, Defection of Faith, of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to Treat with them, of their Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Superſtitions, horrible and continual Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, which cannot be heard without horror. Finally, St. <hi>Paul</hi> had reaſon to ſay according to one of their own Poets, <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Creet <hi>are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Lyars; they are wicked Beaſts, Gluttons, and Lazy.</hi> The 8 days I ſtaid in this Town would have been very weariſome unto me, becauſe of the exceſſive and continual heats, if we had not received ſome relaxation from the Charity and agreeable Converſation of the Fathers <hi>Benedelto Benedetto,</hi> and <hi>Franciſco Paroſchetti,</hi> of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, who reſided there at that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Paſſage to</hi> Cyprus <hi>and</hi> Nicoſia, <hi>with an Account of the City of</hi> Nicoſia <hi>and its Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE parted from <hi>Candia</hi> the 8th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> two hours before day, in a little Frigat, for to go on board our Ship, into which we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred at Sun-riſing; ſome time after we weighed
<pb facs="tcp:199363:12"/>Anchor and ſailed. The Wind was favourable unto us in paſſing by the Iſle, which we left to the Right; then we entred into the Gulph of <hi>Settalia,</hi> a dangerous place for ſailing, and ſo continuing our courſe through that Gulph, we diſcovered on the Left <hi>Caſſo</hi> and <hi>Scarpanto,</hi> which are Inhabited by <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and depending upon the laſt. We left alſo on the ſame hand <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and all <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramania,</hi> without yet being able to ſee them, for we were too far wide; that was alſo the reaſon, that after we had run for three Days and three Nights without the ſight of Land, that we arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the 12th of <hi>August</hi> at <hi>Cyprus.</hi> We An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored in the Evening at <hi>Lemiſo,</hi> where the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, particularly the <hi>Turks,</hi> made a viſit to our Ship; we were there 3 days on board, for that there was nothing in that place worth the ſeeing, and no Church for to do our Devotion in.</p>
               <p>We parted about Twelve on the 16th for <hi>Sali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> whither a good Wind brought us in a ſhort time, and we arrived there two hours before Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetting; from thence to <hi>Candia</hi> is about 600 Miles. Next day, very early, we went aſhoar, and on directly to <hi>Arnique,</hi> which is not paſt a Mile di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; 'tis a Monaſtery of Religious <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who live there in a ſmall number for the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of ſome <hi>Italian</hi> Merchants. Our Ship continued its courſe for <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> the which obliged us to ſee for another Veſſel to paſs for <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and as we could not obtain that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, we ſojourned ſome days in that Iſle. That I might loſe no time I left my Companion, who had been conſtantly indiſpoſed ſince we came from <hi>Candia,</hi> in the hands of theſe good Religious; and the <hi>Maronite</hi> that we brought along with us, and I, accompanied an honeſt <hi>Venetian</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199363:12"/>who lived in thoſe Parts, and were going to <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> anciently called <hi>Lettra,</hi> ſince <hi>Lencolto,</hi> and which was ſometime the Archbiſhoprick and Metropolis of this Kingdom; 'tis 24 Miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Arnique.</hi> I undertook this Journey for to inform my ſelf, as well as poſſibly I could, of the Spiritual Concerns of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> which are there in great numbers.</p>
               <p>There are none but <hi>Turks</hi> that have liberty to enter thereunto on Horſeback, and to all other ſtrong Places: As for the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and others, they are obliged to alight at the Gate, and when they are within, they have power to re-mount their Horſes, and ride to their Lodgings. The <hi>Turks</hi> have made this Order out of meer vanity: I entred then into the Town, and that <hi>Venetian</hi> Merchant did me the favour to conduct me with him into his Lodging; having refreſhed my ſelf a little after the fatigues of the Road, I went to ſee that which was worth viewing, and particularly the Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicoſia</hi> is a large and very fair City, built af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Eaſtern faſhion, but it is ruined in divers places, becauſe of the late Wars, for the <hi>Turks</hi> have taken it by force of Arms from the <hi>Venetians,</hi> together with the reſt of the Iſle. Some years ago it was ſo, that God, by his Juſtice, was willing to puniſh the Sins and Schiſm of the <hi>Greeks</hi> in thoſe places. They adored there formerly, with much veneration, the Holy Trinity, but now, to the great regret of all good Chriſtians, you can hear but the impious Invocation of the falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet.</hi> They had ſometime there Churches and Altars raiſed to the honour of good Saints, but inſtead of them there is nothing now but Moſques, amongſt which ſtands ſtill that grand and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199363:13"/>Temple of St. <hi>Sophie.</hi> There is no ſound of Bells to be heard in all the <hi>Levant,</hi> for to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Divine Worſhip, according to ancient Cuſtom, and of the hours of the Day, for the Steeples are either ruined, or without Bells; the <hi>Turks</hi> have taken them for Warlike Uſes, and made Pieces of Artillery of them. Inſtead then of the confuſed and inanimate ſound of Bells, they are ſerved with the diſtinct and animate Voices of Men, who at certain appointed hours mount up to the tops of the Steeples, for to give the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants notice. This manner of obſerving their hours, is in uſe in all the <hi>Levant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is at <hi>Nicoſia</hi> 4 ſort of Churches, which I have ſeen all in particular. The Turkiſh Moſques are the moſt conſiderable, as well for number, as for the beauties and grandeur of their Buildings; altho' Chriſtians are not ſuffered to enter into them, yet I failed not to ſee through the Iron Grates, that that which hath been made of the Temple of St. <hi>Sophia</hi> was the principal and moſt magnificent of them all; 'tis a large and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Fabrick, which has many Pillars in it, as may be ſeen in moſt of our Churches; it had no Altars, Images, nor Paintings, the Walls were only whited. There is at the Door of this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a delicate Fountain, which was not there in the time of the Chriſtians; the <hi>Turks</hi> waſh therein the crowns of their Heads, Hands and Feet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enter into the Moſque, at the ordinary hours, and particularly in the Afternoon, at which time theſe Villains invoke their falſe Prophet, and cry without meaſure, <hi>Halla, Halla, Chibir, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemme Sur Halla;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>God is a great God,</hi> Mahomet <hi>is the Companion of God;</hi> with many other Fooleries and Blaſphemies. Thoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199363:13"/>who aſſiſt not with the reſt at theſe Publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, pray in particular in their Houſes, if they be of Quality, or in other places where they are. They roul themſelves at Noon-tide upon a Mat or Carpet. There are alſo other hours wherein they are called to Prayers, <hi>i. e.</hi> at 3 a Clock, an hour before Sun-ſet, an hour before Day, at Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing; and, in ſhort, 7 times Day. Obſerve their manner of praying, as I my ſelf have oftentimes ſeen them in their private Houſes: As ſoon as ever they come upon the Mat or Carpet, they turn themſelves round, then incline their Bodies, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their Thumbs that part of the Head which is behind the Ears, and they riſe themſelves ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times all of a ſudden, touching the Earth with their Hands; they fall ſometimes upon their knees, or rather ſland upon their heels, and beat the ground lightly with their Forehead, and having got up again upon their feet, they hold their hands mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly upon their Breaſt, repeating their Prayers with caſt-down Looks, and ſpeak between their Teeth. They recite them all along, inclining their Bodies interchangeably towards the Earth, and touching it with their Forehead; then they riſe up, and falling down anew, they continue to reſt for ſome time upon their heels, with their Legs a-croſs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Greeks</hi> have another ſort of Church, of which I ſhall obſerve only; That if a <hi>Latin</hi> Prieſt ſhould celebrate Maſs therein, they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all the Water in the Ocean was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to cleanſe it, ſo much they waſh the Altar, and all the Church alſo, from a belief they have that a <hi>Latin</hi> Service renders it impure and profane. Their uſage in the Conſecration of the Bread, and their other Rights, are very well known; they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199363:14"/>as great enemies to the <hi>Latins</hi> as the <hi>Turks.</hi> That honeſt Merchant, with whom I Lodged, told me, That they refuſed Abſolution to one of his Domeſticks, a <hi>Greek</hi> by Nation, becauſe he ſerv'd a <hi>Franck,</hi> for ſo they call all thoſe that follow the <hi>Latin</hi> Rights. It will not be beſides my purpoſe, to render here an Account of another of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, the matter happening to the ſame Man, who being confeſſed for an ordinary and common ſin, was by his Confeſſor refuſed Abſolution, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, He could not do it without the conſent of 7 other Prieſts; this buſineſs being effected with a little Money, they ſtretched the Penitent upon the ground as if he had been dead, and at length granted him Abſolution in reciting of certain Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers over him, they made uſe of to that purpoſe. They are wont to demand Money for Abſolution, and will refuſe it when they cannot obtain the Sum, for they pretend they have 5 or 6 Crowns due to them for abſolving common and ordinary ſins. The Penance which they enjoyn for very great ſins, is to forbid 'em to communicate for 4 or 5 years; perhaps they may do this out of a contempt and averſion they may have for the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, which orders it once a year: the which is ſo much the more eaſily credited, ſeeing they make certain Plays, wherein is introduc'd a <hi>Latin</hi> Perſonage, to whom are offered an hundred injuries, as daſhing him on the face, and ſeveral other the like outrages.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Latins</hi> have their but a ſmall Church, or rather Chapel, which is well maintained, and has a Prieſt of Age and Wealth for a Paſtor, but very ignorant. The <hi>Italian</hi> Merchants who live there ſupply 'em with Food and Raiment, and furniſh 'em alſo with Sacred Ornaments. Finally, The <hi>Maron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes</hi> have their Church there alſo, which is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199363:14"/>in ſo poor a condition, that I really pity'd them. In order to know what was their Right, as that of other Places of the Iſle, where they were diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I addreſs'd my ſelf indifferently to the <hi>Italians, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Maronites;</hi> I learn'd they had all one and the ſame Right common to all their Nation, that they all lived under the ſame Patriarch. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that the Places where they lived conſiſted in 19 Villages, which are <hi>Motoſic, Fludi, Santa-Marina, Oſomates, Ganſili, Carpaſia, Cormachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Primiſia, Caſapifani, Veno, Cibo, Jeri</hi> near <hi>Cittria, Crenſada, Attala, Cleipirio, Piſcopia, Gasbria, Cefalanriſeo,</hi> and <hi>Sotto Cruſcida;</hi> that in every one of theſe Places they have at leaſt one Pariſh, and in ſome 2 or 3, with one Prieſt, or more. And I was aſſured that they had eight Churches at <hi>Metoſic,</hi> and that the Prieſts were very aſſiduous in their Duty, being not much oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied with their own particular Concerns. That Nation hath alſo ordinarily a Biſhop in that place, but he was then dead, and they had not yet elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another.</p>
               <p>There is in the Kingdom a <hi>Greek</hi> Biſhop, who is the General-Receiver of the Tributes which the others are obliged to pay to the <hi>Turks;</hi> they drein each every Year of 70 Aſpers. The Janiſaries will not ſpare to beſtow the Baſtinado on thoſe that pay not; and the Biſhop is no more exempt than the reſt, purſuant to the information of the Receiver. He requires beſides, 15 or 20 Ducats of every Prieſt that is put into Orders. See the miſerable Eſtate the Chriſtians are reduced to who are ſubject to the <hi>Turks,</hi> altho' there be leſs <hi>Turks</hi> there than <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for of 30000 Inhabitants that are in <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> and upwards, ſcarce is there 4 or 5000 of them that are <hi>Turks,</hi> and there is not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199363:15"/>above 12 or 13000 in all the Iſland, the greateſt part of whom are Renegades, who turn <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> for to render their Lives more eaſie and ſupportable; ſo that it ſeems an eaſie matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover this Iſle from under the Tyranny of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and re-eſtabliſh it in the Chriſtian Faith, for the Renegades could no ſooner ſee the Chriſtian Soldiers, but they would throw off their Turbants and put on Hats inſtead, and turn their Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> But we will leave this, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our ſubject.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtians, whether <hi>Greeks</hi> or <hi>Franks,</hi> do not wear a Turbant, nor ſhave their Heads, but they cut their hair genteelly as we do, and wear upon their Heads an Hat, or black Bonnet. They cloath themſelves, nevertheleſs, according to the manner of the <hi>Levantines,</hi> with a Reſt without a Collar, which reaches down to the Knees, with large Sleeves reaching to the Elbows. They gird themſelves with a Linnen Cloth, or ſome other the like Girdle, which comes 3 or 4 turns about. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Veſt they have another Garment over a firſt, reaching from their Necks down to their Legs; and above all, another Veſt without a Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and cut almoſt after the ſame faſhion as the firſt: they wear them ordinarily of a black, or violet colour, or elſe of ſome other colour which pleaſeth them beſt. We will ſpeak hereafter more particularly of the Habits of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites,</hi> and of their Cuſtoms, but now it remains we ſhould deſcribe the nature of the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199363:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Iſle of</hi> Cyprus.</head>
               <p>THis Iſle is at leaſt 480 Miles about, 80 Miles broad, and 200 in length, and hath two Capes; that on the Weſt comprehends the Cape of St. <hi>Epiphany,</hi> which the Ancients called <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mante,</hi> and the Cape of <hi>Srapano,</hi> or <hi>la Pointeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conta,</hi> or the Cape <hi>Zephiro;</hi> the other is called St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> from whence you paſs into the Eaſt, it has no other Port on the Eaſt-ſide but <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta,</hi> it is a famous Town which hath been built by <hi>Ptolomy Philadelphus.</hi> The great Ships are ſafe, nevertheleſs on the Coaſts of <hi>Raffo, Simiſo, Salines, Craſoco,</hi> and <hi>Cerines.</hi> There are in divers places more Capes, which are ſomewhat advanced into the Sea, the moſt conſiderable of which is the Cape of <hi>Cats,</hi> ſo called from a great number of Cats which they bred there in the Monaſtery of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> where live the Religious Order of St. <hi>Baſil;</hi> they have put in theſe Cats, for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a great number of Serpents which breed there, and there is a conſiderable Revenue left for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>This Iſland had once very many fair Cities, but has none now, ſaving <hi>Nicoſia</hi> and <hi>Famaguſta,</hi> who retain ſomewhat of that ancient Grandeur; all the reſt are Villages, there is none of them inhabited by the ancient Nobility, for they are either entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinct, or are retired elſewhere ſince the <hi>Turks</hi> have made themſelves Maſters of it; the famous Mountain of <hi>Olympus</hi> is almoſt in the midſt, very near to <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> it is very high, and 54 Miles in circumference, and at every 4 Miles end there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199363:16"/>a Monaſtery of thoſe Monks of whom we ſhall ſpeak hereafter, with delicate Springs, and Fruit in abundance: The Air there is very agreeable, and is never ſo cold, in the extremity of Winter, that one has need of warming, but the heat is ſo incommodious, both night and day, that 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to travel in the day time.</p>
               <p>There is every where in this Iſle fine Fields filled with Fruits, as well on the Mountains as on the Plains, which renders the Country fertile and plentiful; wherefore it has been called <hi>Macaria,</hi> from a Greek word which ſignifies <hi>Happy.</hi> The Ancients had reaſon to ſay it was the Country of <hi>Venus,</hi> and to give <hi>Venus</hi> the name of <hi>Cypriana,</hi> and to the Iſle that of <hi>Cytherca;</hi> for 'tis not only ſaid that ſhe was born at <hi>Aphroditium,</hi> and brought up at <hi>Cytherca,</hi> but that ſhe reigned at <hi>Idalium,</hi> called at this day <hi>Dalli,</hi> 12 Miles from <hi>Nicoſia</hi> Southwards: Hence it comes that they Sacrificed naked Men and Women to <hi>Venus</hi> at <hi>Paffo,</hi> which was ſometime built by <hi>Agapenor</hi> General to the Army of <hi>Agament</hi> King of <hi>Micenes.</hi> This abuſe ceaſed, when the Temple was demoliſhed at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Barnabas.</hi> There is near unto the Cape of St. <hi>Epiphany</hi> two famous Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, one of which is called the <hi>Amorous Fountain,</hi> becauſe that thoſe who drink of its Water grow paſſionately in Love; and the other quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe it extinguiſheth this paſſion in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>This Iſle abounds in Wheat as well as Wine, and other excellent Viands, and ſupplieth other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; the Sun and Soil render the Wines very ſtrong and agreeable, but after they are put into pitched Veſſels, they receive ſuch a guſt as is not pleaſing to thoſe that are not accuſtomed thereto,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199363:16"/>nevertheleſs all agree they are good for the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. You will find there all manner of Pulſe in abundance, Barley, Dates, Mulberries, Oranges, Lemons, Citrons, and all other Fruits, except Cherries, Cheſnuts, and Sorb-Apples. There is no want of Sugar, Saffron, Coriander, Seſamum, Lintell-ſeed, Honey, and ſometimes Manna; the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bean, the Herb whoſe aſhes ſerves to make Sous, and that with which they waſh Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and other Cloths. There may be had Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, Turpentine, and Scamony, and other things that are valuable: There are alſo Veins of Gold, Copper, Marcaſite, Latten, and of Iron, Roach-Allom, Pitch, Roſin, Sulphur, and Salt-Petre; and beſides, you may have there the Berry where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they Dye Scarlet; as alſo Coral, the Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald, Chryſtal Diamonds, and other precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>There are no great Rivers in all the Iſland, but only Brooks and Rivolets. There is a little River runs very near unto <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> wherein are a great quantity of Jaſpers, which have the vertue, as is known, to ſtop bloud. Beſides, there is ſo great a quantity of Cotton, that the Inhabitants not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cloath themſelves, and make all ſorts of Cloths therewith, but they furniſh alſo <hi>Italy,</hi> and other Parts; 'tis that which makes their principal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues. They alſo gain conſiderable profit by white Salt, which they get from a fair Salt-Pit of ſweet Water and Rain. This Salt-Pit is at leaſt ten Miles about, and 'tis an admirable thing to view all that vaſt Campaign, which appears as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Snow; there is in the midſt a Pit that never freezeth, altho' all the Salt-Pit is congealed. There may be ſeen alſo whole Fields, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath enriched with Capers without the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199363:17"/>of cultivating, and every one has the liberty to take as many as he pleaſes. Their Mutton is very good Meat, their Sheep are large and fat, and have a prodigious Tail, which yet is no longer than thoſe of our Country, but is at leaſt half a foot broad, and ſo thick, that it appears round; it hangs behind, and beats always their ſides as they go along. Their Goats have Ears hanging downwards, and 3 fingers in breath, their Horns are a little more elevated than ours, and their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head more ſhort, which gives them a greater grace and hardineſs; they have alſo a tuft of hair in the midſt of their Forehead. It will be hard to believe a thing I have experimented, which is, That I have not ſeen in this Kingdom, nor any part of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> any Animal, whether Horſe, Mule, or Aſs, which trotting joulted his Rider; they all go lightly and eaſie, and Men are accuſtomed to ride their Horſes there without Bridle, Saddle, Stirrup, or Spurs, an Halter ſufficeth them, with a little Clout ſpread upon the back of the Beaſt. Finally, we may ſay, That this Iſle aboundeth with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies: Before they became ſubject to the <hi>Turks,</hi> they lived ſplendidly, and in freedom, but ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual. It produced formerly divers illuſtrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, performing great Services to their Country, and who have been very commendable for their Knowledge and Piety, <hi>viz. Aſclebiades</hi> the Hiſtorian, <hi>Solon</hi> one of the 7 Sages of <hi>Greece, Evagoras, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lobuia, Kenon</hi> of <hi>Cittia,</hi> Author of the Sect of the Stoicks, <hi>Apollonias</hi> the Phyſician, <hi>Xenophon</hi> the Hiſtorian; and beſides theſe, the Apoſtle St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> his Couſin, <hi>Epapheroditus, Paul Sergius, Titus, Nicanor, Epyphanus,</hi> and divers others.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199363:17"/>
               <p>This Kingdom hath been from time to time ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſeveral Maſters; it were too tedious to make a repetition of its Changes and Revolutions. <hi>Selim,</hi> Sultan of the <hi>Turks,</hi> took it by force in the Year 1570. with an Army of 200000 Men: But enough of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> we paſs now into <hi>Syria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Our paſſage into</hi> Syria: <hi>Of the City of</hi> Tripoly.</head>
               <p>I Loſt all the time I had imploy'd in this Iſle, to ſearch for a conveniency to paſs into <hi>Syria,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that I was conſtrained to go for <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta,</hi> in order to be tranſported hither. We parted from <hi>Saline</hi> on the 27th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and having a good Wind we made ready by Noon, and ſteered our courſe for <hi>Tripoly,</hi> where we arrived two days after very early, for this traverſe is not above 150 Miles, but it was more incommodious unto us than all the reſt of the Vovage, becauſe we were on board a very ſmall Veſſel. We might have gone off ſooner, had it not been for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of our Seamen, who retarded our departure, inſomuch that we were forced to caſt Anchor the ſecond day, 7 or 8 Miles from Port, being harraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all night with a Tempeſt, and yet we durſt not ſail for fear of falling upon ſome Rock, as we would unavoidably have done, if we had weighed Anchor in the night; 'tis certain it was a dangerous night, but having got a Wind on break of day, we arrived in a ſhort time at the Port of <hi>Tripoly,</hi> which is fortify'd with 5 fair Towers ranged on the ſhoar. Altho' I was much indiſpoſed, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199363:18"/>cruel Sea-ſick, having eat little or nothing for ten days, I found my ſelf much recovered as ſoon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ever I ſet foot on Land. Having cauſed my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to be mounted on a little Aſs, I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go on foot to <hi>Tripoly,</hi> which was two Miles diſtant from the place we were at; the Sun was already far advanced in the Horizon, when I began to ſet forward on my way, and its beams were exceeding violent in that Country, where 'tis alſo hot all the night, however I failed not to divert my ſelf to ſee 50 or 60 Camels paſs along conducted by the <hi>Arabs,</hi> who are a black and cruel Nation. Theſe Camels carry Aſhes, which they make of a certain Herb that is burnt in thoſe Parts. They lay them in great heaps in certain Pits, wherein they are hardened, and furniſh hereby <hi>Venice,</hi> and moſt part of <hi>Europe,</hi> with a great quantity of Matter to make very fine Glaſſes. I took alſo much pleaſure to view a green Field, which might have been taken for a great and ſpacious Garden, ſo well was it filled with Mulberry and Orange-Trees, of an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſmell, not to ſpeak of many other Fruit-Trees, which are as common there as Elms, Poplars, Cheſnut and Wallnut-Trees, with us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tripoly</hi> is ſituated at the foot of a Mountain in ſight of the Sea; there is about it a Fortreſs upon a Rock, that commands it intirely. This City abounds in many things, and is full of Traffick; it's principal Commodity is Silk, Spun Cotton, Raiſons, Soap, Tallow Candles, which are there made very good. There is at leaſt 500 <hi>Jews</hi> in that Town, for the moſt part <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſe,</hi> crafty in the way of Trade, always ready to cheat the <hi>Christians,</hi> particularly the <hi>Italian</hi> Merchants, who are there but a few, ſince
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199363:18"/>the <hi>Venetians</hi> quitted thoſe Parts, and fail for <hi>Scandaroon.</hi> They have no other Church there but a little Chapel, which is in one of their Houſes, and for the moſt part have no Prieſt to officiate therein. There you may find abundance of <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Maronites,</hi> the firſt of which live in the Town, the other Lodge without in a ſmall Village that is above it; the <hi>Turks</hi> are there in greater numbers than any other Nation, and wear a white Turbant; the <hi>Jews</hi> have ordinarily a red Bonnet half a foot high, flat and round; the <hi>Italian Christians</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> wear an Hat, or black Bonnet; the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> a ſtreaked Turbant, or Bonnet, of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent form, that of the <hi>Jews.</hi> They all wore formerly a Turbant with this ſole difference, That the <hi>Turks</hi> had a white, the <hi>Jews</hi> a yellow, and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> a ſtriped one; but the abuſe crept amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who began to wear ſuch great ones, as if they ſeemed willing to cope in grandeur with the great <hi>Ottoman</hi> Seigniors, wherefore it has been ſo ordered, that none but <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould wear the Turbant. The <hi>Jews,</hi> by reaſon hereof, have diſcontinued it intirely; the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have not the right one, but content themſelves to have upon their Bonnets ſome turns of a ſtriped cloth, in form of a Turbant. There are alſo many <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Arabs</hi> of mean condition, who do the ſame thing with white Stuff. We Lodged with a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Merchant, who was a rich Man, and knew our company in a more particular manner; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us with much charity and civility, he put my companion, who was ſick, upon a Bed forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and cauſed him to be ſerved with every thing neceſſary for him. I went into the Cuſtom-Houſe for to take out that which I had brought from <hi>Italy,</hi> part whereof was to be preſented to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199363:19"/>Patriarch of the <hi>Maronites</hi> on behalf of the Pope, and the reſt to be diſtributed amongſt their Churches; the whole conſiſted of ſome Caſes, one whereof was filled with Church Ornaments, and a Patriarchal Veſt made all of Cloth of Gold and Silver of great value. I did all that ever I could to haſten my Journey to <hi>Mount Libanus,</hi> for there was but 20 Miles from <hi>Tripoly</hi> to the place where the Patriarch made his reſidence, but I was obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſojourn there for three days, in which time I obſerved that Oxen carried burdens upon their backs like Camels, Mules and Aſſes, as Wood, or any other neceſſary Commodity; inſomuch, that Saying ſeemed to me no longer true,
<q>
                     <hi>Optat Ephippia bos piger, Optat arare caballus.</hi>
                  </q> However I know full well, that they Till their ground with Horſes in a great part of <hi>France,</hi> the which they practiſed alſo then in <hi>Syria,</hi> becauſe of a certain diſtemper that had almoſt deſtroyed all their Oxen. I was obliged to ſhut my ſelf in the Houſe for moſt part of the day, not daring to be known in that Country, nevertheleſs I was very deſirous to inform my ſelf of their Cuſtoms, and Manner of Living. I mounted in the evening up the Terraſs for to take the Air, and view the Town as well as I could; I perceived the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Women upon the Terraſſes of the Neighbouring Houſes, and eaſily comprehended by that, that the place where <hi>David</hi> ſaw <hi>Berſheba</hi> was but a Terraſs of the ſame faſhion as that on the top of the Houſe, and there is much appearance that theſe ſort of Terraſſes were in uſe at that time. I will ſpeak no more of the other particulars I obſerved in that City, both at this time, and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199363:19"/>other I was obliged to return back this way, for that I am unwilling to interrupt my Hiſtory of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> which ought ſpeedily to follow, but I will firſt exhibit ſomewhat I have ſeen and learnt of the manner of the Living of the <hi>Turks</hi> in that Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Faſhion of the</hi> Turks <hi>Habits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Turks</hi> ſhave all their hair, yet there are many of them who leave ſome growing on the crown of their heads, which makes a kind of a Tuft; they do not ſhave their Beards at all, but caſt off the ends only of that on the upper Lip: long Beards are much in eſteem amongſt them, and the longer and larger they be, the more eſtimable are they. Wherefore 'tis one of the greateſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces that can be made to any one, to threaten him with the cutting off of his Beard, altho' this threat is ordinary enough amongſt them. They wear upon their head a Bonnet, which they call <hi>Takia,</hi> and which is made of cloth or ſilk inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd with cotton, and place very neatly at the top a long and fine cloth of white cotton, which they call <hi>Seſta;</hi> whereof they make a great or ſmall Turbant, according to the quality of the Perſon. Thoſe who are above others, in reſpect of Birth or Dignity, carry a great one; and there are ſome who have them of an exceſſive bigneſs. Their Sifts, as well as other Veſts, are made without Collars, and for the moſt part of white cotton; there are ſome who wear blue ones, with very
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199363:20"/>wide ſleeves, inſomuch that all the Arm ſeems al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt naked. The lower part of their Sifts is not at all wide, at leaſt they ſeem as ſowed together at the end when they wear no Drawers, and for that purpoſe they make them large. Their Veſts ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily are a little longer, and hang almoſt down to the ground. The Vulgars wear commonly white, or of ſome other colour, but ſeldom black and green, perhaps becauſe the <hi>Francks</hi> wear ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily black, and that green is the colour of them of the Race of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who they ſay was uſed to be dreſs'd in that colour. Hence it comes, that none but thoſe of his Race wear a green Turbant, or a ſmall piece of that colour faſtened to the white. The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> dare not have their Cloaths, Bonnet, or any other thing, about them of that colour; they have two Veſts, the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt has a Girdle to tie about it, and the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt is the <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Abb:</hi> they call it the <hi>Spain</hi> when the cloth is made of fine Wooll, and well wrought, as with us in <hi>Italy,</hi> for they are not ſo induſtrious as we in thoſe Countries. The <hi>Abb</hi> is more ſlightly woven, and conſiſts of courſer Wooll, 'tis ſtriped, and divided with long and broad black and white ſtreaks. The Girdle of the nether Veſt is made of thick narrow Linnen cloth, about three fingers broad, and long enough to come two or three turns about, or of a leathern ſtring; one may ſee ſome of theſe Girdles made of very fine ſilk, and curiouſly wrought. They co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Legs with large Drawers, which are made of fine Linnen cloth or ſtuff, and deſcend down to the Feet, which are naked, in Shoes of black Leather, or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Goats leather of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther colour, particularly red, blue, and yellow, to the end they may waſh themſelves with greater
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199363:20"/>facility before their Prayers. The form of their Shoes differ not from ours, but that they are not ſo neat and handſome, and have an higher in-ſtep; there is a little piece of Leather, two or three fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers long, that ſerves for a ſtring, faſtened on each ſide to the ears of the Shoes, with a button in the middle. But their Slippers are much unlike to ours, they wear them with Shoes and without; you cannot know them to be Slippers they are ſo much like unto Shoes, unleſs they cover leſs of the feet before, for they do no more but hide the Toes, and turn upwards very much; moreover their ſides are not ſo high as thoſe of the Shoes, and under the Sole they place, inſtead of a Heel a little piece of Iron in form of a creſcent, which ſerves inſtead of leather, and makes much noiſe in going. They wear no Hats to defend themſelves from the Rain, but have a piece of ſtuff extended over their Turbant, which is done ſo handſomly, that when 'tis gathered at the top, and enlarged below, you would take it for a Monks Hood; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they make uſe, againſt the Rain, of a long Cloak ſlightly made in the Country, which keeps out the water very well; it hangs down as far as the middle of their Leg, and together with their Hood upon the Turbant, ſerves them not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in travelling, but alſo in the Town. Thoſe which have none of this ſort, wear a good thick Cloth, which hath long and large ſleeves; others are content with their <hi>Abb,</hi> which alſo keeps out the Rain.</p>
               <p>The Women wear alſo Sifts, Veſts, Drawers, Shoes and Slippers, ſaving that inſtead of the <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Abb,</hi> they have a Veſt ſomewhat ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than that of the Men. They wear upon their head a toque of cloth or ſilk, ordinarily red or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199363:21"/>blue, which they adorn with work of gold and ſilver; their hair being gathered into Treſſes, hang beind their ſhoulders, bound with Ribbon, or ſome other ſtuff; you cannot ſee it curled at top with them, nor any the like vanity; their Countenance appears natural, and without paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they wear Rings, Pendants in their Ears, Bracelets, wherein there is ſome Medley or other, as poliſh'd Iron, or Pewter, or Latten, or a good quantity of Gold and Silver, according to the quality of the Woman and her condition. Theſe Bracelets are 3 or 4 fingers broad, and are not compoſed of divers Rings, as ours, but of one Plate of Metal with but little form; and they not only wear them about their Arms, but alſo Legs, near to their feet, not that they can be ſeen in the Streets dreſs'd in this manner, for when they go out of their Houſes, they wrap themſelves ſo cloſe up in a linnen or cotton Cloth, that thoſe that look upon them cannot ſee as much as their hands, altho' they are allowed the liberty of their Arm and Hand. Yet their faces are no more ſeen, for they are ſo careful to hide them with a black or white Cloth, that there remains only but a little cleft before their eyes for them to ſee through. Sometimes they cover their faces with black Crape very tranſparent, through which they can ſee others, without being ſeen themſelves. This is the manner of the Womens going abroad, be they <hi>Jews, Greeks, Syrians,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> that they may the more conveniently go along the Streets. When they be wet or dirty, they wear Buskins of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Goats-leather, which reach up as far as the knee, and ſo tucking up their cloaths on each ſide, they paſs through without being at all wet, or bedaubed with dirt. The <hi>Maronites</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199363:21"/>have other Cuſtoms, of which we ſhall ſpeak hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the Belief of the</hi> Turks.</head>
               <p>ONE need not doubt but that thoſe Hearts, which have not the true Worſhip of God, nor the Knowledge of his Faith, have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled Vertue for to repleniſh themſelves with all manner of Vice; 'tis this which I have manifeſtly known amongſt theſe Nations, who indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that our Lord was an Holy Man, and a great Prophet, which makes them honour the place of his Birth, and burn Lamps there, as may be ſeen ſtill at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> but they believe not that he was God, nor the Son of God, neither will they believe he died upon the Croſs, for they ſay he ſubſtituted another in his place, and for that purpoſe withdrew himſelf from the hands of the <hi>Jews,</hi> paſſing through a hole, or large cranny, which was above the place where he was retired that night for to pray, and that he appeared not ſince that time. They worſhip no other but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> whom they pretend to be a greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and it were ſcarce credible with what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and magnificence they guard his Tomb at <hi>Meccha,</hi> what expence they are at to receive em that come to viſit it, and in what degree of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they are held who perform this Pilgrimage, particularly thoſe who are born by the way. They bear all the name of <hi>Scerif,</hi> which ſignifies great Saint; they alſo, as all other Nations, have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199363:22"/>Prieſts, which they call <hi>Santons,</hi> taking for that purpoſe the moſt zealous obſervers of their Law, altho' the beſt of them are no leſs vicious than the reſt. This is the ceremony they obſerve at the creation of their Prieſts; They cauſe them to come into the preſence of the People, and extolling their Zeal and Vertue, they add, That they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereunto, and ſo make them <hi>Santons.</hi> Then all the company preſently run to kiſs their hands, and ſo after this ceremony they become Prieſts. Their Office is to apply their Cares to the Moſques, and there is none but reſpects them, even to the Sultan himſelf. Beſides theſe <hi>Santons,</hi> they have alſo amongſt them other inconſiderable Perſons, who appear all ſlaſhed, hack'd, and half naked, carrying for the moſt part a ſtick in their hands, to which are faſtened Rags.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> have Beads which they tell over, they carry them in their hantis, or hung at their girdle, but they are much different from ours, for each Bead of theirs is of the ſame bigneſs, and have none of that diſtinction we have of the tenth in ten Beads, altho' they are compoſed of ſix Tens. They have moreover another kind of Beads, which are divided into three parts with ſmall threads, becauſe this ſort is greater than others, conſiſting of an hundred grains, yet they employ no more time than we in telling them over, but, on the contrary, have ſooner done, becauſe they ſay not at each Bead for a whole Prayer, but theſe words, <hi>Stafurla,</hi> i. e. <hi>Praiſe be to God;</hi> or elſe, <hi>Eſſebh L'allah, Elmayd L'allah;</hi> which ſignifies, <hi>Praiſe to God, Glory to God.</hi> They are not ſuffered to eat Pork, nor to drink Wine. See the reaſon why <hi>Mahomet</hi> forbad them the uſe of Pork: When he had hidden under ground ſome Veſſels
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199363:22"/>full of Water, for to perform a Miracle like unto that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſhew thereby that he was a great Prophet, it happened that this Animal, which digs always in the earth, ſpoiled all this Myſtery. As for the Wine he forbad it; for that being entred into a Village, accompanied with ſome Soldiers, they preſſed him to pay for their drink, and being drunk, they would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled him to grant them the uſe of the Women of that place, and having refuſed it, whether that he could not, or would not grant it, they thereupon abuſed him; in conſideration therefore of theſe two accidents, he forbad, Pork and Wine to his Followeas: nevertheleſs, there are but a few Perſons of Quality that obſerve this forbiddance, the reſt of the People covet it with eagerneſs, and drink it without Water, which is the reaſon that you may meet all day long with drunken folks, but they are not puniſhed. They have ſtrange liberty to ſin, from whence proceeds infinity of Villanies, for that they believe, in waſhing of their feet, they cleanſe alſo their Souls of all pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. They acknowledge no other Confeſſion, but a ſmall Pitcher of water, which they preſerve to that purpoſe; and they imagine they can be ſaved by ſo eaſie a means. They believe alſo, that we, who are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> can be ſaved by our Law, but they condemn all other Religions. They have for that effect a pleaſant Story, ſaying, That at the higheſt part of the Wall of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> there is a piece of Pillar that ſtands a little out of the Wall, where there will be a little Gate for an entrance into the ſaid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> will come to Univerſal Judgment, that the firſt will ſtand upon that Pillar, and the other oppoſite againſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199363:23"/>him on <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> that both of them will hold in their hand a Cord, which will be extended over the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> that all muſt walk upon that Cord, and that we and they ſhall go ſafely thereon into Paradice, each being eſſiſted by his Prophet, but with this difference, That in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, where floweth Rivers of Honey, they ſhall enjoy all forts of pleaſure, as well in eating and drinking, as in the uſe of beautiful Women; and inſtead of that, we ſhall ſerve them with Horſes and Mules to ride upon. And finally, That the <hi>Jews,</hi> and all other Sects, ſhall fall under the Cord into Hell, where they ſhall ſuffer eternal puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>My arrival to</hi> Mount Libanus, <hi>and how I was received by the Patriarch, and of the difficulties I found in my firſt Conference with him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Muſt now return to my Voyage, from whence I have ſomewhat digreſſed. Finding my ſelf out of the danger of <hi>Tripoly,</hi> I departed from thence on the laſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> three hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sun-ſetting, and being accompanied with divers Perſons of that Country I was going to, I mounted on a little Aſs which went rarely well, and taking our way towards the Mountain, we travelled as long as day laſted; but as ſoon as night approached, we reſted our ſelves in a Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage appertaining to the <hi>Maronites,</hi> where after
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199363:23"/>having made an ordinary Repaſt, we lay upon Mats extended over a Terraſs, and reſted our ſelves there for the ſpace of ſix hours; then Journying through rough, ſteep, and uneven ways, we ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived in nine hours to a place called <hi>Eden,</hi> which in the Hebrew ſignifies <hi>a Place of pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</hi> there we refreſhed our Beaſts, which were wearied. We performed the reſt of our Journey after the heat of the day was over, and arrived on the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> at Sun ſetting, at the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Caunubin,</hi> where reſides the Patriarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> towards which place his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had ſent me. My arrival was as unawares, yet there were divers Prieſts, and ſome other Perſons, that came pretty far to meet me on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Patriarch, who was obliged to keep his Bed for a whole Year paſt, becauſe of his Age and Infirmity. I was conducted to the Monaſtery, where I was received with great demonſtrations of joy, and with the ſound of three conſiderable Bells, which they have there by a particular Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege. I went firſt to the Church, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the Patriarchs Houſe; I found the Church pretty enough, but a little dark, and ill ordered. As to the Patriarch, I accoſted him in a little Chamber which had no Hangings, becauſe he made Profeſſion of a Monaſtick Life, and that the inſatiable Avarice of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſuffered him not to be better accommodated; I found him ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon his Bed with his Patriarchal Turbant in his hand, and after I had made him my obeiſance, I preſented him with his Holineſs Brief, which he very devoutly kiſſed, and placed afterwards upon his head, which is a mark of reſpect in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. He obſerved the ſame ceremony when I gave him the Cardinal Protectors, and our Generals
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199363:24"/>Letters; he enquired after their health, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of a grand affection, and I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd him with the good intention of his Holineſs, and the great care he took both of his Perſon and the whole Nation. After I had ſpent ſome time with him, I was conducted to Supper; next day believing that Father <hi>Fabio,</hi> whom I had left ſick at <hi>Tripoly,</hi> was ſomewhat recovered, and could ſit on Horſeback, I ſent a good Mule for to carry him very eaſily to the place where I was; in effect, he arrived there three days after, but he was ſo weak ſtill, that he was obliged to keep his Bed, wherein he remained 15 days, and indeed he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was well ſince that time.</p>
               <p>I began, after the ſecond day of my arrival, to diſcourſe of my Affairs with the Patriarch: I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained unto him the deſign of my Voyage, with which he teſtified himſelf to be well ſatisfied, however he could not forbear to inform me of two things which much troubled him; the firſt, That his Holineſs had ſent him only but a ſimple Brief, inſtead of addreſſing to him a large and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Bull, which might authentickly ſet forth the Antiquity of their Belief, and their re-union with the Holy See, as the Popes his Predeceſſors had done; that it would have been great conſolation to the Biſhops, and all the People, that ſhould ſee it; and that he had ſo much the more reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it, becauſe he had employ'd the precedent Year a Perſon to his Holineſs, to proſtrate himſelf at his feet, and to render him in his own Name, as well as in the Name of all the Nation, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions that were due unto him, as being all his good and faithful Children. He complained alſo that his Holineſs had made him no anſwer to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of being confirmed in his ancient Title of Patriarch of <hi>Antioch.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199363:24"/>
               <p>After I had heard theſe complaints with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I made him anſwer as I judged moſt proper; after which he ſeemed very pleaſant. I propoſed unto him afterwards an Overture of a Synod, to the end we might know what was then the true Eſtate of Religion in thoſe Parts. I added, That for that purpoſe he needed only but convocate the Biſhops, which might, without danger, render themſelves at the place where we then were. This Propoſition gave him occaſion to make far greater complaints than before; he ſet forth the Reaſons he had of an heavy complaining againſt a Synod, that had been held ſome years before, where had been preſented unto him, and to the Biſhops, a blank Paper to ſign, with aſſurance that it ſhould be filled up with nothing but what ſhould be good and profitable for the Nation, and that having ſigned it with much facility, they had been abuſed, for that thoſe who required this ſigned blank were no ſooner returned to <hi>Tripoly,</hi> than that they filled it up with a great number of Errors, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Hereſies, and without giving information hereof to any one of the Synod, or leaving any Copy behind; they had moſt maliciouſly defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them to the Pope and his Cardinals, that out of the fear he had of the like inconvenience, he vigorouſly oppoſed my requeſt unto him. The foundation of this complaint appeared ſo ſtrange to me, that I could ſcarce believe it, but the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact being reported by ſo conſiderable a Perſon that affirmed it, and being alſo confirmed by all his Aſſiſtants, I durſt not deny it; I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to excuſe it as well as I could, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to uſe my Efforts to recal this Writing, to the end I might appeaſe his much irritated ſpirits. I aſſured him alſo, on my own part, that I would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199363:25"/>undertake nothing without his participation and conſent. At laſt he preſented another great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, or part, of the War that raged extreamly between the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for the Sultan was in the Field in Perſon, with a puiſſant Army, which rendered the execution of a Synod exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difficult, for it was dangerous to aſſemble the principal Perſons of a Nation for to treat at that conjuncture with an Envoy of the Pope. But I ſatisfied alſo the Patriarch in that point, telling him that means might be found out to aſſemble them under other pretences. This good Old Man then conſented to my entreaty, and writ to the Biſhops to invite them to a Synod, but as we could get together but two, I thought it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to remit that Aſſembly till another time. In the mean while, I made uſe of this opportunity to go viſit the Deacons, they are but two in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and perform the Office of Secular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, to govern the People, Judging their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and Treating with the <hi>Turks</hi> about all Matters that regard the Tributes, and about every other affair that occurs. The principal of theſe two is a Man of great Experience, and penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Judgment, who is expert in War, and well inclined to Religion; he approved forthwith of my deſign, and was willing to take the care upon him to aſſemble the Biſhops, and all others whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I pleaſed, altho' he was then ſick of a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, under which he had laboured all the day. He aſſured me, he would render himſelf there, with the other Deacon his companion, and that he would endeavour I ſhould receive ſatisfaction in whatever I propoſed, but I judged it better to deſer the Meeting till ſuch time as he was recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that in the mean while I might inform my ſelf more particularly of all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199363:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the Cedars of</hi> Libanus <hi>and the holy River; and of the nature of the ground of</hi> Mount Libanus.</head>
               <p>I Went to ſee, during that ſpace of time, the Cedar Trees which were not very far off; they ſtand upon an high and craggy Mountain, and are called Saints, becauſe of their Antiquity. And the Natives believe they are ſtill the ſame as thoſe that were in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s time, which is the reaſon they go viſit them with great devotion, eſpecially on the day of the Transfiguration of our Lord; at which time they ſay Maſs moſt ſolemnly at the foot of a Cedar, upon an homely Altar of Stone. Moreover, as theſe Trees are but a few in number, they eſteem it a Miracle that they cannot be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned exactly; I counted 23, and another of my Companions but 21; and there is a great deal of appearance, that the ſame root ſends forth in ſome of them two branches, which are ſometimes rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned for one, ſometimes for two. They never fell them to make boards, but there is an infinite number of other Trees for common uſes, growing upon two other Mountains, which are ſituated in ſuch a manner, that being joined to the former, form a kind of a Croſs. That which they call the Mountain of <hi>Saints,</hi> forms the top, and the other two the ſides. They affirm that certain <hi>Turks,</hi> who fed their Flocks thereabouts, having been ſo impious and hardy, as to cut down ſome of theſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199363:26"/>Trees they call <hi>Saints,</hi> were puniſhed forthwith with the utter loſs of their Beaſts. One may alſo ſee there the Spring of a Rivolet, which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants call the holy River, for that it takes its ſource from the Mountain, whereon grow the <hi>Cedar-Saints</hi> in a very hidden and delicious place, and from it deſcends along the Valley, running with little murmuring ſtreams amongſt flint ſtones.</p>
               <p>I was very much ſatisfied to have ſeen the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid place, and in my return to the Monaſtery, where reſided the Patriarch, I informed my ſelf of the goodneſs of the Soil, of the Cuſtoms and Ways of living in that Country, as alſo of their Belief; and I endeavoured to obſerve them as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly as poſſibly I could.</p>
               <p>All the Country conſiſts of ſtony and high Mountains, which extend from North to South; 'tis a good days Journey in breadth, and four or five long; ſo that in circumference it may be 6 or 700 Miles. Yet theſe Mountains, by the Induſtry and Labour of Men, ſeem for the moſt part like a Plain, for they gather the ſtones toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſome low places, which are diſperſed here and there, and raiſe up high Walls therewith, and ſo proceeding on daily erect others therewith; inſomuch, that by the force of levelling Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and filling up of the Valleys, they make of a barren Mountain a pleaſant Campaign, which may be eaſily cultivated, and ſuch as is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and agreeable. This Country abounds in Corn, excellent Wines, in O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Cotton, Silk, Honey, Wax, Wood, ſavage and tame Animals, and eſpecially in Goats: As for ſmall Animals, there are but a few, becauſe the Winter there is very ſharp, and that they have Snow continually. They have a great number of Sheep; big and fat as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199363:26"/>thoſe of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> As ſoon as you paſs <hi>Cyprus,</hi> there are no more Hogs to be ſeen, becauſe the <hi>Turks</hi> eat none, but in recompence to that, you ſhall find a great number of wild Boars in their Foreſts, as well as Bears, Tygers, and other the like Animals.</p>
               <p>The reſt of the Country is fill'd with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges, which are as big as Hens; no Dove-Houſes to be ſeen there nor in all the <hi>Levant,</hi> but there are abundance of Pigeons, Turtle-Doves, Black-Birds, Gnat-ſnappers, and all ſort of Birds. There are alſo Eagles, and many Squir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels to be ſeen. They never uſe Spades to their Vineyards, but they cultivate them with their Oxen, for they are planted with ſtrait rows of Trees far enough one from another. They uſe no props for to ſupport the Trees, but let them creep along the earth; the Wine that is produced therefrom is delicate and exceeding pleaſant; it's a very ſurprizing thing to ſee the bigneſs of the Grape, which is equal to a Prune, and I eaſily comprehended in ſeeing of them, why the <hi>Hebrews</hi> had ſo great a deſire to taſt them, and that they puſhed forwards with ſo much paſſion the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> after they had ſeen the Grape which the Spies of <hi>Joſhua</hi> brought back from the neighbouring Countries.</p>
               <p>Theſe Mountains abound therefore not only in ſtones, but in all other things neceſſary to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Life; and I doubt not but that they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowelled with rich Mines. There is a certain place a little above the Monaſtery of <hi>Caunubin,</hi> where is found ſtones which give light like unto Flambeaux, which apparently diſcovers, that they are compoſed of Matter full of Sulphur and Bitumen. There may alſo be ſeen, in other places, ground fit for the production of Iron. As I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199363:27"/>on my Journey, the Deacon <hi>Joſeph Cater,</hi> who was with me, aſſured me, That it was but very lately, at the eating of a Goat, he found all her Teeth of a ſilver colour. This confirms that which I obſerved in <hi>Candia;</hi> to wit, That the Animals, that live on <hi>Mount Ida,</hi> eat a certain Herb which renders their Teeth of a golden co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, which, according to my judgment, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe proceed than from the Mines which are under ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of the Cuſtoms of the</hi> Maronites, <hi>and of their Manner of Living.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Maronites</hi> will not ſuffer the <hi>Turks</hi> to live amongſt them, altho' they be in all the reſt of <hi>Syria,</hi> ſo that you cannot ſee one there; they are beholding for it to the great care of their Deacons, who ſpare neither their Purſes nor their Lives to that purpoſe. Their lives therefore upon their Mountains no other than the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which they call <hi>Maronites,</hi> who have taken their name from a certain Abbot called <hi>Maron,</hi> whom they ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> to the Pope in the time that all the Eaſt was ſeparated from the Holy See, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into divers Sects. This Abbot returned from thence with the Title of Patriarch over 'em, who lived firm and conſtant in their Faith. This ſame Perſon lead a Religious Life, ſo that they invoke him as ſuch in their Maſſes. They do not inhabit great Cities, and magnificent Palaces, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199363:27"/>little Villages, whereof there is a great number, and in divers places. Their Houſes are mean and little worth, not but that they have noble and rich Perſons amongſt them, but they are tyranniz'd ſo over by the <hi>Turks,</hi> that they are conſtrained to ſhun all manner of grandeur and oſtentation; they make themſelves poor that they may ſhun ill treatments, and they affect alſo to go meanly clad. Their habit differs not from that of the other <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantines,</hi> which conſiſts of a Turbant and little Veſt that deſcends down to the knees, or to the middle of the leg, and ſometime they wear the <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Abb</hi> to cover it; they go ordinarily with their legs naked, altho' there be ſome who have Drawers on, according to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> manner, with Shoes. The Arms they uſe are the Bow, Harquebus, Cimitar and Dagger; they are very tall Men, of a natural ſweetneſs, docible to Arms, and reſemble the <hi>Italians</hi> more than any other Nations. They uſe no Tables, nor Stools to ſit on, but inſtead thereof ſit down croſs-legg'd upon Mats or Carpets ſpread upon the ground, and there eat and drink; inſtead of a Table-cloth they lay a round piece of leather, and cover it about with Bread, tho' there be but two or three to eat. They ſit round, and put the Victuals in the middle; they eat juſt as the <hi>Turks</hi> do, making no uſe of Napkins, Knives, nor as much as Forks, but have only very pretty wooden Spoons; and when they drink the Glaſs goes round. If any one eats in anothers Houſe, 'tis the Maſter of the Houſe that waits, and ſerving every one with his Glaſs, ſo that he has no manner of repoſe at the Table. They drink often, however their Glaſſes are but ſmall; the more they drink, the more honour they think they do to their Hoſt; and altho' the leather,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199363:28"/>that ſerves for a Table-cloth, be taken up, yet they ceaſe not to drink as long as there is any Wine in the Veſſel. Theſe leathern Table-cloths are neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly folded up with the drawing of a ſmall cord that is round about them. If any one comes in after they are ſet at Table, when he has ſaluted the company he ſits down, eats and drinks without any more ado, and 'twere a great incivility to do otherwiſe. They uſe no Sheets to their Beds they ſleep in, btt only cotton Coverlets; each faſtens a ſtring to the Coverlet, and ſo lies under it.</p>
               <p>When they make any bargain they uſe great ſimplicity, for they have no Scriveners to draw Writings, but they take one anothers words, or a ſimple piece of Paper, or elſe truſt to the good Faith of ſome Witneſs, and uſe the ſame manner at the making of their Wills. They content not themſelves to weep only for the Dead, but make hideous cries and lamentations, and ceaſe not fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to agitate their Bodies here and there. They dreſs no Victuals, for ſome time, in the Houſe of the deceaſed, but their Relations and Friends ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them; wherefore at the uſual times of Repaſt, you ſhall ſee many Women enter with Baskets on their Heads full of Victuals, and the Men come ſoon after for to comfort the Relations of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and to eat with them.</p>
               <p>Theſe People let their Beards grow, and ſhave their Heads, which is the reaſon that they never uncover them no more than the other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Levant.</hi> They highly reſpect their Prieſts, and when they meet them they kiſs their hand, and the Prieſt gives them the Benediction, forming the ſign of the Croſs, accompanied with certain words over them. If they have a Prieſt at their Table they make him drink firſt; beſides he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199363:28"/>drinks alſo laſt, in reciting certain Oriſons, and no body is ſuffered to drink after him. If they mount on Horſeback to go ſome Journey, they preſent themſelves civilly to a Prieſt, praying him to grant them the Benediction, and recite over 'em ſome Prayers before they ſet forth on their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The uſe of Incenſe is very common amongſt them, for they are not only ſerved therewith in the Churches, but alſo at the beginning and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Repaſts, when they crave a bleſſing upon their Victuals, and return God thanks for the ſame. If at any time a Perſon of Quality comes amongſt them, or one of principal Degree in the Church, a Prieſt goes before to receive him with Incenſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Maronite</hi> Women are civil and modeſt, their manner of Dreſs differs not much from the <hi>Italian,</hi> their Apparel deſcends to the ground, and covers their breaſts and ſhoulders entirely; 'tis very plain, being but Cloth of white Cotton, or at beſt but of a violet or blue colour, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a little wrought. They wear upon their Heads a kind of Linnen Veil, which covers all their hair both before and behind. If they meet by chance with a Man they know not, they ſhun him, or cover their faces with their Veil. There are many of them, who like the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Women wear certain Bracelets upon their Arms and Legs, and others of the form of a Fillet at the Forehead, with ſmall pieces of ſilver. They uſe not to curl their hair, nor to paint their faces, neither can you ſee any other the like vanity amongſt them; which is ſo much the more commendable in them, as the contrary is blame-worthy in our <hi>European</hi> Dames.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199363:29"/>
               <p>When they come to Church, they place not themſelves amongſt the Men, nor yet where they may ſee their faces, for all the Men ſit at the upper part of the Church, and they ſtay near to the door for to get firſt out as ſoon as Service is done, to the end they may not be ſeen of any. There is no Man ſtirs from his place till they be all gone forth. The Country is altogether free from Debauched and Common Women, ſo that you can hear there no manner of diſcourſe of Adulteries, or other the like Vices, which is a particular favour of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of their Sciences and Books, and of their Money they pay to the</hi> Turks.</head>
               <p>THeir Prieſts are as ignorant as the Common People, for they can but only read and write. Thoſe amongſt them are eſteemed moſt Learned, who beſides the <hi>Arabick</hi> Language, which is the Mother-Tongue, have ſome knowledge in the <hi>Caldee,</hi> which is regarded by them as the <hi>Latin</hi> is by us. There is not above three or four, who being returned from <hi>Rome,</hi> that throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Philoſophy and Theology, but we hope by the help of God, that there ſhall be for the time to come a greater number of them, of whom there is great care taken to have them inſtructed in the College that has been founded for them at <hi>Rome,</hi> which is very neceſſary for thoſe Parts. They have no convenience nor advantage of Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199363:29"/>no more than in all the reſt of the <hi>Levant,</hi> which might have been of great uſe to publiſh and multiply their Books; however, I think it a great happineſs to this Nation, and alſo to all Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for that not having amongſt them any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons, the reſt of the <hi>Levant</hi> being filled with <hi>Jews, Turks, Armenians, Neſtorians, Jacobites, Dioſcarians, Eutychians, Cophts, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſins, Greeks, Georgians, Melhites,</hi> and other Sects, their wicked Books would multiply too faſt by the help of Printing; and beſides, their good Books would have been eaſily corrupted, and ſtuffed up with falſities and errors.</p>
               <p>They write therefore their Books in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts, altho' that is not totally exempt from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for that the Tranſcribers can add thereto, and change at their pleaſure; however, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires pains and much time, and there being but a few Scribes in all thoſe Parts there is not much reaſon to fear it, and they may always eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remedy it. They make uſe of certain Canes to write with, not knowing the uſe of Gooſe Quills, and other Birds. They do not read as we do, from the Left to the Right, but quite contrary, from the Right to the Left, after the manner of the <hi>Jews.</hi> They begin alſo their Books as they do, that is to ſay, where we end; yet they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not altogether the manner of the <hi>Jews</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to wit, From Right to Left, but turning their Paper ſide-ways write a-croſs.</p>
               <p>One cannot imagine what vaſt Sums the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> of <hi>Mount L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>banus</hi> pay to the <hi>Turks,</hi> beſides the <hi>Carage,</hi> which is an ordinary Tribute; they make daily new <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ange,</hi> and continual Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The <hi>Carage</hi> is great for every one pays ſeparately for his Goods, Perſon, and his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199363:30"/>The ſecond Tribute amounts to ſeventeen Crowns a Head, as well for Children of 9 or 10 years of Age, as for Men. The firſt is a Crown for every eight Foot of Land one poſſeſſeth. The <hi>Emir Elias,</hi> the Governor of the Country for the Sultan, ſends to gather theſe Tributes; and altho' the Grand Senior hath fixed the Sum he is to collect for all the Year, yet he ceaſeth not to demand more. And the Receiver comes not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimply to take the Air, if they do not pay forthwith, comes another Receiver, who aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Sum; the which they call the <hi>Carage,</hi> or <hi>Tribute of Solicitation,</hi> and the longer they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard the Payment, the more the Sum increaſeth. Wherefore it comes to paſs, that if any one has not his Money ready, he is obliged to take it from the <hi>Turks</hi> upon very great Intereſt; and if he finds himſelf unwilling to accept of it upon the conditions, he is conſtrained to ſell his Land forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with for as much as he can get for it, inſomuch that it happens oftentimes, that one loſeth a great Inheritance, or a Tenement of 4 or 5000 Crowns value, for a very ſmall matter; nay, ſometimes for a Crown. The Dead pay their <hi>Garage</hi> as well as the Living, for as the Grand Seignior eſteems himſelf Abſolute Maſter of the Country, and of all the Eſtates of the Inhabitants, to whom he grants only the uſe of them, he believes, that in caſe of Mortality, all their Poſſeſſions ought to return to him, and by conſequence the right Heirs, or Teſtators, if they have a mind to enjoy them peaceably, ought to pay him a certain Sum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the Eſtates they inherit. Some pay ten or a dozen Crowns, others forty or fifty; and it amounts ſometimes to an hundred or two of Crowns, or more. There is a Perſon who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199363:30"/>rangeth the Country up and down continually, for to learn who are dead, to the end he may raiſe the Tribute. If any one has been lately Interred, he ſoon perceives it, and cauſeth them alſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to open Graves for to ſee if there be any newly dead.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if any one has buſineſs neceſſary to be treated about with the <hi>Emir,</hi> be it to demand a Favour, or Juſtice, he concludes nothing but by the force of Money. No Perſon durſt appear before this Judge without large Sums and Preſents, he that carries moſt receives moſt profit; and 'tis almoſt incredible how much Money he ſqueezeth from theſe poor People in a Year, nay every Day, ſo inſupportable is the Tyranny of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſo Miſerable is the condition of them who live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Dominion; the violence is too great, and I cannot believe it can be endured any long time, many of them are already withdrawn, and have abandoned their Lands an Houſes, others depart daily, and go into other Countries, being no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to endure the grand Impoſitions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are ſurcharged, they chuſe rather to live in the Poverty and Afflictions of a voluntary baniſhment, than to remain with their Eſtates in their own Country, under ſo inſupportable a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. Altho' theſe are withdrawn, the <hi>Emir</hi> pretends he will loſe upon that conſideration none of the ordinary Tribute; he is paid Yearly by the two Deacons, two thouſand Crowns for theſe abandoned Eſtates, part of which they pay out of their own Pockets, and the reſt is paid by the People, to the end he ſend not any <hi>Turks</hi> into thoſe Places for to poſſeſs them; but I ſhall no longer detain the Reader with the relation of a thing ſo ſad and deplorable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199363:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of their Eccleſiaſticks and Religious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE muſt now begin to ſpeak of the Belief and Religion of theſe People; and for your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding you muſt know, they have, as all others, Laicks, Eccleſiaſticks, and Religious; but as we have ſufficiently ſpoken already of the Laicks, we are now to ſay ſomething of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks and Religious.</p>
               <p>The Clergy have their Degrees, as well Sacred as not Sacred: This pretty Hierarchy, which hath been eſtabliſhed in the Church, is perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the Perſon of the Patriarch, who is ſubject to the Pope, and that of divers Biſhops, and of a good number of Prieſts, who are govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Biſhops. The Patriarch and the Biſhops keep a perpetual Celibat, and there are none but the Monks that are admitted to this Dignity, for there are none but theſe that live unmarried. If they take any one that has broken this Order, they lock him up forthwith in a Monaſtery, and he eats no more Bread.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of Biſhops amongſt-them, one of which are but meer Abbots of Monaſteries, and have no care of Souls upon them; they have neither the Mark nor Epiſcopal Habit, but are dreſs'd as other Monks are, and have only this Privilege, That they carry the Mitre and Croſs in ſinging of Maſs. The other have under their Governments the greateſt Churches, and wear a Veſt nethermoſt altogether, according to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199363:31"/>Mode of the Country, and over that a <hi>Spain,</hi> or Violet coloured Cloth, which deſcends down to the ground, with a very great blue Turbant. The Patriarch is clad in the ſame manner as the Biſhops, and 'tis he alone that hath the particular Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all <hi>Mount Libanus,</hi> excepting ſome places too remote from him, where he placeth ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for that end; but as he cannot always in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon viſit ſo great an extent of Land, which is very difficult, he keeps by him two or three Biſhops, one of which applies himſelf particularly to the Adminiſtration of <hi>Cannubin,</hi> where the Patriarch reſideth, and to collect the Taxes and Revenues of the Country, which amount to three or four thouſand Crowns. He ſends the other here and there into different Places, for to viſit the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and ſupply their Neceſſities. There are moreover three other Biſhops without theſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which have alſo their Juriſdiction apart, but yet with a dependance upon the ſame Patriarch; one of which reſides at <hi>Damas,</hi> the other at <hi>Alep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po,</hi> and the third in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> every one has the care of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> which have a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on him.</p>
               <p>The other Prieſts, and with much more reaſon the Deacons and Sub-deacons, can at leaſtwiſe, if they be not Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, marry before they receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders, which they are the rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to do, becauſe the People look not favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably upon them if they be not married, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are young; and the Biſhops do with great difficulty admit them into Orders, if they confine not themſelves into the Monaſteries, or not marry. The Deacons, Sub-deacons, and the other inferior Clerks, have no other habit but ſuch as the Laicks wear. The Prieſts are not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199363:32"/>but by a blue Turbant, which they wear a little leſs than that of the Biſhops; and as to the reſt, they do no ways differ from others.</p>
               <p>The Religious have none of that diſtinction of Order and Profeſſion that is uſed elſewhere, they are all alike: I am perſwaded that theſe Monks are the remnants of thoſe ancient Hermites which lived ſeparate from Mankind, and dwelled in great numbers in the Deſarts of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Valestine;</hi> there are excellent Authors that have treated of them, and I believe I have my ſelf good proofs for to ſupport that Opinion.</p>
               <p>The firſt are the Places of their Abode, for their Reſidence is not in delicious Plains, or on pleaſant little Hills accommodated with agreeable Proſpects, nor in well-peopled Cities and Places, frequented by Men, but they are retired to the moſt abſtruſe Parts of theſe Mountains, ſeparated from all Commerce, and living under great Rocks, ſo that they ſeem to dwell in Grots and Caverns, fit rather for wild Beaſts than Habitations for Men.</p>
               <p>Their poor and ordinary Apparel ſerves for a ſecond Proof: They wear but a pitiful, unvaluable, ill-ſhaped Coat, wherein they wrap themſelves, with a black Cowl upon their heads; and this Veſtment deſcends only from the ſhoulders to the girdle, without any thing to cover their ſhoulders withal; neither is there any other Habit cut ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the faſhion of theſe, that are uſed amongſt all the Community of their Religious.</p>
               <p>Their manner of Living furniſheth us with a third Proof: They live only upon that which the Earth it ſelf produceth, and never eat any Fleſh, tho' they be ſick and in danger of death. As for Wine they very rarely drink any. They have no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199363:32"/>particular Rules, nor written Conſtitutions, for to be obſerved by every one, as may be ſeen in all other Religious Houſes, who are eſtabliſhed to live in Community. They make no expreſs Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the three Vows of Religion; to wit, Poverty, Chaſtity, and Obedience; but when they are received into the Monaſtery where they make Profeſſion, one holds a Book in his Hand, and reads only ſomething that belongs to them, advertiſing them, That they ought to live in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence, and adds many the like things. Theſe Advertiſements are ſufficient to make them keep a perfect Chaſtity: You ſhall never hear any ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous or ill report of them, altho' they cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally go alone up and down, and ſtay oftentimes many days tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther out of their Monaſtery. They have Goods and Money of their own, and can diſpoſe thereof at their death. If they have no longer a Mind to ſtay in the Monaſtery, they go into another, without the leave of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</p>
               <p>In the fourth place, They are never permitted to Exerciſe any Eccleſiaſtical Function; they have no Spiritual Exerciſe in common for the good of their Neighbour, and have no Power either to Preach or Confeſs, ſo that they are only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>In the fifth place, They give to their Superiours and Chiefs the Name of Abbot, as the Hermits did of Old.</p>
               <p>Finally, I ſhall take for the ſixth and laſt Proof, the name they bear of the Monks of St. <hi>Anthor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y;</hi> and 'tis this that ought to make ſome impreſſions upon the ſpirits of thoſe who would ſearch out the cauſe why theſe Religious are ſo called.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199363:33"/>
               <p>Has this good Man ever founded any Religious Houſe for to live in Community? Did he not live a Solitary and Hermitical Life, in the Deſarts of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> exerciſing the Function of Abbot, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe that lead the ſame Life of himſelf? There is therefore reaſon to believe, that this was the true Original of the Monks, which are at this day in <hi>Mount Libanus,</hi> and which are called the Monks of St. <hi>Anthony.</hi> Many have imagined that they were reduced to that poverty they live in, through the continual Oppreſſion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who obliged them to Labour and Cultivate the Earth, but I do not doubt but that was the end of their Conſtitution, for ſo much as the holy Hermits and Servants of God, for to ſhun Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gain their Living by the Induſtry of their own hands, accuſtomed themſelves to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for a good part of the day; theſe ſame had many Perſons under them, whom they employed to the hardeſt Labours, and they contented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to carry on the ſame, and render it leſs pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. As to their Hoſpitality, the uſe whereof, perhaps, they have preſerved ſince their Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they highly exerciſe it, eſpecially in the Monaſtery of <hi>Cannubin,</hi> where there is kept an open Table for all the Year round, admittance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never forbid, not only to the <hi>Maronites,</hi> and other <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and all Comers, who are welcome to eat what they pleaſe, which is the cauſe of vaſt expence unto them; for as 'tis the ordinary Reſidence of the Patriarch, 'tis incredible what multitudes are drawn thither daily, either through Neceſſity, Curioſity, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, or ſome other Matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199363:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of the Errors that have been impoſed upon them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Diſcovered, with much evidence, the Abuſes whereof I am about to ſpeak, and ſome others of the ſame nature; which made me open my eyes, and apply my ſelf with all Induſtry to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that might regard their Belief, not only becauſe theſe matters were of very great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, being the foundation of all Religion, but alſo becauſe I had learn'd, that ſome years paſt, they had been attributed unto them amongſt other Errors.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there was in Jeſus Chriſt but one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to wit, The Divine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Holy Ghoſt proceeded only from the Father.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That all the Trinity was Incarnated, died on the Croſs, and roſe again. And thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed theſe errors unto them, ſaid, That that was the reaſon why they added to the Triſagion, which is Sung by the Angels, <hi>Qui natus es pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, qui Crucifixus es pro nobis, qui ſurrexiſti, &amp; aſcendisti in coelum pro nobis miſerere nobis;</hi> as if they retained the ancient Errors condemned in the fifth Council of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That an Husband might put away his Wife, and take another, if ſhe committed Adultery, or far other reaſons.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:199363:34"/>
               <p n="5">5. That there is no Original Sin.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the Souls that departed from their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſaw not Heaven for to be there rewarded, nor Hell for to be there puniſhed, but that they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for that till the Univerſal Judgment: And that in the mean time, they remained in a place where there was neither grief nor joy.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That 'tis Lawful to deny ones Belief out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and alſo by Words, provided it be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured up in the heart.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the Sacrament of Confirmation was not diſtinct from Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That they gave the Euchariſt to young Children.</p>
               <p>Altho' I uſed all my own Induſtry to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of theſe Errors, and imploy'd others for that purpoſe, yet I could never diſcover but two of them, to wit, The repudiation of their Wifes, and the Communion which they gave to Children. I am very well ſatisfy'd, that the firſt is not an error whereof the whole Nation ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, as if it approved of this Divorcement, but an accident that happened two or three times, which had been fomented through the violence and tyranny of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who favoured the deſigns of ſome Profligates, who had put away their Wifes for to marry others of whom they were enamoured. Thoſe ſort of People being not able to obtain the conſent of the Patriarch for to marry them, had recourſe to the <hi>Emir,</hi> who gave them, for their Money, permiſſion to do it, giving them his Letters to the Patriarch for to excuſe them, who diſſembled his reſentments thereof upon juſt conſiderations. 'Tis certain, that the like caſe happening at the time of my being there, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199363:34"/>would no ways conſent thereto, but not being able to remedy it, he was obliged to paſs it by. In regard to the ſecond Error, 'tis common to all, neither can it be eſteemed for an Error nor Hereſie, ſince the Church hath heretofore practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame thing for a long time. As for the other Errors, I underſtood very well that they had been falſly charged with them; however, having read in one of their Books, I know not what concerning one Will and one Operation in Jeſus Chriſt, and ſome other impure things, I reſolved to put all theſe Articles ſeparately into writing, and to propoſe each in particular to the Synod, when it ſhould be aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, before it came to the reformation of Abuſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of the aſſembling of a Synod, and of the Profeſſion of Faith that was made there.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter I had informed my ſelf of all things as well as poſſibly I could, I applied all my cares to give notice forthwith of the Synod, for which I had ſuch a deſire, to the Biſhops, two Deacons, and to the moſt underſtanding Clergy. They aſſembled the 28th of <hi>December,</hi> which is the 18th according to the ſupputation of the <hi>Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> who have not received the reformation of the Calendar of <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. The Patriarch then, and thoſe which were ſummoned, finding themſelves together, read publickly the Pope's Brief, which contained my Miſſion, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199363:35"/>I had from his Holineſs; and as every one remained ſilent, I expoſed unto them at large, the Reaſons that had moved me to convocate this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. I repreſented unto them the importance of it, entertained them at the ſame time with the great care and affection his Holineſs had towards them; then I ſpoke a few words to the Biſhops in particular, touching their Duty, and the Charge they had of the Church.</p>
               <p>I divided the Matters to be treated of into three Heads; the firſt whereof regarded to their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; the ſecond to the young <hi>Maronites</hi> that were to be ſent from that Country to <hi>Rome;</hi> and thirdly, To thoſe that would be ſent back again from <hi>Rome</hi> unto them. As I was ready to open the Synod, with the Matters that regarded the Belief and Conformity of their Religion to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I was interrupted by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, who teſtified his having received much diſpleaſure about a Synod that had been held ſome years ago from <hi>Rome,</hi> proteſting that neither he, nor his Predeceſſor, had done, nor approved of what was tranſacted; whereupon he deteſted, and anathamiz'd, the Errors which had been impoſed upon them and the Nation. He anathamiz'd all thoſe that held them, or had ever held them, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring us, That he had always followed, and would ſtill for the future, the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> to which words the prime Deacon being tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with zeal, added theſe, <hi>Yes, we will follow, and never ſeparate in any part from it, whatever miſery may befall us.</hi> Indeed, I conceived much joy to ſee that the beginning was accompanied with ſo firm a reſolution, and ſuch great ſtedfaſtneſs of ſpirit, ſo that it incouraged me in ſuch a manner, that I believed I had no further ſearch to make,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199363:35"/>for to render me certain of my Enquiries. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, for to be more aſſured, and alſo to juſtifie them, I applied my ſelf to examine all the Errors, one after another, and that every one in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſhould declare his Belief; all, with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent agreed, without any diſpute or controverſie, and made Profeſſion together of the following Articles.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That there is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> but one Perſon which is Divine, with two Natures, two Wills, two Operations; one of which is Divine, the other Humane. It was a great comfort to me, to ſee in all their Books very ample teſtimonies of this truth; I found alſo particular Works compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon this ſubject, which was well handled, and filled with a great number of Authorities drawn from the Old and New Teſtament, as well as from the <hi>Latin</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers.</p>
               <p n="2">II. That the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> proceeded from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son, as from the only Principle; that which is read not only by them in divers places of their Books, but alſo ſuch as is rehearſed by them in the Creed, <hi>Qui eſt, patre &amp; filio procedit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. That the Son alone was Incarnated, and not the whole Trinity; as alſo who was born, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who roſe again, and who aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and for that reaſon they took the word <hi>Triſagion</hi> two manner of ways, applying it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the whole Trinity, ſometimes to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon only; but when they took it for the firſt, they added it not at all, but when for the ſecond, they added it by coherence to the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Birth, Death, and other the like things, which truly agreed with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:199363:36"/>
               <p n="4">IV. That it might be judged by their Actions, that they acknowledged a place of Purgatory, and Original Sin; that the firſt was ſufficiently ſet forth by their Alms and Prayers.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That the ſecond proved it ſelf plainly by the Baptiſm they gave to little Infants, to the end that being waſhed and cleanſed of their ſins, they might obtain eternal Life, altho' they had committed no Actual Sin that required their being waſhed and cleanſed by that Sacrament, knowing that St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> made often uſe of that argument, to prove that ſame truth againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> of his time.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That Souls, generally ſpeaking, when they depart from the Body, go ſtraight to Heaven for to enjoy Bleſſedneſs, or to Hell, for to be there eternally puniſhed, or for a time to Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That 'tis never Lawful for to deny ones Faith in words, as Jeſus Chriſt himſelf manifeſtly declared; <hi>He that denies me before men, him will I alſo deny before my father which is in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Finally, That in Marriage they permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſometimes a Separation of Living, but that nothing but Death was able to diſſolve the Bond of Matrimony, in ſuch a manner as that it was lawful for the Husband to Eſpouſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conformable to thoſe words of Jeſus Chriſt, which are ſo expreſs; <hi>Whoſoever puts away his Wife, and marries another, commits Adultery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I failed not to object, and lay before them, thoſe Books wherein I found ſome Errors: They made anſwer, That they were not their true Books, but that they had been maliciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived by the <hi>Jacobins,</hi> and diſperſed amongſt their Nation; that as to the reſt, their Books were very different, and that the Pope had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:199363:36"/>falſe information of them; which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied me ſo much the more, becauſe in their Actions I diſcovered that it was ſo in effect. I ſaw in their Books, which they acknowledged for true, nothing but what was Catholick; and as others have not made that diſtinction with exactneſs enough, one ought not to be aſtoniſhed if they returned to <hi>Rome</hi> with ſuch contrary Informations: Wherefore having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, by what is here demonſtrated, and by many other Enquiries and Circumſtances tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in this Synod, plenary ſatisfaction of the firmneſs of their Belief, we made ſeveral Canons for to reform the Abuſes amongſt them, and to confirm the Profeſſion they made here of their Faith, and added what other things we thought neceſſary for to oblige them to a firm conſtancy therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199363:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of the</hi> Maronites <hi>that were to be ſent to</hi> Rome; <hi>and of thoſe that ſhould return from thence into their own Country.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Had yet ſaid nothing of two Points, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belong'd to my Commiſſion; the firſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the young <hi>Maronites,</hi> that they ſhould be ſent to the College at <hi>Rome,</hi> to be inſtructed there: and the ſecond, to thoſe who had finiſh'd their Studies there, and ſhould be ſent back to them, for to labour, and aſſiſt their Brethren in all Spiritual Concerns. As to the firſt, we encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd no Difficulty in it; for ſo ſoon as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd our Deſires, it was unanimouſly conſented to. See what was propos'd; That all thoſe that ſhould be ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould not be dull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, and that they ſhould at leaſt be able to read and write, and have ſome knowledge in the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Grammar, to the end that they might be ſooner ſerviceable to their Country; wherefore it was neceſſary they ſhould ſend them of the age of fourteen, that they ſhould not put them on the way to <hi>Rome</hi> before that they had given informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof a Year before; that thoſe whom they ſhould chuſe in one or many Places, according to the conveniency they found, ſhould be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in their Voyage with prudent and faithful Perſons; that they ſhould not go aſhore in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> but paſs directly for <hi>Venice,</hi> from whence they might come to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:199363:37"/>
               <p>As to the ſecond Article, we imploy'd much more time and words; the Difficulties proceeded as well from the Poverty of the Churches, which had no Revenues to entertain the Prieſts, as from the Oppreſſion of the <hi>Turks;</hi> wherefore I firſt conferr'd in particular, then publickly with the two Deacons: I propos'd unto them, that in reſpect of thoſe who were already come from the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege at <hi>Rome,</hi> or who ſhould return for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the cure of Souls, that they ſhould be ſupplied from the Temporalities, and beſides, that they ſhould be exempt from the Tribute which every one pays for his Head to the Grand Seignior. They return'd me a very civil and Chriſtian An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and promis'd to do what I propos'd unto them, and at the ſame time entreated me, that I would obtain from his Holineſs a ſmall Penſion for the ſubſiſtence of theſe Labourers: I aſſur'd them I would uſe my endeavour, and with ſo much the more confidence to ſucceed, for that having fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen their demand, I had already entertaind his Holineſs therewith, who had in a manner given me his Word for it.</p>
               <p>I made known unto them, on the part of the Pope, what Diſpleaſure he had conceiv'd, to ſee at this preſent time amongſt them a ſmall number of excellent Labourers, recommendable for their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Piety, unimploy'd: I then propos'd Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments for them, and for ſuch as for the future ſhould return from <hi>Rome;</hi> in the mean time, as it was neceſſary they ſhould be provided with good and faithful Paſtors, which ſhould have a perfect knowledge of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with which they were willing to keep an Union, I added, that theſe Perſons might very uſefully be imploy'd there, in making the moſt capable of them Biſhops,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199363:38"/>who ſhould govern the People; which was ſo much the more neceſſary, ſeeing they had then three or four Biſhopricks vacant, to the great prejudice of Souls; and that of others they might make Prieſts, Curates, and Preachers. They had already im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd ſome of them to catechize Children and the Ignorant, to read Leſſons of Caſes of Conſcience to the Prieſts, to correct their ſuſpected and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Books, and to compoſe others which ſhould be proper and neceſſary for the Nation. They might alſo keep ſome of 'em near the Patriarch and Biſhops, for to ſatisfie any Difficulties they might rencounter, to accompany them in their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, and alſo to viſit ſome Churches, or for to go ſometimes one way, ſometimes another, according to the occaſions th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had for them. Not to ſpeak of other Neceſſities that might daily occurr, I let them underſtand, that they ought to have recourſe to Prayer, for to render God Thanks for ſending of ſuch Labourers amongſt them, endow'd with the neceſſary Qualifications.</p>
               <p>My Diſcourſe was ſo evident, that they all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd with one accord, that <hi>it ſhould be done for the future;</hi> the Patriarchs promis'd it very freely: And as there was now no matter of importance undone, and that it was to be fear'd, leſt they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd themſelves ſuſpicious to the <hi>Turks</hi> if the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod laſted any longer, particularly becauſe of a great concourſe of People that flock'd thither daily, amongſt whom were alſo found <hi>Turks,</hi> the Aſſembly was diſmis'd, and every one had the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to retire to his own Habitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199363:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of the Death of the Patriarch, and of the Election of another.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoon as the Synod was diſſolv'd, and the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs that I treated with the Patriarch were terminated, I took my Leave of him, ſeeing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might hinder and ſtop my return to <hi>Italy;</hi> my deſign nevertheleſs was not to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeedily, but firſt to viſit ſome of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Monaſteries, and give the Biſhops ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, who liv'd there, and entreated my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. I had reſolv'd to go from thence as far as <hi>Damas,</hi> for to ſee the Biſhops and <hi>Maronites</hi> of thoſe parts, for I judg'd it very dangerous to go to <hi>Aleppo.</hi> From <hi>Damas</hi> I was to return to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubin,</hi> to ſee in what manner they obſerv'd the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that had been made, and to part from thence for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before my return to <hi>Rome.</hi> I went therefore directly with my Companion and ſome others to the Monaſteries of <hi>Chſaia</hi> and <hi>St. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony;</hi> theſe two Monaſteries are ſo near one to another, that they ſeem almoſt to be in the ſame place: there was in one of them two Nephews of the Patriarch, one of whom was Archbiſhop and Abbot of the Monaſtery, and Suffragan to the ſame Patriarch: in the other he had <hi>three Brothers,</hi> which were all three Archbiſhops. We went from thence to <hi>Eden,</hi> which is the moſt conſiderable place of theſe Mountains; we were receiv'd there very honourably, and with great demonſtrations of Joy.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199363:39"/>
               <p>From <hi>Eden</hi> we went to the Monaſtery of St. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> which is not above a mile diſtant from thence. We were always accompanied with the better ſort of People, who walked on foot before our Mules, and out of the reſpect they bore to the Pope, and in honour to us, they would ſing certain Songs and Spiritual Airs, which they uſually ſung as they marched before the Patriarch and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality. Being arrived at the Monaſtery, we went to ſalute the Abbot, who was an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, exceeding aged: We were no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into the Church, but there came a man with all ſpeed, being ſent on purpoſe from <hi>Cannubin,</hi> that brought us the News, that the Patriarch lay a dying, and if I were minded to ſee him alive, I ſhould loſe no time: wherefore, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, we took our leave of this good old man, and returned with all ſpeed to <hi>Cannubin,</hi> but it was impoſſible for us to arrive there till two hours after his death: it was on the fifth of <hi>October,</hi> according to our Calendar, and on the twenty-fifth of <hi>September,</hi> by their ſupputation, we found him in the Church, ſitting in a Chair, clad in his ſacred Habits, having the Mitre on his Head, and Patriarchal Croſs in his Hand: there were abundance of his Relations, both Men and Women about him, who wept and beat their Breaſts, making hideous Cries all night. Next day came a multitude of People thither, and among the reſt a great number of Prieſts, who aſſembled for to interr him. The two Deacons render'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves there likewiſe. They carried him at Noon to the uſual Burying-place of the Patriarchs, which was not above a Muſquet-ſhot from thence, and then laid him in that Grott, fitting in a Wooden Chair, according to their cuſtom.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199363:39"/>
               <p>The Election of the Patriarch that ought to ſucceed and govern all the Nation in Spiritual matters, was to be done by the people, and there is a time appointed for that, which is the Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day after the death of the other; the Chiefs of that Aſſembly were very urgent with me to ſtay and aſſiſt at that Election, aſſuring me they would chuſe that perſon I ſhould name; but I thought it more convenient to withdraw, and leave the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction entirely free to themſelves. I confeſs indeed I had regard to the Complaints that were made of the former Patriarchs, for having render'd that Dignity as hereditary in their Family: as they had already two Brethren that had been Patriarchs, the matter was reduced to ſuch a point, that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Abbot of <hi>Chſaia</hi> muſt infallibly ſucceed his Uncle, becauſe of the great places he enjoy'd, and alſo of the ſpiritual relation he had to him; who had added to the Family of the Patriarch all the Nobles and Perſons of Quality of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by holding of their Children to Baptiſm: Moreover the Archbiſhoprick and Abbey of <hi>Chſaia</hi> muſt have been given to his Brother, who would alſo be Patriarch in his turn, and then the Nephews would tread in the ſame Steps. I failed not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that day to entertain the Deacon <hi>Joſeph Cater</hi> herewith, who was a prudent and underſtanding man, as I confer'd with him about ſome other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. He had indeed nothing to object againſt the Perſon of that Abbot, ſaving that having alwaies been confined to a Monaſtery, where he had lead an hermetical life, it was plain he had but little Experience, eſpecially in things belonging to a Paſtor. I departed the day following for <hi>Tripoli,</hi> with a deſign to ſtay there during the Election of a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199363:40"/>new Patriarch, and to return again as ſoon as I ſhould hear of his being elected.</p>
               <p>The People flock'd thither from all parts far and near, inſomuch that they amounted to above the number of Two thouſand on the day of the Election, to wit, the 13th of <hi>October,</hi> according to our Calendar: The Archbiſhop <hi>Joſeph Riſi,</hi> of whom we have already ſpoken, was choſen by the plurality of Voices; he elected for his Suffragan, and for to viſit all the Churches in that Country, <hi>Moſes Aniſio,</hi> who was already of the Order of Prieſthood, and who was recommended unto him by ſome Perſons of Quality; he conſecrated him Archbiſhop, and took for his Archprieſt, to the end he might take care of the Land of <hi>Eſdron,</hi> his Country, <hi>John Bareck,</hi> who had been educated at the College in <hi>Rome,</hi> and whom the preceding Patriarch had made Prieſt, according to the right of the Nation. The new Patriarch gave me notice of the Election, and deſir'd me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and ſent Men and Mules for to conduct me. I agreed with his Requeſt, and went with ſpeed: He teſtified at the ſight of me, that he was exceeding joyful for my return. I treated with him about no particular affairs, but was much ſatisfied to hear him declare in generous terms the Goodwill he had for to acquit his Charge with Fidelity, and the great Care he would take of the Souls under his Conduct. I exhorted him to continue and put in execution ſuch laudable Deſigns, and ſo took my leave of him, in order to finiſh the Reſolutions I had form'd to go to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199363:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>My return from</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to</hi> Tripoly, <hi>and thence to</hi> Alexandretta; <hi>with an account of</hi> Alexandretta.</head>
               <p>AFter I had ſatisfied the Intentions of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and had ſeen in Perſon the Holy Places of the Birth, Life, Death, and Reſurrection of of our Lord, I returned to <hi>Tripoly,</hi> in order to be Tranſported for <hi>Italy;</hi> my return was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodious becauſe of the Seaſon, and of my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Embarked in the Month of <hi>December,</hi> in a ſmall Ship which let in Water on all ſides, ſo that there was a Man always employed to Pump it out. This traverſe is at leaſt 200 Miles, but, thanks be to God, we arrived ſafely at <hi>Tripoly</hi> before <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> for our Conſolation, and that of ſome Chriſtian Merchants who lived there, and who wanted extreamly ſome Spiritual Succour for the Duties of that day.</p>
               <p>After we had ſpent that Feaſt as devoutly as we could, we had a conveniency to go for <hi>Italy</hi> and for <hi>Rome.</hi> There was in the Port of <hi>Tripoly</hi> three French Barks, one of which was bound for <hi>Malta,</hi> and another for <hi>Sicily,</hi> whence it would have been eaſie for us to go to <hi>Naples,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Rome;</hi> the deſire we had to ſee theſe Iſlands, enticed us extreamly to embark in one of theſe two Veſſels, but by good fortune we could not agree with the Maſters. I ſay by good fortune, for that when we had arrived afterwards
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199363:41"/>at <hi>Iſtria,</hi> we underſtood that one of their Barks had been Caſt-away, and the other made a Prize by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and thus we had been either loſt in the Sea, or carried Priſoners into <hi>England,</hi> but God preſerved us from both. We reſolved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to return to <hi>Venice,</hi> and underſtanding that the Ship, wherein we had paſſed the Year before, was ſtill at <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> from whence it would part on the firſt fair weather, we were exceeding glad of it, becauſe it was a great and ſafe Veſſel; the only difficulty was to come at it, which we ſurmounted by the conveniency of the third French Bark, whereof we have ſpoken, which tho' but ſmall, was good, and well rigged, having alſo an able Pilot. We then changed our Pilgrims Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and clad us like Merchants, having a furred Veſt on as they wear them in the <hi>Levant,</hi> and a toque on our heads, at the top of which was a Band of ſtriped Cloth, which repreſented the form of a Turbant, according to the Turkiſh man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Having imbarked on this Veſſel, with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and neceſſary Refreſhments, we ſailed on the third of <hi>January</hi> about Midnight; the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was very fair, but it changed ſuddenly, and we were furiouſly toſs'd with the Waters for three days and three nights together. But finally, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching near <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> with the help of God, through the Gulph of <hi>Ghiaccia,</hi> we met with our Ship on the 12th of the ſame month, three hours before Sun-ſetting; we found no great difficulty to agree for our paſſage with the Maſter, who knew us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> which is alſo called <hi>Scandaroon,</hi> is a very little place, wherein there is not above twenty or thirty Houſes, which ſerve for ſhelter to ſome Merchants who come to that Port, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199363:41"/>thither to Traffick to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> which is not far off. The Houſes are built of Wood, and thatched with Straw, for there live none there but a few Merchants, who are intirely employ'd to Trade, and voluntarily ſuffer all ſorts of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, through a deſire they have to gain wealth. We ſaw there Oxen and Bufflers carry burdens upon their backs as Mules and Horſes do in <hi>Italy.</hi> There are Camels that continually carry Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize to and from <hi>Aleppo;</hi> and that which ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed me moſt, was to ſee theſe Animals go to the Sea-ſide for to drink the ſalt water, as we ſee other Beaſts drink freſh They ſay this was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the Country of the <hi>Amazones.</hi> We found there two Religious <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who lived in great poverty, for they had no other Habitation ſave a little Church built of Wood, which was filled with Water when it rained, where there was a Plank for theſe wretches to eat their Victuals upon, who lay upon the Boards, without any other conveniency. As we were forced to ſtay there many days, we converſed much with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:199363:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of what happened to us in</hi> Cyprus.</head>
               <p>AFter we had ſtay'd with much inconveniency in that place till the 26th of <hi>March,</hi> our Ship hoiſted Sail at Midnight, and having made all things ready, we ſteered our courſe for <hi>Cyprus;</hi> we ſucceſsfully approached <hi>Salines</hi> on the 29th of the ſame Month. Having ſlept all night in the Ship, we went aſhoar next day very eaily, and went to the Monaſtery of the Religious at <hi>Arnique,</hi> where we had already been received the preceding year with much charity: Theſe good Religious redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled their kindneſs in that place, where an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent befel us; for I being retired into a little Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to eaſe Nature, at a time when one of the Religious was ſaying of Maſs, it was no ſooner ended, but a <hi>Venetian</hi> Merchant, who came to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute me, demanded forthwith if I had received his Letter at <hi>Tripoly,</hi> and as I informed him I had not, he changed colour, and remained quite ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. His action made me judge there was ſome miſchief in the caſe, and having preſſed him to tell me why he asked me ſuch a queſtion, he freely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, If you had received my Letter, I would have been much ſurprized to have ſeen you here, for I gave you information to go another way to <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe of a certain <hi>Italian</hi> Runagado that is here, who hath been with the <hi>Sangiac,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of this Iſle, and entertained him with theſe words, <hi>Are not you Governor here? Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do you ſuffer the Pope to ſend hither his Spies
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199363:42"/>from</hi> Rome, <hi>for to go treat about Affairs with the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>of</hi> Mount Libanus, <hi>who have aſſembled the People there, created new Biſhops, and done other the like things, which prejudice your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> This Runagado hath been charged by the <hi>Sangiac</hi> to find you out and Impriſon you, to the end you might be brought before him and ſo ſent forthwith to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the Grand Seignior, who, without doubt, would cauſe you to be Impaled.</p>
               <p>I thanked this Friend, as I ought, for the care he had taken of my Life, in giving me ſuch good Information, which I ſhould not have failed to make uſe of if I had received it, for I would have gone another way. I then took my leave of my Merchant, and after I had made a ſmall Repaſt with theſe good Religious, I was reſolved to go on board for to conceal my ſelf as well as I could in the Ship; but when I came to the Sea-ſide, I found it ſo tempeſtuous, that there was neither Man nor Shallop to be ſeen for to put me on board the Veſſel, ſo that I was obliged to return to the Monaſtery to attend the appeaſing of the Sea, and placing all my truſt and hopes in God. Theſe good Fathers had given us the uſe of a little Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber near the Gate, with a Bed for us to lie in; for my part, I lay in a Cheſt in my Cloaths, my ſleep was not long, but was much interrupted with the apprehenſions I had leaſt the Runagado, who was at <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> but a days Journey from us, knowing that the <hi>Torniella</hi> was arrived, ſhould come to enquire if we were to paſs in it into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> In effect, the thing happened as I imagined, for he came to knock at the Gate of the Monaſtery an hour before day, which when I had heard, and at the ſame time the noiſe of the Religious run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199363:43"/>to open the door, I quickly got up, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth boldly, demanded who was there? He made me this anſwer, <hi>'Tis an honeſt Man, who is come to be informed whether you are come from the Ship which is in the Road;</hi> and having told him no, he had the curioſity to know who was in that Chamber where we lay; they anſwered him that they were two <hi>Venetian</hi> Merchants; whereupon he retired to a Chamber near to that for to repoſe himſelf. Theſe good Religious did not bely themſelves, for we were clad like Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants. So ſoon as I heard theſe words, as I ſaw my ſelf expoſed to the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> and in a Country ſo remote, and ſuch an enemy to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> I waked my Companion, and made him forthwith get up.</p>
               <p>There was in that place a <hi>Venetian</hi> Merchant, who, as I had learnt, often aſſiſted other Perſons, and charitably delivered them from the hands of the <hi>Turks.</hi> He was then employed about loading a Veſſel with Goods to be ſent for <hi>Venice;</hi> as we went out of the Monaſtery we met him coming to Divine Service, and I believed that God had ſent him on purpoſe to relieve us. After I had ſaluted him, I ſaid, <hi>I know, Sir, that there are many Perſons obliged to you for the good Offices you have rendred them, finding themſelves in the ſame condition as we are; that is it which makes me believe that God has ſent you hither.</hi> I ſet forth unto him the poſture of our Affairs, and entreated his aſſiſtance; he offered forthwith to uſe all poſſible means to that end, and returning, conducted us to his Lodging. Then going out, and coming in again, he ſaid, <hi>You are not ſafe here, and there is no other remedy but to put you aboard, and there to ſtay in your Ship with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199363:43"/>coming aſhoar, but wait for a Wind; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come along with me, and I'll conduct you to your Veſſel.</hi> We went forthwith to the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, but the Sea was ſtill ſo agitated, that we could ſee neither Man nor Boat.</p>
               <p>After we had walked for ſome time upon the ſhoar, there poſted by a great number of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> of the Country, and made us much afraid; for when they came near, they looked upon us with much earneſtneſs. The Skiff of our Merchants Ship came a little after to Land with two luſty Seamen, for to load and carry Goods aboard; wherefore we approached near the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Seamen having already come on ſhoar, this good Merchant told them, <hi>Make haſte, and carry theſe two Gentlemen forthwith to the</hi> Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niella. We had no ſooner thanked him, as we were obliged, but that theſe two Seamen took and carried us in their Boat, and Rowing with all their ſtrength, notwithſtanding the Waves, which were very high, they brought us in a ſhort time to our Ship, but it was not without much danger. We got into the Veſſel, being very joyful, and acquainted the Captain with the poſture of our Affairs; and putting our ſelves under his protection, he received us very civilly, and gave us aſſurance thereof. He gave us alſo his own Cabbin, with Orders we ſhould not ſtir out of it all the day, nor to ſhew our ſelves to thoſe that ſhould come on board for to bargain for Goods. He aſſured us likewiſe, upon his word, that we had nothing to do but to repoſe our ſelves, and that if we ſhould be ſearched for, he would ſooner deliver them all the Fraight than us. This Commander was indeed a Man of the World, and loved to divert himſelf; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199363:44"/>faithful and juſt to his Word. We remained ſo pent up in that little Chamber, as in a Priſon, for three days, for the Ship was in the Road all that time for to take in her Lading.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Voyage from</hi> Cyprus <hi>to</hi> Venice.</head>
               <p>AFter we had thanked God for his Deliverance of us from ſo great a danger, we ſailed upon break of day on the 12th of <hi>April,</hi> and made the Cape at Sun-ſet. The fair weather, and the calmneſs of the Sea, made us hope for an happy Voyage, but on St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Day the Waters were ſo much agitated, when we paſſed the Cape of St. <hi>Epiphany,</hi> becauſe of the great Winds that ſtood contrary, that we were very hard put to it. The 27th of the ſame month we lowered all the Sails, and guiding the Ship only at the Helm with a great deal of addreſs and pains, we left it to the pleaſure and mercy of the Winds, ſo much was the Sea agitated at that time; then, without ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, we paſſed by <hi>Caramania, Rhodes, Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panto,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Candia,</hi> the Cape of St. <hi>John, Cerigo, Matapano,</hi> and the <hi>Morea,</hi> and drew near <hi>Venetique,</hi> to take in Refreſhments, and particularly Water, whereof we had great need. From thence we ſailed for <hi>Zant,</hi> where the Ship ſtayed the 19th of <hi>May,</hi> becauſe of a difference that aroſe between the Captain and Gunner. I believed, for to avoid ſcandal, we ought to change our Ship. In effect, after we had payed the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the <hi>Torniella</hi> what was due to him for our
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:199363:44"/>paſſage, we agreed with the Maſter of another Veſſel called the <hi>Stork,</hi> which was in the Port rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſail: We went on board it with all we had, and getting out of Port at Midnight, we ſailed on the 23d of the ſame Month, leaving <hi>Cefalonia</hi> on the Right. There was great likelihood of fair weather, but on the day after there happened ſuch a great blaſt of Wind, that tore off the great Sail of the Fore-Maſt, but that was remedied forthwith, and continuing our courſe, we left as well upon the Right as Left, <hi>Corfu,</hi> the Cape of <hi>Otranto, Cimara,</hi> or <hi>Linguetta, Saſeno,</hi> which is the Cape of the Gulph <hi>Durazzo, Caſtlenovo,</hi> which belonged ſome time to the <hi>Spaniards, Raguſo,</hi> all <hi>Dalmatia, Carnero,</hi> and divers other Places. At laſt we arrived in <hi>Iſtria</hi> on the 8th of <hi>June,</hi> two hours after Dinner time, and went aſhoar at <hi>Rovigno,</hi> where we ſaw, upon an high Hill, the Church of St. <hi>Euphenny,</hi> with five or ſix Rocks about it. Our Ship was to ſtay for ſome time there, and as we had but an hundred Miles to <hi>Venice,</hi> and that we thought it troubleſome to ſtay there ſo long, we reſolved, with two other Merchants, to hire a little Bark for to finiſh the reſt of our Voyage. This pitiful Bark had but a Mat for all its Sails; we run more danger in this our laſt paſſage, than we had done in all our courſe, for as we had got half way, there aroſe ſuch a furious Tempeſt, and the Wind ſtood ſo contrary, that out of the fear that poſſeſs'd us, we could find no better expedient than to pull down the Sail, or rather Mat, which being forced by the violence of the Wind, carried us ſometimes on one ſide, ſometimes on another, and put us in danger of periſhing. At laſt it pleaſed God to appeaſe the Wind, and give us
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199363:45"/>fair Weather, wherefore purſuing our courſe, we paſſed by <hi>Piara, Jeſole,</hi> which was ſome time deſtroyed by <hi>Attila, Marzoba, Burano, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cello,</hi> and on the 10th of the ſame Month arrived happily at <hi>Venice,</hi> three hours before Sun-ſet; but as we were come from the <hi>Levant,</hi> ſuſpected to be infected with the Plague, we were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to go aſhoar. They ſent us in our Bark to make the cuſtomary Quarantine, into a Channel far remote from the City.</p>
               <p>There were ſome of our Friends that came to viſit us, and make merry with us, for our happy Return, and ſent us Evening and Morning every thing we ſtood in need of: They reſted not till they obtained of the Gentlemen Intendants in Matters of Health, permiſſion for us to go to our Lodgings, inſomuch that we made but ſix days of our Quarantine, and being joyful for our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, we laid aſide our Merchants Habit, and took that of our Order again. After which, we ſojourned for ſome time in <hi>Venice</hi> for to refreſh our ſelves, after the tedious fatigues of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation.</p>
               <p>We parted from <hi>Venice</hi> the 23d of <hi>June</hi> for to go for <hi>Padua,</hi> and there I ſaw again, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, the ancient Schools where I had ſometimes read Publick Lectures. We parted from thence the 7th of <hi>July</hi> for <hi>Mantua,</hi> and arrived there the 8th, at <hi>Parma</hi> the 11th, <hi>Bolonia</hi> the 17th, <hi>Immola</hi> the 21th, <hi>Forli</hi> the 22th, <hi>Ceſene,</hi> my Birth-place, the 27th, and at <hi>Rimini</hi> the firſt of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> as it was my companions Country, he tarried there for ſome days, to give ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to his aged Father, whom he had not ſeen for a long time, which was the reaſon we could not get to <hi>Loretta</hi> till the 12th of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199363:45"/>ſame Month. We ſtaid there for a few days, and on the 16th ſet forth for <hi>Peruge,</hi> where we had many Acquaintance, and we made what haſte we could for to get thither the 18th; we ſtaid there for the reſt of the month, for our own conſolation and that of our Friends. We parted from thence the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> and partly out of Devotion, partly out of Curioſity, we went to <hi>Mount Corano,</hi> where there is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Houſe, in which place they live in great auſterity; thence to <hi>Alvernia</hi> and <hi>Camaldoli.</hi> We employed ſeven days in that Progreſs with much ſatisfaction, then returned to <hi>Peruge,</hi> in order to go for <hi>Rome,</hi> where we at laſt arrived on the 17th of the ſame month; whether I had no ſooner got, but I made it my buſineſs to gain admittance for to proſtrate my ſelf at his Holineſs feet, which I ſoon effected, who welcomed me kindly, and to whom I gave a particular Account of my Negotiation, wherewith he expreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be extreamly ſatisfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:199363:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE Author of this Relation is not exact enough in his Report of the <hi>Turks;</hi> firſt of all, there is but little appearance that they have taken all the Clocks of the <hi>Levant</hi> to make Artillery with them; for that Metal whereof they are compos'd is not at all proper to make Cannon. If they then depriv'd the Chriſtians of their Obedience, it was rather an Effect of their Policy than Oeconomy, for that the ſound of theſe Clocks might ſerve for a Signal for the execution of Revolts, and to give the Alarm to all in a ſhort time. Neither is it true, that the Men get up to the tops of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naretts or Steeples of the <hi>Turks,</hi> for to ſupply the want of Clocks, in crying, 'tis ſuch an hour, or ſuch an hour of the day: but the Author hath heard ſay, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> inſtead of Clocks, are ſerved with the Voices of Men, for to give notice of Prayers, from the top of the Moſchs; in effect this Officer crys with all his force three times from the top of the Minarett, <hi>Allah Ecber,</hi> that is, <hi>God is Great;</hi> then he continues to ſay for three times, <hi>Eſched en allah illah allah, I teſtifie there is no other God, but God:</hi> then he ſays again three times, <hi>Eſchen en Mohammed reſoul allah, I wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that</hi> Mahomet <hi>is his Prophet.</hi> He adds ſome other Articles, as, <hi>Hai allaſſalat, God live by Prayer; Hai alaphaleh, Live to Salvation; Allah Ecber, God is Great; L'allah illa, allah, There is no other God but God.</hi> He ſays alſo at Noon, and in the Evening, and about an hour and a quarter
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199363:46"/>after Sun-ſetting, <hi>En allah ou Malaikto falouna ala el Nabi, That God and his Angels bleſs the Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third place, the <hi>Turks</hi> come but five times a day to Prayers, as every-body knows; 'tis true, that there be two other Prayers, but they are voluntary, the firſt of which we may call that of Supererogation, ſince they are free to be at it or no, is perform'd an hour and an half before Morning-prayer; the other is done every <hi>Friday,</hi> at Nine of the Clock, but there are none but the Officers of the Moſch and ſome other Zealots that aſſiſt thereat.</p>
               <p>In the fourth place, the Author does not well uſe the Arabic words which the <hi>Turks</hi> pronounce aloud in their Moſchs; 'tis eaſie to correct them by what I am about to ſay, for they do not give to <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Quality of Companion of God, but that of <hi>Reſoul allah,</hi> that is, <hi>the Envoy of God. Mahomet</hi> affects to take the Names which God gave <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Old Teſtament, and to our Lord in the New.</p>
               <p>As to the Faſhion the <hi>Turks</hi> obſerve at their Prayers, I believe that they have taken them from the <hi>Jews,</hi> for they wag their Heads very much in the reading of the Law in their Synagogues; but the <hi>Mahometans</hi> go beyond them. 'Tis a pleaſant thing to ſee the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Children, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat in their Schools ſome Verſes of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> eſpecially when they pronounce the word <hi>Allah,</hi> how they throw their Heads backwards and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: I do not queſtion but that all theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have their Reaſons, I believe they make uſe of 'em at leaſt to hinder their ſleeping during their Prayers, which happens too often amongſt us. They ſay immediately in putting their Hands to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199363:47"/>their Ear, <hi>Allah Ecber, God is great;</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards laying them acroſs their Breaſt, <hi>Rabbena lac Elmegd, Lord, to thee the Glory:</hi> after that they proſtrate themſelves, ſaying, <hi>Allah Ecber, God is great.</hi> This laſt Action is doubtleſs an Adoration, for that is the manner of adoring amongſt the Eaſtern Nations; and we have divers Examples hereof in the Old Teſtament: 'tis alſo the way of ſaluting Perſons of great quality, 'tis uſed in reſpect to the Pope. The three Eſtates harangue the King upon their Knees; but as to Cardinals and Biſhops, they only kiſs the Border of their Robes in doing of them reverence; they are marks of a profound Reſpect, which have been introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into the Ceremonies of Religion, wherefore we ought not to ridicule theſe Proſtrations which the <hi>Turks</hi> uſe at their Prayers, for we cannot be too humble in the preſence of God. I remember to have heard a <hi>Jew</hi> ſay, that it was to be read in one of their Authors, that the Reaſon which moved them to agitate their Heads at Prayers was, for that Prayer is like unto a Flambeau, that burns the Flames off which is in continual agitation, and ſeems always to fly up; but the more learned <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, that this Cuſtom is founded upon thoſe words of <hi>David, All my bones ſhall ſay, Lord, who is like unto thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Greeks, whom the Author ſpeaks of in this Chapter, it ſeems that they have been, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to uſe theſe ſort of Movements for to divert the Jealouſie of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who would not be well ſatisfied to ſee them ſo well united with us. As the Greeks are nouriſh'd up in that averſion for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, one ought not to be aſtoniſhed if they contemn its Ceremonies, and look upon them as Prophanations; beſides that, the long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199363:47"/>Diſputes that have been between both Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches hath not a little contributed to entertain this Averſion: in the mean time, we ought not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to all the Nation a Vice that regar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s none but a few falſe Zealots; one need but conſult for this purpoſe the oriental right, bearing the Title of the Anſwers of the Patriarchs; the matters in queſtion are there propos'd, and very judiciouſly decided.</p>
               <p>The Author continues to render the <hi>Greeks</hi> odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in aggravating their ill conduct in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Penance, as if they deferred not to grant Abſolution to the Penitent for the ſpace of four or five-Years, but through a Contempt they had of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which obligeth every one in particular to communicate at leaſt once a Year: but we muſt render the <hi>Greeks</hi> Juſtice, for they follow herein for the moſt part the uſage of their Church, which is very ancient. If a new Right hath introduc'd a new Diſcipline into the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ought we for that reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all thoſe Churches which conform not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to this Diſcipline; for <hi>that which is neither againſt the Faith nor good Manners ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> It is the Duty alſo of an honeſt man and a good Chriſtian, to become conformable to the Manners and Diſcipline of them amongſt whom he lives; but 'tis certain that the Greeks, which are not latiniz'd, follow yet to this day a good part of the ancient Diſcipline in the adminiſtration of Penance: They have their penitential Books which regulate them, and it is not their Caprice which makes them impoſe one Penance ſooner than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but they follow their Canons herein. There is nothing this day more common amongſt them than to ſeparate their Penitent from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199363:48"/>for a Year or two, and ſometimes more. I ſee alſo no reaſon why the Author ſhould charge the Greeks of Ignorance and Superſtition, becauſe a Confeſſor refuſeth Abſolution to a Penitent before he calls ſeven other Prieſts for to have their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the abſolving of him. I confeſs, this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of acting may ſeem ſtrange to them who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult no other than the preſent Cuſtom; but if any takes the pains to look back towards the firſt Ages of the Church, he ſhall obſerve, that this Cuſtom was alſo in uſe at <hi>Rome.</hi> Did not the Pope <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> aſſemble the Prieſts and Biſhops which were then at <hi>Rome</hi> to deliberate about a Penance that he ought to inflict upon ſome Schiſmaticks which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter'd into the Church? 'Tis therefore no very ſurprizing thing to ſee a Papas or Greek Prieſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate with his fellow-brethren touching a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he ought to impoſe upon a man, who being engag'd in the Service of a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> had every day near occaſions to offend againſt the Ceremonies of his own Religion, whether in performing Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence on a <hi>Saturday,</hi> or in eating of Blood, or in not obſerving ſome other Article of the Greek Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline. I confeſs nevertheleſs, that when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes aſſemble about matters that require not their meeting, and with a deſign only to exact Mony, that that Abuſe ought to be condemn'd, and not the thing in it ſelf.</p>
               <p>It ſeems alſo, that the Author would ridicule the Greeks under pretence that they cauſe the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to lye upon the Ground, and in that poſture recite over him certain Prayers in form of an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, not knowing that the Greeks confeſs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſitting, and that they are content to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelves twice, to wit, at the beginning, when they demand the Benediction of the Prieſt,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199363:48"/>who for that purpoſe invokes upon them the Grace of the Holy Spirit; and at the end, when the ſame Prieſt prays alſo, that God would enable them to accompliſh the Penance impoſed upon them. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if the Greek Prieſts take Mony for granting Abſolutions, they are the more excuſable, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Miſery they are in at preſent. They have no Benefices, as our Clergy; and they are obliged to pay certain Summs to their Biſhops, as their Biſhops alſo do the ſame to the Patriarch, and finally, the Patriarch to the Grand Seignior. In a word, it may be reckon'd amongſt their Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; and if you find it not ſtrange, that the moſt part of the Latin Prieſts ſince the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the new Rights, ſubſiſt upon their Maſſes and Confeſſions, why is that blamable in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſes, who have much more reaſon, as being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a far greater neceſſity?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:199363:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chapter.</head>
               <p>THere are many things in this Chapter touching the Belief the <hi>Turks,</hi> that ſtand in need of Reformation, or further clearing. Firſt, They do not give the name of <hi>Scerif,</hi> but that of <hi>Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi,</hi> to thoſe who make the Journey to <hi>Meccha;</hi> beſides, the word <hi>Scerif</hi> ſignifies Illuſtrious, and not Saint. As <hi>Meccha</hi> is to the <hi>Turks,</hi> the ſame as the <hi>Holy Land</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were formerly to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo the <hi>Mahometans</hi> uſe divers things which are conformable to the ceremonies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> for the word <hi>Hadgi</hi> is taken from the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word <hi>Hagag,</hi> which ſignifies to celebrate a Feaſt; inſomuch that <hi>Hadgi,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> is he who makes a Journey into <hi>Meccha,</hi> for to perform there the Feaſt of Feaſts, as they ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> to go to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to keep their Paſſover. In effect, the <hi>Mahometans</hi> call the Temple of <hi>Meccha, Beit allah,</hi> the Houſe of God, which is the name the <hi>Jews</hi> gave to their Temple. There is no other place alſo where the <hi>Turks</hi> offer Sacrifice but there, as there was amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> but <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where it was permitted them to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; they give moreover the name of <hi>Corban</hi> to that Sacrifice: and, in effect, they kill a great number of Sheep, which are afterwards diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the Poor. They make at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> at the ſame time, a kind of commemorating <hi>Corban,</hi> for to repreſent the Sacrifice that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at <hi>Meccha;</hi> nevertheleſs, the Sacrifice of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> hath this reality in it, That they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199363:49"/>offer alſo there true Victims, as tho' it be but a Memorial of that which is done in the Territory of <hi>Meccha,</hi> which is a place conſecrated for that uſe. This ſame place was frequented before <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi>'s time, for the <hi>Arabs</hi> Journied thither in honour of the Progreſs of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom they believe to be Author of part of the Ceremonies that are uſed at <hi>Meccha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Prieſts are called <hi>Imams,</hi> not <hi>Santons,</hi> for <hi>Santon</hi> is taken for a kind of Religious Order. Thoſe Prieſts who apply their Cares to the Moſchs, ought to be knowing in the Alcoran; there are amongſt them others that may be called Chaplains, or Almoners, for they attend on Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who not being able to go daily to the Moſch, cauſe the Alcoran to be read unto them by theſe ſort of Almoners or Chaplains. One may add alſo to theſe another kind of Beneficiars, who much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble our Canons, and other Eccleſiaſticks, of Collegiate Churches; theſe laſt have the Alcoran divided into divers parcels, and read one Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph every day, inſomuch that it might be truly ſaid of them, <hi>Beneficium eſt propter Officium,</hi> for the Revenues of their Prebendaries conſiſt moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe ſort of Lectures, for which they are paid. There are alſo leſſer Benefices, which are as Chapels or Hoſpitals, which Princes or particular Perſons have founded, to the end they might there be pray'd for after their deaths, and that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed certain Charities ſet forth in the Title of the Foundation. I ſhall ſay nothing of the <hi>Khat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> of the Moſch, which is properly that which we call the Curate of the Pariſh; this Perſon placeth himſelf on an advanced ground, and reads what <hi>Surate</hi> or Chapter he pleaſeth. He reſerves the largeſt Chapters for <hi>Fridays,</hi> for that the Duty of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:199363:50"/>that day is longer, and that they uſe much more Adorations or Proſtrations than on all the other days of the Week. Beſides theſe Curates, they have <hi>Scheics,</hi> or Preachers, which hold the Alcoran open before them, and read ſome Verſe thereof for a Text to their Sermon: They ſet forth the different Interpretations of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctors upon that Text, and for to confirm their Aſſertions, they have recourſe to certain Narrations, which reſemble rather Fables than true Hiſtories. They enlarge alſo much upon the Moral part, and preach vigorouſly againſt Vices. As to the Religious <hi>Turks,</hi> whom the Author calls inconſiderable Perſons, there are divers ſorts of them; they are diſtinguiſhed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily by the difference of their Habits, manner of Living, and various Rules and Conſtitutions, for you ſhall find ſome that make Profeſſion of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, others of Chaſtity, others of perpetual Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Others again apply themſelves entirely to a contemplative Life, and every one carries about him the marks of his Profeſſion. Thoſe which have feathers on their Heads, pretend to diſcover there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that they are Men of Meditation, and receive Revelations. Thoſe whoſe Habits are made up with pieces of divers colours, believe by that to expoſe their Poverty to view. There are ſome alſo who carry ſomewhat at the Ear, to ſet forth their Obedience and Submiſſion to the Spirit, which tranſports them to extaſies. The Chains that ſome of them have at their Necks or Arms, are demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the vehemency of the Spirit which agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates them. They have alſo a ſort of Monks which live in Community, and Hermits that inhabit the Deſarts. Beſides theſe, there are amongſt them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Mendicants, who live upon Alms. There are others who imploy themſelves altogether to Works
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:199363:50"/>of Charity, and the good of their Neighbour; as they eſteem themſelves for the moſt part to be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely above others, ſo they ſay with the Phariſee in the Goſpel, <hi>I am not as other men.</hi> Every one of them believes he is in the true ſtate of Perfection, but in the mean time they differ extreamly in their Sentiments; for one Sect is perſwaded that there is nothing but the Grace and Mercy of God that can ſave Men; others, on the contrary, pretend they cannot be ſaved without good Works; and that our Salvation depends entirely upon the uſe we make of our Liberty. Theſe laſt pray much more to God than the others, and they riſe up in the night for to ſing together <hi>L'alla illa allah.</hi> — Every one ſupports his opinion with Viſions and Miracles, and they have the Hiſtory of their Saints, which they endeavour to imitate. Theſe Religious can never agree with the <hi>Imams</hi> or Prieſts of the Moſques, they bear them envy, and pretend that they lead a better Life; and that their Prayers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are more efficacious, and for that reaſon the Alms of the People ought rather to belong to them than to the Prieſts. But the Prieſts make anſwer to that, That the Alms are only due to them, upon the account of their Benefices, which oblige them to take care of the People; and that it belongs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to them, and not to the Religious, to teach the Law of the Prophet. They hold that there has been a great diſpute had about this ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sultan <hi>Amurath</hi> the Second, who was obliged to ſupport the Religious, under the pretence of a Miracle which befel in their favour, altho' reaſon and good ſence made him incline to the part of the Prieſts and Officers of the Moſques. It was the ſame <hi>Amurath,</hi> who ſeeing himſelf in great danger in the Battle of <hi>Varne,</hi> againſt the <hi>Hungarians</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:199363:51"/>and <hi>Poles,</hi> made a Vow, if he eſcaped, he would confine himſelf into a Monaſtery, and do Penance there the remainder of his days. In effect, the <hi>Mahometans</hi> make alſo Vows, and the Religions entertain them in that Cuſtom as much as they can, for they are benefitted thereby; and they have likewiſe, to that end, certain days of Devotion ſet apart, when they go to viſit the Sepulchres of their moſt famous Saints, for to obtain fair Weather or Rain. In a word, to recommend unto them all their Affairs; and if one would believe them, they want neither Hiſtories nor Miracles for to give Authority to their Devotions.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Mahometaniſm</hi> is a Communion of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, we ought not to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to ſee amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> divers things which are obſerved amongſt us; thoſe which have a perfect cognizance of theſe two Religious, may eaſily ſhew the Original of moſt part of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan</hi> Ceremonies, and if I were not afraid leaſt that would detain me too long, I would produce divers Examples hereof, but I will ſimply confine my ſelf to that which my Brother hath treated of; wherefore I paſs on to their Chaplets.</p>
               <p>'Tis true as our Author has obſerved, that the grains of their Chaplets are not unequal according to the faſhion of the Chriſtians; they do not recite alſo paſt two different Prayers, and by conſequence have no need of divers grains for to keep them in mind. They have, nevertheleſs, ſome diſtinction in their Chaplets, that conſiſt of an hundred Beads, for they divide them into three parts, and ſay at one of thee parts, 33 times, <hi>Souban lallah;</hi> that is, <hi>God is praiſe-worthy.</hi> Upon the other, <hi>Elha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel allah; Glory to God.</hi> And laſtly, upon the third, <hi>Allah Lober, God is great.</hi> Theſe three
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:199363:51"/>times 33, making no more than fourſcore and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, they have therefore added another Prayer at the head of the Chaplet, for to make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber an hundred; 'tis in that their Beads are a little like unto ours, for beſides the crown, or the round of their Chaplet, there is another thing about, which makes up the place of that in ours, which is called the croſs of the Chaplet. That Chaplet, according to my judgment, hath taken its original from <hi>Mea Beracot,</hi> or the hundred Benedictions which the <hi>Jews</hi> are obliged to recite daily. The <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> have this common, that they almoſt do nothing without pronouncing ſome praiſe or benediction; but as the <hi>Mahometans</hi> have reduced theſe hundred Benedictions into three ſorts of Thankſgivings, that hath obliged them to divide that Chaplet into three parts, as the Chriſtians have divided theirs into tens, for to obſerve the manner of their <hi>Paters</hi> and <hi>Ave's;</hi> beſides their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing of that Chaplet in particular, they have Singing-men for to ſing them aloud in their Moſques.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Mahomet</hi> forbad the eating of Pork, he had no other deſign than that he might not ſeparate the <hi>Jews</hi> too far from his Religion, which is the reaſon that the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> who are half <hi>Jews,</hi> take a great deal of precaution that they eat no other Animals whom they eſteem unclean; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which our Author produceth is a merry Tale only. As to Wine, it is not directly forbidden, and it ſeems that it was rather Councel than Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. Perhaps <hi>Mahomet</hi> was deſirous that his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould have that in common with the <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> of the Old Teſtament, for to diſcover its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and beſides, there is nothing that brings greater order and utility to the State than his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:199363:52"/>As the <hi>Turks</hi> are more ſober than we, they ſubmit themſelves without difficulty to this Rule; they bring other Reaſons for this injunction than that which our Author produceth, but one ought not to rely upon all the Hiſtories which the <hi>Turks</hi> ſet forth, for to illuminate and ſupport the difficulties that are found in their Religion, for they make no ſcruple to invent them at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, wherein they have imitated the <hi>Jews,</hi> who ſtuff their Books with infinity of Fables. This Vice is alſo common to all the Chriſtians of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> as may be ſeen in their Books, wherefore we ought to be cautious of them.</p>
               <p>'Tis certain that the <hi>Turks</hi> have taken their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions from the <hi>Jews,</hi> for they retain their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies touching the Faſhion and Manner of waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they have alſo imitated them in their Praiſes and Benedictions which they recite, when they waſh either their Hands, Face, or any other part of their body, but nevertheleſs, it ſeems that they have no ſet form of Benedictions as the <hi>Jews</hi> have, for I have read differences upon that ſubject. They purifie themſelves always before Prayers, and 'tis for that reaſon that they then waſh their hands for three times, and at the ſame conjuncture recite a Praiſe to God; they obſerve the ſame thing at the waſhing of their faces, and other parts of their bodies. I'll ſay nothing here of their Baths, for that would detain me too long, I'll only obſerve that they retain ſo great a veneration for theſe ſort of Purifyings, that they ſeem not to have retained Circumciſions but through coherency with theſe Ablutions, for they pretend with the <hi>Jews,</hi> that if the leaſt part of their bodies remain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d unw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed, the bathing would be worth nothing; ſo that it was for that reaſon principally that they eſtabliſhed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:199363:52"/>Circumciſion, to the end that the skin being not the part which was hidden of that skin before the Circumciſion, might remain all open, and that ſo it might be waſhed; therefore they place Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion amongſt the different kinds of purity and cleanneſs, which they are obliged to obſerve. 'Tis for that reaſon that they take care to circumciſe thoſe that are Naturalized as little as they can, and 'tis no ordinary thing to ſee perſons thus uſed from their birth, ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> have a Law which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides in that caſe, that 'tis ſufficient to draw blood, and afterwards they are to be eſteemed <hi>Jews</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other form of Circumciſion. The <hi>Jews</hi> do alſo affirm that <hi>Adam, Seth, Noah,</hi> and divers others of the ancient Patriarchs, were circumciſed from their birth, and they ground it upon this, That it was impoſſible for them to enter into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice without being circumciſed. The <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> Doctors affirm alſo, That their Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> was circumciſed; which they have aſſuredly taken from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Books.</p>
               <p>The Author does not exactly relate the Hiſtory of the Cord that traverſeth the Valley of <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> and upon which all the World muſt paſs for to preſent themſelves to Judgment: That which gave occaſion to this Fable is, That the <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> believed, that at the laſt day of Judgment, all the World ſhall paſs upon a thread as ſmall as a hair, which will be extended from one end of Hell to another, and that the Juſt ſhall paſs quicker than Lightning over this Bridge, whereas thoſe that will be loaden with a great number of ſins, ſhall crawl along with much difficulty, and fall at laſt into Hell. 'Tis eaſie to ſee that they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this Fable from the words of the Evangeliſt, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the way which leads to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:199363:53"/>is very narrow.</hi> But as I have already ſaid, the People of the <hi>Levant</hi> pleaſe themſelves much with theſe ſort of imaginations which Men of Senſe will regard as Parables, and they are but Simple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons that take them for true Hiſtories.</p>
               <p>I ſhall touch ſomewhat here of the Theology of the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> for a ſupply to that which is wanting in the deſcription which our Author made of their Belief. He very well obſerved, that the <hi>Turks</hi> honour indeed the memory of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but that they will not acknowledge him for God, nor for the Son of God. In effect, one of the firſt Inſtructions which they give to their Children in their Catechiſm, is, <hi>That God hath no Wife, that he is neither Male nor Female, and that conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is uncapable of Generation.</hi> Which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the words of <hi>Mahomet</hi> in his Alcoran, where he expreſly ſaith, <hi>That God hath no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for he hath no Wife;</hi> and the moſt able <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> expound theſe words of the eternal God to his Son, <hi>This day have I begotten thee,</hi> by theſe, <hi>have I brought up and nouriſhed thee.</hi> Thus you may ſee how they fortify themſelves againſt the Myſtery of the Trinity.</p>
               <p>The firſt Axiom of their Theology is taken from theſe words of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat ſo often, <hi>Hear, O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one;</hi> for they ſubſtitute in place thereof, <hi>L'allah illa allah, There is no other God but God:</hi> Inſomuch that it may be ſaid, that their <hi>L'allah</hi> is the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Scema</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> they differ however from them, in that they add to their <hi>L'allah</hi> theſe other words, <hi>En Mahommed reſoul allah,</hi> And <hi>Mahomet is the Envoy of God;</hi> and that, without doubt, in imitation of that which our Lord hath ſaid in St. <hi>John, This is life eternal, that thou ſhouldſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:199363:53"/>know the true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</hi> There is nothing more often repeated in the Alcoran than theſe words, <hi>La illah hou; There is no other God but he.</hi> I have an ancient Copy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, where they are always written in Capital Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for to diſtinguiſh them from the reſt of the Text, as alſo many other expreſſions like unto 'em. As for Example: <hi>Va illakcom illah vahhid; And your God is God alone. Ana illah la illah illa ana, I am God, and there is no other God but me. La illah illa ant, There is no other God but thou. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> hath affected this ſo frequent a repetition of the ſame thing, for to conform himſelf to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who affect it yet more; and that which plainly proves that the <hi>Mahometans</hi> imitated the <hi>Jews,</hi> is becauſe they retain it even to their geſtures. For when the <hi>Santons</hi> ſay, <hi>La illah illa hou, There is no other God but him,</hi> you would ſay they are mad, ſo much they agitate and wagg their heads from one ſide to another, crying as Men poſſeſs'd with the Devil. The <hi>Jews</hi> do the ſame thing when they recite the Prayer or Benediction <hi>Scema, Iſrael</hi>— which is <hi>la illah</hi>—of the <hi>Turks,</hi> for they turn their heads towards the four Parts of the World, for to notifie that God is every where, and Lord of the Univerſe. Theſe <hi>Santons</hi> moreover, in ſinging the word <hi>hou,</hi> him, which is the laſt of the Praiſe, <hi>la illah</hi>— prolong the ſinging thereof as long as they have breath to draw, and when they are at the end, they make an effort for to pronounce it louder, as if they breathed their laſt ſigh. The <hi>Jews</hi> obſerve the ſame thing at the laſt word of their <hi>Scoma,</hi> which is, <hi>Had, one,</hi> for they reſt ſometimes a whole hour upon that word; and when they are at the laſt letter, they throw their heads here and there, and you would take them for
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:199363:54"/>mad. And ſo the <hi>Santons</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> which imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them, are in that but Repreſentatives of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as in the moſt part of their other Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Axiom of their Theology is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in theſe words, <hi>Ou Mohammed reſoul allah, And</hi> Mahomet <hi>is the Envoy of God.</hi> Of all the qualities that <hi>Mahomet</hi> takes in his Alcoran, this ſame is the principal, 'tis writ in great Characters in the Manuſcript I have already ſpoken of; and when any one embraceth the Turkiſh Belief, they are content to have him only pronounce theſe words, <hi>La illah illallah, ou Mohammed reſoul, allah, There is no other God but God, and</hi> Mahomet <hi>is the Envoy of God.</hi> 'Tis in this ſence that our Author ought to be underſtood, when he ſaith. They worſhip no other God but <hi>Mahomet,</hi> for that they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be a true Prophet, whom God hath ſent to reform Religion. And 'tis upon that Miſſion that their Belief is grounded, inſomuch that it is neceſſary they ſhould make mention of it in their Profeſſion of Faith: Not but that they have regard to <hi>Moſes,</hi> our Lord, and the other Prophets, but as our Author obſerves, <hi>Mahomet,</hi> according to their ſentiments, is a greater Prophet than they, for they hold him for the Envoy of God by way of Excellency, and for the Comforter that is ſpoken of in the Goſpel. They believe that God hath ſent from Heaven Sacred Books to divers Prophets, and that he made uſe for that purpoſe of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Angel <hi>Gabriel;</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> received the Law in that manner, <hi>David</hi> the Pſalms, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> the Goſpel, and other Prophets other Books, to the number of 104, but that ſince the deſcent of the Alcoran, which was in coming down no leſs than 23 years, theſe Books are no longer Authentick, and ſo ought not to be followed as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rules.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:199363:54"/>
               <p>Beſides the quality of Prophet, which the <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> give to our Lord, the Alcoran ſtiles him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Kalmet allah, The word of God;</hi> which, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, muſt not be underſtood as if they believed him to be that Word which is in God from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but after the manner that the <hi>Jews</hi> call the Prophets, the Word of God. And 'tis in that Sence that the <hi>Socinians</hi> expound the Goſpel of St. <hi>John,</hi> where our Lord is called the <hi>Word,</hi> which they have aſſuredly taken from the <hi>Jews.</hi> There is nevertheleſs a certain Sect of <hi>Mahometans,</hi> which, according to the Report of <hi>Abraham Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelenſis,</hi> a <hi>Maronite,</hi> believe that Jeſus Chriſt being the <hi>Word</hi> he ought to be God, for that the <hi>Word</hi> is uncreated; but there is a great deal of appearance, that that uncreated Being which they attribute to our Lord in quality of the <hi>Word,</hi> is no other thing but that ſame uncreated eternal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which is attributed to their Alcoran, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who ſay alſo that their Law was before the creation of the World, which ought to be underſtood of the Ideas of God. The Word of God is no other in that place, according to the ſence of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctors, but his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and as our Lord was born without a Father in an extraordinary manner; thus, ſay they, that he is the Word by way of excellency, having no other Parent but that ſame Commandment of God, who created the World out of nothing. For the <hi>Mahometans</hi> believe alſo, as well as we, that Jeſus Chriſt was born of a Virgin, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs is no great Miracle in their eyes, for they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have amongſt them divers Perſons born in a Supernatural manner; and as the <hi>Arabs</hi> are leſs knowing in Phyſick than Metaphyſick, they eaſily believe the Miraculous Births of theſe donatives of Heaven.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:199363:55"/>
               <p>They have two ſorts of Theology, to wit, Poſitive and Scholaſtick: The Poſitive Theology is ſupported by the Alcoran and Tradition: Inſtead of that, the Scholaſtick Theology is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Reaſon. There are amongſt them Doctors that reject the laſt as new, and invented by Man, and pretend that it deſtroys the true Theology, which ought to have no other Principle than the Word of God; that is, The Alcoran and Tradition, but the wiſer ſort believe that the Scholaſtick Theology was produced with time as a neceſſary Evil, and that 'tis very uſeful for to refute new Hereſies; they call it <hi>Alam alcalam,</hi> which ſignifies a Science of Words or Reaſoning. Thus <hi>Pocoke,</hi> in the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating of <hi>Abul fagarius,</hi> interprets <hi>Alam alcalam</hi> no otherwiſe than <hi>Scholastick Theology.</hi> In effect, their Theology is like unto that they learn in our Schools, and draws its Original from the <hi>Arabs,</hi> who have tranſlated the Books of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> into their Language, and apply themſelves ſolely to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicks, inſomuch that the <hi>Latins</hi> are beholding to them at this day for all their more ſubtil Parts in their Philoſophy and Scholaſtick Theology, for the firſt Latin Tranſlations of the Books of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> came from the Book of <hi>Averroes,</hi> which hath been tranſlated into Latin, and we have been alſo for ſome time, without reading <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the Greek. One ought not to be ſurprized, that the <hi>Latins</hi> and <hi>Arabs</hi> handle their Theology in the ſame manner, ſince they have extracted their method from the ſame Fountain; there are nevertheleſs ſome <hi>Arabs,</hi> who rather follow the method of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> than <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for that this laſt ſeems to them baſe and unworthy the Majeſty of God. For your better underſtanding, you muſt know that there are two ways of ſpeaking of the Attributes of God,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:199363:55"/>the one is drawn from <hi>Plato,</hi> and the other from <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> the firſt is all divine, and regards God but in himſelf; the other all humane, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders God in reſpect to his Creatures. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> hath follow'd the firſt manner of ſpeaking of God, St. <hi>Thomas</hi> on the contrary follow'd the ſecond. The <hi>Arabs</hi> are divided amongſt themſelves upon that point; for the one will have the Eſſence of God to be ſo ſimple in it ſelf, that we cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute unto him an Underſtanding, a Will, a Power, nor any other Perfections and Attributes that are ordinarily given him; 'tis not that they ſay, <hi>God knows not, ſees not, and hath no Power;</hi> but they believe that God doth all this by his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; which is ſo ſimple, that we ought not to obſerve any thing that may diminiſh the Idea of that Simplicity <hi>which comes to paſs,</hi> ſay they, <hi>in giving Attributes to God;</hi> for this word <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute</hi> ſuppoſeth ſomething upon which it falleth, and whereof it may be affirmed. Add moreover to this, that they deny theſe <hi>Attributes,</hi> to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate as far as poſſibly they can the Perſons from the Trinity which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> place in God: Others on the contrary pretend that theſe ſort of <hi>Attributes</hi> are no way incompatible with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence. In a word, they fall into the ſame Diſputes as we do in regard to the <hi>Attributes</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of God: for there are ſome who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh theſe <hi>Attributes,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> as do the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> and others who reject that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſupport themſelves with Reaſons like unto them we read in the Books of the <hi>Thomiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, we acknowledge two ſorts of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, one of which is called Negative, for that, in regard to many things we may conceive, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they may be ſaid of God: and the other Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:199363:56"/>for that it affirms of God all thoſe things that include no Imperfections. So the <hi>Arabs</hi> have both the one and the other Theology; for there are ſome of them who ſay, that God is not a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but that He is above Subſtance; that He is not Power, but that He is above Power: In a word, they place God above all that we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or expreſs by our Words. This ſort of Theology hath been in uſe ſince the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, and is yet to this day much in eſteem. As to the Affirmative Theology, there are amongſt them a number of Sects, which yet do not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether accord, and ſpeak not all in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Perfections of God: The <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctors glory alſo they are divided into many Sects.</p>
               <p>You muſt nevertheleſs obſerve, that this diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Opinion is no ways hurtful to the State; for they all agree in the fundamental Articles of Religion; and as the fundamental Articles are very few in number, they have an entire liberty to diſpute of an Infinity of important points, and judge of 'em as they pleaſe, without being reputed Hereticks or Schiſmaticks for it. This great Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion paſſeth amongſt them for a War of Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks, where one has one Sentiment, another ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as amongſt the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> and <hi>Thomiſts;</hi> they ſay, that all that ought to be believ'd is contain'd in the <hi>Alcoran</hi> and <hi>Aſſona</hi> or <hi>Tradition;</hi> but that there are certain difficult points therein, about which the Doctors ought to be conſulted, and whoſe Deciſion they ought to ſtand to; however, they do not believe that the Deciſions of their Doctors are infallible, for Probability alone ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to put their Conſciences in repoſe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they might be falſe, they do not ſin in credit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:199363:56"/>of them, <hi>For,</hi> ſay they, <hi>God hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe that are not knowing in the Law to follow the Doctors that inſtruct them, and not to examine too ſcrupulouſly if their Deciſions be true:</hi> Beſides, 'tis a great point of their policy not to inſiſt, but upon a few fundamental and neceſſary points of Salvation; for it were impoſſible but that of ſuch great Philoſophers they ſhould produce a great number of Hereſies, if their Religion had conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of many Articles of Faith, and of difficult Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. This great Liberty therefore which they have to ſpeak at their pleaſure of all matters of Religion, that are not included in the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Articles, hath produc'd an infinity of Sects, who all endeavour to deſtroy one-another, for that every Sect believes its own Principles uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable: They handle with much Subtilty the ſame Queſtions which we do in the Schools; for example, in regard to the Attributes of God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which I have already remark'd, they examine all the Divine Power if ſuch a thing is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible or impoſſible, if God can do Evil, and if alſo he can do what he will; how many ſorts of Wills there be in God; whether it be that Will which is from all Eternity, or that ſame Will within the time: They diſpute of Predeſtination, of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Man, if he produceth his Actions him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or is it God alone who is the Author, and that Man ſerves but for a paſſive Inſtrument, who hath not in himſelf the Principle of Action.</p>
               <p>One Sect attributes all to God, as being the Cauſe of all things: others on the contrary give all to the Creatures, and will have, that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf without having need to be occupied about our Affairs. There are ſome of them who pretend that God is not the Cauſe of our Faith,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:199363:57"/>but that it comes of it ſelf, and from our own good diſpoſitions: Others are of a contrary Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who go ſo far as to deſtroy all the Liberty of Man, from whom they remove all ſorts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, and ſay, <hi>that God conſiders not our Merits, but his own Will alone; and 'tis He that hardens the Hearts of whom He pleaſeth, and is no leſs the Author of Evil than of Good.</hi> This Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which is very common amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> is founded upon the Idea which they have of all the Divine power, to whom they attribute all things, as if the Creatures were but meer Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. They believe, for example, that it is God that produceth heat in the Hand, and not the Fire. That the Victuals which we eat doth not nouriſh us, but that it is God alone that doth that in us; <hi>For,</hi> ſay they, <hi>there is no other Mover but He.</hi> there are ſome who keep in the medium of theſe, and place neither Conſtraint nor abſolute Neceſſity in the Will, but yet do not attribute ſo great and abſolute an Indifference thereto. Finally, they hold great Diſputes touching the Liberty of the Bleſſed: ſome believe that the Liberty of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is a true Liberty; others pretend that it me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits rather the Name of Neceſſity than Liberty, having no Indifference. The nature of Habit which hath been produced long ſince in our Schools is not unknown to them, for they there diſpute of Faith, if it be an Habit; if that Habit be ſimple or no; if it be acquired all at once, or by degrees. <hi>Calvin</hi> might have found Maſters amongſt the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> who might have read him Lectures of Faith and Good Works; for there are ſome of them who have writ before him, <hi>that the Faithful can never loſe the Faith; that neither Murder, nor Adultery, nor the other great Sins, can hinder him
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:199363:57"/>from being always of the number of true Believers, unleſs he ſay the Sins that he committed were with permiſſion, for then he ſins out of pure malice.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they cannot agree amongſt themſelves about the diſtinction of Faith, if it comprehends in it Works or no; and they ſearch out with much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, if it's poſſible to be ſaved without Faith, and that being ſuch as they ought to believe of them who are in the utmoſt parts of the Earth, and have never heard ſpeak of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> many believe that in that caſe Faith is not ſo abſolutely neceſſary, and that then they may be ſaved by the meer Light of Reaſon, as 'tis to be feard ſome have in the ſame manner been ſaved under the Old Teſtament. They have alſo very great Diſputes touching ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit and implicit Faith. There are ſome who teach 'tis ſufficient to have an explicit Belief of God and <hi>Mahomet;</hi> that as to other Articles of Faith, 'tis enough to believe them implicitly and in groſs; and they found this upon a Principle that is very common to the <hi>Turks,</hi> to wit, that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Truth there is no need to know nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it; that God puniſheth not the Faithful for not taking greater care to be inſtructed in their Belief: nevertheleſs, they are never permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to uſe Equivocations when they are queſtion'd about their Faith, for then they are obliged to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer without heſitation, whether they are <hi>Muſſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> or true Believers.</p>
               <p>Altho' the <hi>Mahometans</hi> are great Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, yet that hinders not their having amongſt them Sects which attribute all to Senſe, and who believe that God is a Body, and that what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of him is to be taken literally. In a word, thoſe have the ſame Opinion of God as the ancient <hi>Anthropomorphites.</hi> There are ſome alſo who are
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:199363:58"/>ſo far from conſidering God in himſelf, according to the method of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in him all the Perfections that may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that they purſue on the contrary the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who regarded not the Ideas in themſelves, for that he believed them to be Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera's, but formed Ideas after the induction of particular things. Theſe ſort of People pretend that God knows not things but after they are come to paſs; that that which is ordinarily called the future Contingent cannot be known of God by the Principles of <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> That that which is not cannot be known. The <hi>Socinians,</hi> who make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſo refin'd a Philoſophy, and according to which they regulate all Religion, are but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of theſe <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctors.</p>
               <p>They are moreover divided amongſt themſelves about the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> I will not touch upon the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Diſputes touching the reading of that Book, which was very different, and which obliged them to reſt contented at laſt with the Limitation of certain Pricks which ſerve for Vowels, as the <hi>Jews</hi> have done with the Hebrew Text of the Bible, and who have alſo compos'd their Grammar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Arabic, I ſhall ſpeak only of certain Sects which <hi>Abraham Ecchelenſis</hi> reports to be unwilling to receive all the Surates or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Alcoran as canonical, pretending that the Surate of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which contains the Hiſtory of that Patriarch, is in their eſteem Apocryphal. And the <hi>Perſians</hi> receive not for authentic certain Verſes of the Alcoran, which are received by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:199363:58"/>
               <p>Beſides their Alcoran, they depend much upon Tradition, and they have an <hi>Aſſonna,</hi> which is the ſame thing as the Miſna of the <hi>Jews:</hi> however, you may find a ſort of <hi>Puritans</hi> amongſt them who take the Alcoran alone for their Rule, not believing that the Words of Men can oblige them to any thing in Conſcience, and under pain of Sin. As to their manner of expounding the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran, ſome conform themſelves entirely to the Letter, others fall upon Allegories, believing it cannot be literally underſtood, but that there are diverſe meanings conceal'd under the Letter; which they do in imitation of the Jews, who ſay, that the Scripture hath ſeventy-two Panims or Faces. In ſhort, ſome follow the literal ſence, others the moral, and others confine themſelves principally to the myſtical ſence; they add more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that Religion cannot ſubſiſt without ſome Author authenticly to decide all the Difficulties that occurr; others finally are of that opinion, that without <hi>their Sect</hi> there is no Salvation.</p>
               <p>They have moreover a kind of Canon-Law wherein they diſtinguiſh a Divine Right from that which is but a poſitive Right. They have alſo a great number of Caſuiſts of all ſorts of Sects, but the moſt judicious <hi>Turks</hi> have no eſteem for all theſe Caſuiſts, from an Opinion they hold, that they ought to have recourſe to the Ancients. They prefer, amongſt others, a certain Doctor, whom they call <hi>Abuhaſine,</hi> for that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that that ſame perſon hath followed more exactly than others the Text of the Alcoran and Tradition, whereas the greateſt part of the new Doctors ſeparate themſelves from it, through too much reaſoning.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:199363:59"/>
               <p>I might have here many things to ſay touching their Morals, but I perceive I have already too far digreſſed: one may ſee more at large a part of that which I have related touching the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> in a Book of <hi>Abraham Ecchelenſis,</hi> entitul'd, <hi>De Origine nominis Papae,</hi> and in the Notes which <hi>Pocock</hi> hath joyned to that which he cauſed to be printed of <hi>Abel Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius.</hi> I have taken the other part from the Books of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctors, from whence one may eaſily judge that the Followers of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met are not ſo ignorant in their Religion, as is ordinarily imagin'd. 'Tis true, that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to the <hi>Arabians</hi> for all the Subtilty of their knowledge in Theology, but they have now very learned Books written in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> Languages. The Catechiſms alſo which they teach their Children at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſpeak of God in a very ſublime manner; and to the end the Reader may judge hereof, I will relate here the Words of the firſt Chapter of a Catechiſm compoſed in <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> by <hi>Mahomet Ben pir Ali; That Worſhip is due to God alone, who hath no Companion, nor any like unto him; that He hath no need of eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor ſleeping; and that 'tis altogether impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he can be ſubject to theſe ſorts of Infirmities and Imperfections; that he is neither in Heaven nor in the Earth, nor on the right nor on the left, nor above nor below, nor behind nor before, for he takes up no place; that he hath alſo neither form nor manner of being, neither Head nor Ear, nor Tongue nor Mouth, nor Hand nor Foot; that his Eſſence hath neither beginning nor ending; that he exiſts of himſelf; and that his Being is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the ſame eſtate:</hi> Moreover, <hi>That God
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:199363:59"/>hath created the World out of nothing; that he can annihilate it in a moment by his only Will; that nothing is hard for him to do; that it is as eaſie for him alſo to create ſeven Heavens, and ſeven Earths, as the leaſt Crumb of the World; that the Creatures bring him neither Loſs nor Profit.</hi> In the two fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapters the Author ſpeaks extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well of the Life of God, of his knowledge of his Will, in what manner thoſe places are to be explained wherein it is ſaid, <hi>He ſpeaks and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands.</hi> The <hi>Perſians</hi> alſo expound in the ſame manner all that regard the Divine Perfections; they ſpeak very exactly of the Unity of God, of his Eternity, Independance, Knowledge, Power, Life, Will; how he ſees all things without Eyes; how he underſtands without Ears; that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways was, is, and always will be; that he is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Body nor Subſtance. In a word, moſt part of the Mahometans, whether <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Perſians,</hi> treat of theſe matters almoſt in the ſame manner as we ſee them treated of by the learned <hi>R. Moyſe,</hi> and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:199363:60"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the Ninth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE Patriarch of the <hi>Maronites</hi> complained, that the Pope had ſent him but a ſimple Brief inſtead of a ſolemn Bull, and gave him not the Title of Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> as the other Popes his Predeceſſors had done. I know not why <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth followed not in this the Example of his Predeceſſors, for the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeldom differs from its uſage, and when they have once conferred a Title, they are not afterwards accuſtomed to refuſe it, for they do nothing there but upon good deliberation: It might happen that Pope <hi>Clement</hi> acted thus with that Patriarch out of the Uncertainty he was of his Belief, founded upon the relation that had been lately made him at <hi>Rome. Paul</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond writing, in the Year 1468, to <hi>Peter</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> gave him the Quality of <hi>Reverend Brother</hi> Peter, <hi>Patriarch of the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites <hi>entituled of</hi> Antioch. The <hi>Jacobites</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume alſo the ſame Title of <hi>Patriarch of Antioch;</hi> and it is <hi>at this</hi> day no extraordinary thing to ſee in the <hi>Levant</hi> divers <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of the ſame Church, for ſince the Eaſtern Nations have been divided into ſo many Sects, every Sect would have its own Patriarch; the Patriarch of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> takes ordinarily the Name of <hi>Peter,</hi> for that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they affect that Name the more, ſince they have been united to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:199363:60"/>
               <p>As to the two Deacons mention'd by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, theſe apply themſelves ſolely to the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities; and it ſeems the Patriarchs of the <hi>Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> would imitate the Apoſtles when they ſaid to their Diſciples, <hi>'Tis not good to leave the Word of God to ſerve at Tables:</hi> wherefore they diſcharged themſelves of all Temporal Affairs, and left them to the management of the Deacons they choſe for that purpoſe. This was the occaſion of the eſtabliſhment of the Deacons, and the <hi>Maronites</hi> ſeem to have retained this Apoſtolic Diſcipline; for their Patriarch applys himſelf ſolely to Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things. They give to theſe two Deacons the Quality of Lords, for to diſtinguiſh them from the ordinary Deacons that officiate at the Altars, and we ought rather to call the former <hi>Governors,</hi> or <hi>Adminiſtrators of the Temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> than <hi>Deacons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I believe the Author has made uſe of the word <hi>Deacon,</hi> for that the <hi>Syriack</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick</hi> words which the <hi>Maronites</hi> make uſe of to expreſs the Name of that Charge, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtrators.</hi> However it be, certain it is, that theſe Deacons have had formerly the adminiſtration of the Temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that that Charge render'd them very conſiderable; but they grew inſolent, ſo that the Church was obliged to make Canons to moderate them. There is no ſuch thing to be ſeen in the Deacons of Mount <hi>Libanus,</hi> although they have more Authority than the Deacons of the Church formerly had.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:199363:61"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the Eleventh Chapter.</head>
               <p>I Have ſomewhat to ſay concerning the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> which the Abbot would have to be derived from the Abbot <hi>Maron;</hi> he follows in that the common Opinion of the <hi>Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> for in the Preface they have prefix'd to their Caldeck Maſs printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> they pretend they have had their Name from St. <hi>Maron,</hi> whoſe Life <hi>Theodoret</hi> has written, and for to confirm it they cite an Epiſtle of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to the ſame <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> which he wrote unto him during his Exile: and they add, that the Monaſtery which bore afterwards the Name of St. <hi>Maron,</hi> was very conſiderable at the beginning of the Sixth Century, ſince <hi>Alexander</hi> Abbot of St. <hi>Maron</hi> was the firſt that ſubſcribed the Letter which the Archimandrites or Abbots of <hi>Syria</hi> wrote to Pope <hi>Hormiſdas. Gabriel Sconita,</hi> and <hi>John He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonita, Maronites,</hi> in a little Treatiſe they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, touching the Manners and Religion of the <hi>Levantines,</hi> are alſo of the ſame Opinion, yet without rejecting the Sentiments of them who believe that the Name of <hi>Maronite</hi> came of a certain Country in Mount <hi>Libanus,</hi> called <hi>Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia;</hi> but they cannot endure to be made deſcended from the heretical <hi>Maron,</hi> and do maintain, that there was never any ſuch of that Name. I will
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:199363:61"/>add to their Sentiments that which <hi>Abraham Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelenſis</hi> ſaith, to wit, that St. <hi>Maron</hi> gave firſt the Name to all the Monks of the ſecond <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and that after the Council of <hi>Calcedon</hi> all the <hi>Syrians,</hi> who defended the Decrees of that Council againſt the <hi>Eutichians, Dioſcorians,</hi> and <hi>Aciphales,</hi> were called <hi>Maronites;</hi> but this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not <hi>F. Morin,</hi> to whom he writ, to follow a contrary Opinion, which is ſupported with the Teſtimony of <hi>William de Syr,</hi> who reports but what he hath ſeen himſelf, and what paſſed in his time.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Maronites</hi> then, according to that Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extract their Original from a certain Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick named <hi>Maron:</hi> After they had been ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church about Five hundred Years, they made an Abjuration of their Hereſie in the hands of <hi>Aimeriek</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who lived in the time of <hi>William de Syr,</hi> and was the third Latin <hi>Patriarch</hi> of that Church: They were before <hi>Monothelites,</hi> and acknowledg'd but one Will and one Operation in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>James de Vitris</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Accon</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Marin Sanat,</hi> are alſo of the ſame opinion touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Maronites.</hi> We may add to theſe Proofs the Authority of <hi>Eutychius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> who ſpoke in his Annals of a certain Monk called <hi>Maron,</hi> who lived in the time of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Maurice,</hi> and who admitted in Jeſus Chriſt but one Will, and one Operation, altho' he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd in him two Natures: Then he ſaid, that this Monk infected many perſons with his Hereſie, and that thoſe who followed his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion were called <hi>Maronites.</hi> The ſame Author ſpeaks often afterwards hereof in his Annals,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:199363:62"/>and makes mention of thoſe who followed that Sect: He affirms, that the Emperor <hi>Heraclius</hi> was a <hi>Maronite,</hi> and that he did many Kindneſſes to thoſe of that Belief. He attributes moreover the Hereſie of the <hi>Maronites</hi> to many Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople, Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and alſo to Pope <hi>Honorius. Philip Mazerius,</hi> in the Life he hath writ of <hi>Peter Thomas,</hi> the Apoſtolic Nuncio in the <hi>Levant,</hi> who died at <hi>Famaguſta</hi> in 1366, treats of the Schiſms of the <hi>Maronites</hi> of that Country; the Author takes the Quality of Chancellor of the Kingdom of <hi>Cyprus</hi> upon him, and he lived at the ſame time as he whoſe Life he wrote, having accompanied him in part of his Travels. Thoſe <hi>Maronites</hi> of <hi>Cyprus</hi> perſiſted in the Errors of the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> even to the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Fourth, in 1445. Their Biſhip, named <hi>Elie,</hi> made Abjuration of them, together with all the Nation between the Hands of <hi>Andrew</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Coloſs,</hi> and ſent a Perſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to <hi>Rome,</hi> who did the ſame in his name; as <hi>F. Raynald</hi> reports at large in his Annals.</p>
               <p>It remains now that we diſtinguiſh the Hereſie of the <hi>Maronites</hi> from that of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> for that, as an <hi>Italian</hi> Author obſerves, they are a Sprout of the <hi>Jacobites.</hi> In effect there is much appearance that the Monk <hi>Maron</hi> quitted the part of the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> or <hi>Eutichaus,</hi> for to render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Chief of a Sect; for we ſee that the <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Maronites</hi> have ſome Books common to both, which however hinders not, but that the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> having ſeparated from the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> have written diverſe Books againſt them, for to prove that there are two Natures in Jeſus Chriſt. 'Tis no good Proof to ſay, that the <hi>Maronites</hi> have not been Hereticks, for that <hi>John Maron</hi> and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:199363:62"/>others of their Writers have compos'd Books a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jacobites, Menophyſites, Acephales,</hi> and <hi>Severians;</hi> for they might have been <hi>Monothelites,</hi> and condemn thoſe Hereſies whereof we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Beſides, they have added many things to their Books ſince they have been totally united to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and it may be they have not only inſerted therein the Condemnation of the <hi>Eutichyans,</hi> but that alſo of the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> and that conformable to the Orders of the Pope's Envoys to Mount <hi>Libanus,</hi> who eſtabliſh'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to review the Books of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> and to retrench in them all that might come near unto Hereſie.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe Proofs, I will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſuſpend my Judgment upon this Subject, until I ſhall ſee in what manner Monſieur <hi>Fauſte Nairon,</hi> a learned <hi>Maronite,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Ecchelenſis,</hi> and his Succeſſor in the College of <hi>Sapience</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> hath defended his Nation from the Hereſies whereof they have been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. This learned <hi>Maronite</hi> hath compoſed a Book in <hi>Italian,</hi> wherein he hath treated of the Original of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> and related all that might contain their Hiſtory. I cannot imagine what hinders the publication of that Work, ſince it hath been finiſh'd three Years ago: I know that divers Latin Authors, whoſe Teſtimonies it were uſeleſs to rehearſe, pretend that the <hi>Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> derive really their Original from that Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>Maron,</hi> of whom we have ſpoken: but we may ſay, that they too eaſily follow the Opinion of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> without being willing to take pains to examine the thing in it ſelf. 'Tis long ſince the <hi>Maronites</hi> have promis'd us the Hiſtory of the pretended St. <hi>Maron,</hi> whoſe Memory they
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:199363:63"/>ſo much celebrate; it were to be wiſhed that ſome learned Perſon amongſt them would plainly exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit that Hiſtory whereof we have but little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for perhaps they have added to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Saints the Heretical Saint <hi>Maron,</hi> as the <hi>Neſtorians</hi> and moſt part of other Sects honour to this day their Patriarchs. The <hi>Neſtorians</hi> honour <hi>Neſtorius</hi> with the Title of Saint in their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Liturgies, and make Imprecations againſt the Memory of Saint <hi>Cyril,</hi> whom they conſider as an Heretick: The <hi>Jacobites</hi> do alſo the ſame thing in reſpect to divers of their Sectaries. There is ſome appearance that it will not be long before we have the Works which the <hi>Maronites</hi> of Mount <hi>Libanus</hi> promiſe to publiſh in one of their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, which is printed at the end of the third Tome of the <hi>Perpetuity.</hi> I wiſh nevertheleſs that before they write of their Liturgies, that they firſt diveſt themſelves of an Infinity of falſe Prejudices, wherewith they are cumber'd, and which hinder them to treat of that matter with exactneſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Moreover, 'tis to be obſerved, that he that hath printed that <hi>Atteſtation</hi> of the <hi>Maronites</hi> hath done it under the name of the <hi>Maronites</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> altho' it hath been writ by them who inhabit Mount <hi>Libanus.</hi> That which deceiv'd him was, that the Patriarch which reſides in the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Cannubin</hi> in Mount <hi>Libanus</hi> takes upon him the Quality of Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> but he does not live at <hi>Antioch;</hi> and I believe alſo that there is not at this time in that City any Church of <hi>Maronites.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:199363:63"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the Twelfth Chapter.</head>
               <p>'TIS no extraordinary wonder to ſee that moſt part of the <hi>Maronite</hi> Prieſts can but only read and write; there are but a very few know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons in all the <hi>Levant,</hi> for they have not the conveniency of Colleges as we have, yet there are ſome of them skill'd in the <hi>Italian.</hi> Beſides, the Jeſuits have Schools in the <hi>Levant,</hi> and particularly at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where they inſtruct Youth. <hi>Cyrilli Lucar,</hi> in a Letter which he writ from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Witem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> pretends that that Ignorance is advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to the <hi>Levantines,</hi> for, ſays he, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain always their ancient Belief without Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: Nevertheleſs, the ſame Author, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letter, hugely reproves the Ignorance of the Prieſts and Biſhops of the Eaſtern Churches, out of a fear he teſtifies to have, leaſt the Eſtabliſhment of the Jeſuits at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> introduce ſome Novelty in the Eaſt; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is obliged to theſe Jeſuits herein, for that they have by that means prevented <hi>Calviniſm</hi> to over ſpread the <hi>Levant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before that the <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onites</hi> had a College at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> they were much more ignorant than they are at this juncture; we have ſeen of them, ſince that time, three very knowing Perſons at
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:199363:64"/>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> who came out of this Seminary. Altho' they have at this time amongſt them divers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons capable to Inſtruct the People, yet they fail not to ſend them ſtill Religious Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to entertain them more in their Duty; but the Eccleſiaſticks of the Country bear them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and often quarrel with them, believing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be more capable to preach, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe other Functions, than thoſe ſent unto them. In effect, it were to be wiſhed there were no other that preached but the Natives, for that 'tis very difficult for the <hi>Europeans</hi> to ſpeak and pronounce the <hi>Arabick</hi> Tongue well, which is the reaſon that the People cannot forbear laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when they hear theſe Preachers ſpeak; ſo far are they from giving them Audience. And I have heard not long ſince, that a Deacon of <hi>Nount Libanus</hi> ſhould ſay, That theſe Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries did them much harm, for that they accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, at their return, of divers Errors, whereof they had no foundation, and that only for to be continued in their Miſſion.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Caldean</hi> Tongue, 'tis true that 'tis the ſame amongſt them at this day, as the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> is amongſt us. Since <hi>Omar</hi> rendered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of <hi>Syria,</hi> at the beginning of the ſeventh Century, the <hi>Arabick</hi> Language intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it ſelf by little and little into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and as the <hi>Arabs</hi> commanded and held the principal Offices there, they obliged the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to conform themſelves to their Language. However, the <hi>Caldee</hi> hath always been conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Church, and the moſt knowing writ ſtill in that Language, after <hi>Omar,</hi> for a long time; nevertheleſs you muſt obſerve, that the Language which the Ancients calls <hi>Caldee,</hi> is
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:199363:64"/>ordinarily called <hi>Syriack,</hi> which moſt part of Grammarians diſtinguiſh from the <hi>Arabick Caldee,</hi> as two different Dialects; but the <hi>Maronites,</hi> whom our Author has followed, call ſometimes their Language the <hi>Caldee.</hi> In effect, that which we call <hi>Syriack,</hi> differs not almoſt from the <hi>Caldee</hi> but the Characters; 'tis true that it hath many Dialects, but all theſe Dialects make but one Language. 'Tis very ancient, and ſome pretend that it was the Language of our firſt Parents. That which might ſupport this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, That there is no other Language that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſo ſimple in its expreſſions; nevertheleſs there is greater appearance that 'tis a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hebrew, as the Italian is of the Latin, and that in proceſs of time it appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it ſelf divers Greek words, and the words alſo of other Languages. It has a particular Character, which is but a corruption of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Character; wherefore 'tis needleſs to ſearch as many have done, who it was that firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the <hi>Syriack</hi> Letters. They differ alſo from one another in their Characters, as the French vary from the Italians in the manner of writing their Letters. The <hi>Jacobites</hi> and the <hi>Maronites</hi> have the ſame Letters, and they are ſuch as we ſee in their printed Books. The <hi>Neſtorian Caldeans,</hi> which are diſperſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of the <hi>Levant,</hi> have different Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters from thoſe of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> and 'tis by that we may eaſily know the Manuſcripts of the different <hi>Caldean</hi> Sects, altho' theſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters differ no more one from another than the writing of a French Man and an Italian.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:199363:65"/>
               <p>We have no room here to ſpeak of all the Books which are written in <hi>Caldee,</hi> we will obſerve only ſuch as are in uſe at this day amongſt the <hi>Maronites,</hi> that we may not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs too far from the deſign of our Author. They have in the firſt place two ſorts of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack</hi> Tranſlations of the Old Teſtament, one of which is done out of the Hebrew, and the other out of the Greek of the Septuagint; however, we muſt not give credit to what ſome ſay of that Verſion out of the Hebrew, which they call ſimple, for to diſtinguiſh it from the other, for they falſly believe that that Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been done in the time of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Hiram</hi> King of <hi>Tyre;</hi> 'tis an Hiſtory which hath no more foundation than that of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack</hi> Letters, for Authors attribute theſe ſame alſo to <hi>Solomon. Gregory Abulfarius</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe two Verſions, and affirms that the Eaſtern <hi>Syrians</hi> make uſe of the firſt, and the Weſtern <hi>Syrians</hi> of both. <hi>Hebed Jeſu,</hi> in his Catalogue of <hi>Caldee</hi> Books, ſpeaks of one <hi>Mar Aba,</hi> who hath tranſlated the Old Teſtament out of the Greek into Syriack; but as the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack</hi> Church was in being long before this <hi>Mar Aba,</hi> it had a Tranſlation of the Bible into Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack taken out of the Greek Tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> for the Church, in the firſt Ages, knew no other Bible but that of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> which ſeemed to have been alone eſteemed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick in the Decrees of Councels, and I know not why the Eaſtern <hi>Tyrians</hi> made uſe of a Verſion made different from the Hebrew Text, ſince the Apoſtles themſelves uſed the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gints;</hi> and that the firſt Tranſlations from the Hebrew, different from that of the Seventy,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:199363:65"/>were rather for the uſe of particular Perſons than any Church. Moreover, <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Nibiſe</hi> and St. <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who preceded <hi>Mar Aba,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Bible of the <hi>Septuagint;</hi> beſides, that Verſion which they call ſimple, for to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it from that of the Seventy, which doth not always follow the Text, differs ſometimes from the Hebrew for to accord with the Greek. However, it may be well ſeen, that at firſt it was entirely conformable to the Hebrew, but that with time it has been corrupted by Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers, and particular Perſons, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it in ſome places by the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that that Verſion hath loſt ſomewhat of its ancient ſimplicity, through the different commixtures that hath been introduced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. There is alſo ſome appearance, that the Hebrew Text, from which that <hi>Syriack</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation hath been made, was not altogether the ſame as that we have at this day; as for the <hi>Syriack</hi> New Teſtament, I do not doubt but that it may be very ancient, yet the dialect wherein it is written is a ſufficient proof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my judgment, for to ſhew that it is not an Original. The <hi>Caldee</hi> that was ſpoken in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the time of our Saviour, was not the <hi>Caldee</hi> Language of the New Teſtament; and if St. <hi>Matthew</hi> writ his Goſpel in that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which they called alſo then the Hebrew, as is very probable, it cannot be ſaid that 'tis the ſame <hi>Syriack</hi> Goſpel as we have at this day, becauſe of the difference of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. cauſed a little Prayer-Book to be printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the year 1585. for their uſe, written in Arabick and Syriack
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:199363:66"/>Characters; that Book contained ſome Prayers, which bore the Title of <hi>Salutation,</hi> and addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Archangels <hi>Gabriel</hi> and <hi>Michael,</hi> with ſome other things of the like nature; whereunto were added the Penitential Pſalms, with the Litanies of the Saints. But theſe Litanies, that are in uſe in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have not been received by the Maronites of <hi>Mount Libanus,</hi> unleſs it be very lately, for that <hi>Gabriel Sionita</hi> hath left them out of his Copy which I have in my hands, and 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that that faſhion of Praying to Saints is not ordinary in the Eaſtern Churches.</p>
               <p>They have alſo their particular Editions of Councels, their Conſtitutions, their Fathers, and divers other Books; nevertheleſs you muſt obſerve, that they acknowledge but the firſt four General Councels that preceded their Schiſm. I queſtion alſo, whether the Maronites have at any time had any particular Conſtitutions, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they procure ſome that bear that Name; it may be that they have added that Title to a Book, which they call at this day the <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Conſtitutions,</hi> which a Learned Man of that Nation pretends to have been written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Califf Omar</hi> rendered himſelf Maſter of <hi>Syria.</hi> I cannot tell what foundation he has for to believe them to be ſo ancient, if it be not that they are written in <hi>Syriack,</hi> and that that Language, according to his Sentiment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow out of uſe from the time of <hi>Omar.</hi> They have been Tranſlated into <hi>Arabic</hi> in 1059. by a Maronite Archbiſhop, according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Abraham Ecchelenſis,</hi> and they treat of divers Matters in Theology, principally of the Sacraments. Proper Baptiſm is there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:199363:66"/>from the Metaphorical, or Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is conſidered as the perfection of Baptiſm; frequent Communion much recommended. There is a long Treatiſe about the Ordination of Chantres, Exorciſts, Readers, Sub-deacons, Deacons, Prieſts, and Biſhops, to whom it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd to aſſemble before their Patriarch. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, one may ſee there Rules for the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Temporalities of the Church, for Tythes, for Pious Legacies, for Civil Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; to wit, for all things that regard Wills, things in Truſt, Inheritances, Donations, Loans, Reſtitutions, and Purchaſes. The ſame Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions regulate alſo the Services that ought to be performed towards the Dead, their Burial, and the Banquets they make for them; therein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, are particular Statutes for Monks, for the Schools, and for the Books that were to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the Church. Finally, you may have Rules there for to make a diſtinction of Sins; Murder, Apoſtacy, and Fornication, are reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the greateſt.</p>
               <p>The Author pretends in this Chapter, that 'tis a great happineſs to the Chriſtians of the <hi>Levant,</hi> that they have not the uſe of printing, becauſe that prevents the errors of ſo many Sects to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd with the Orthodox; one may ſay as much of the impreſſions of <hi>Europe,</hi> which have their commodities and incommodities, for that ought to facilitate great changes both in Church and State. If the <hi>Levantines</hi> lay aſide the uſe of printing for theſe Reaſons, they are wiſer than we in following that Maxim of Policy, <hi>Non proſit potius ſiquid Obeſſe poteſt:</hi> However, the <hi>Turks</hi> permit the <hi>Jews</hi> to print at <hi>Conſtantinople, Salonica,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but 'tis upon condition that they print
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:199363:67"/>none but their own Books, which is of no conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>He adds moreover, that Manuſcripts are more ſubject to changes than printed Books; in effect, that happens but too often, and without having oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſearch elſewhere for examples, the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> alone furniſh us with enough, for one can almoſt ſee no Manuſcript-Books amongſt them, for Divine Service, that are altogether alike and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thoſe printed at <hi>Rome</hi> for their uſe, but ſome are larger, other again contain leſs. 'Tis alſo worthy of obſervation, that <hi>Morin,</hi> who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved he had given us the Ordinations of the Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites entirely, hath printed but the leſſer part, which regards the Miniſtry of the Biſhops; for they are uſed to have two diſtinct Books, one of which ſerves the Biſhop, who Ordains, and the other the Miniſter, who Anſwers him. The firſt is properly the Book of Ordinations, the other is cailed the Clerks Book; in the mean time F. <hi>Morin,</hi> who had but the laſt, hath given it us as an entire Copy of the Ordination of the Maronites, and I am ſurprized that <hi>Abraham Ecchelenſis,</hi> a Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, who hath peruſed the Copy of <hi>Morin,</hi> hath not advertiſed him hereof, that muſt have eſcaped them both; but an omiſſion is no change, and it were eaſie, with little precaution, to ſhun the like miſtakes, which cannot be done when Tranſcribers can add to, and retrench, as they pleaſe, in their Manuſcripts, for they ought to have divers Perſons for to compare them together, and to examine throughly the Contents of the Book, to ſee if they can diſcover therein any Innovation; they need but uſe this Rule about the Books of the Maronites, and it ſhall be found they are not for the moſt part ſuch as they are repreſented to be. For example;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:199363:67"/>If you examine thoſe that have been written in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack,</hi> under the Name of <hi>John Maron,</hi> it will be eaſie to diſcover they have not all the Antiquity which the Maronites attribute unto them; or if they be ſo ancient, divers things have been added thereunto, which could not be written ſince that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <head>Remarks upon the Thirteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>I Cannot tell whether it was Neceſſity or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, that introduced into the Church of the Maronites the uſe of thoſe Biſhops which have no Juriſdiction, and which they ordinarily call <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi ſine Clero &amp; Populo;</hi> this Cuſtom, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, might have its advantages, for that they found ſometimes occaſion to make uſe of Prieſts that were Biſhops, and then they were Coadjutors. It ſeems alſo, that in the time of the Apoſtles, the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was not ſeparate from the Epiſcopacy, altho' they exerciſed not entirely the Function of the Biſhop. It cannot be ſaid that the Abbots of <hi>Mount Libanus</hi> take the quality of Biſhops upon them, for to be exempted from the ordinary Juriſdiction, as many of our Abbots have done, for they know not in that Country what it is to be without theſe ſorts of Exemptions, they have only pretended thereby, that they could promote themſelves to the Epiſcopacy without the leave of their Patriarch, which was the cauſe of great trouble amongſt them, and which <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. remedied. As to the Marriage of Prieſts, there is no body knows
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:199363:68"/>not but that the Diſcipline of the Eaſtern Church differs in that from the Weſtern Churches, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it may be ſaid, that the uſage that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in all the <hi>Levant,</hi> is a diſpenſing with the Canons. I know that the <hi>Greeks,</hi> at this day, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that they follow the ancient Canons, and rely upon thoſe which are called the Canons of the Apoſtles; the 13th Canon of the ſixth Councel, which they call <hi>in Trullo,</hi> made uſe of the foreſaid Canons for a Rule, and they were afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in a Councel of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as if they contradicted the ancient Rules. But St. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany,</hi> who lived long before, declares, That the Marriage of Prieſts was a tranſgreſſing of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons which enjoined their Celibacy; and added, that that was diſpenſed with, becauſe they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten occaſion for Prieſts, and that it was difficult to find them, if obliged perpetually to a ſingle life. The words he makes uſe of, diſcover plainly that this uſage is very ancient in the Eaſtern Church. Moreover, we do not ſee that the Councels of <hi>Nice, Ancyra, Neoceſarea,</hi> and <hi>Laodicia,</hi> have made any Rules for to oblige Prieſts to Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, but on the contrary, the Hiſtory of <hi>Panuche</hi> reported by <hi>Socrates,</hi> demonſtrates, that the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> regarded that Diſcipline which is now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as an hard, ſevere, and unnatural Law, to which they ought in no wiſe to compel the Prieſts to ſubmit. Indeed, as the Church is the Miſtreſs of ſuch Laws, it may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpence with them; and 'tis an effect of its great prudence to accord with the weakneſs of Men when it ſees occaſion, the right of rigour and compulſion is not always, if ever, in ſeaſon. Thus it is certain, the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> V. conſented to the marriage of Prieſts in that famous interim,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:199363:68"/>which was done for the preſervation of peace, till the General Councel had determined ſomewhat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that point, which was then in diſpute. Nay, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> III. himſelf, gave his Nuncio's in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> power to accord with the Emperor, in his demands touching the marriage of Prieſts.</p>
               <p>You muſt nevertheleſs obſerve, that the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline at this day, in regard to the marriage of Prieſts, and other Eccleſiaſticks that are in holy Orders, is not the ſame as in ancient times, for the Prieſthood was not then ſuch an impediment as to diſannul the marriage as it has been ſince. The firſt Canon of the Councel of <hi>Neoceſarea</hi> ordered, That a Prieſt that ſhould marry ſhould be deprived from the exerciſe of his Charge, but it touched not at all upon the marriage it ſelf, which was ſuppoſed to be legitimate. And it appears by the ſame Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, That Fornication and Adultery were puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Prieſts, much more ſeverely than marriage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ordination; and ſo, conſequently, it was a far greater crime. They had alſo this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Deacons and Prieſts; That the Deacons might marry after their Ordination, if they had before proteſted that they could not live Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, which was not permitted by them to the Prieſts; but if it happen'd that a Deacon married after his Ordination, without firſt making his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, his marriage ceaſed not to be good, but they ſuffered him not to exerciſe the Function of his Office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:199363:69"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the Fourteenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THE Reflections which our Author makes in this Chapter upon the Life and Manners of the Religious <hi>Maronites</hi> are very judicious: St. <hi>Hilarion,</hi> the Diſciple of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> was the Father of the Monks of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> as his Maſter had been of thoſe of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> We might have many things here to ſay touching the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Eſtabliſhment of theſe Monks, who are the Source and Foundation of all Monachiſm, but as there are many Authors who have written here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we need not repeat here that which they have ſaid; and all the World knows, that the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Religious Life <hi>hath nothing divine in it:</hi> The number of the ancient Solitaries encreaſed in a moment, for they had no need then of Bulls, Letters Patents, no more than the permiſſion of Ordinaries, for to eſtabliſh Religious Houſes; there was no more demanded, if in the Title of their Foundation they had a ſufficient Revenue for to maintain them, to the end they might not be any charge to the Publick; for theſe firſt Monks were very different from thoſe we ſee at this day, thoſe forſook the Cities for to retire themſelves into the Mountains, built them there very ſmall Lodgings, and every one labour'd at his Calling, inſomuch that their Solitude became Villages in a ſhort time. Likewiſe they gave them the Name
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:199363:69"/>of <hi>Laura,</hi> which is a Greek word, which they uſe in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> principally for to ſignifie <hi>diverſe Houſes joyned together:</hi> and <hi>Agapius,</hi> a Religious of Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> hath inſerted in a Book of his called <hi>The Salvation of Sinners,</hi> a particular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter touching the St. <hi>Laura</hi> of Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> for 'tis ſo he calls his Monaſtery: They had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing at thoſe beginnings of particular places to live upon in Community. <hi>Eutychius</hi> reports, That the Religious that inhabited Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> were diſperſed here and there in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Valleys, about the Buſh where God ſpake unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> until that the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian</hi> cauſed a Monaſtery to be built for to ſhelter them againſt the Incurſions of the <hi>Arabs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe by whom they were governed took the Names of Abbots or Archimandrites upon them; and I believe that theſe two terms came original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the <hi>Syriac.</hi> As to the firſt, which is that of Abbot, which ſignifies Father, there is no doubt of it; and for the ſecon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, there is much likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that the Word <hi>Mandra,</hi> which in the Greek ſignifies <hi>a Stable,</hi> or <hi>place to put up Beaſts,</hi> hath been taken from the word <hi>Dour,</hi> which the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> uſe to ſet forth the Habitation that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers have in pitiful Hutts, and very often in Stables: In effect the <hi>Syrians</hi> uſe the word <hi>Dairo</hi> for to ſignifie theſe ſort of Manſions, and a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery. The <hi>Arabs</hi> have alſo imitated in that the <hi>Syrians,</hi> inſomuch that a Mandrite is no other thing than a ſolitary retirement into a ſmall Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Cell, which our Author compares to the Caverns of Beaſts. He that was the Chief, and as it were the Dean of all theſe Solitaries, took upon him the Name of <hi>Archimandrite,</hi> that is,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:199363:70"/>Head and Maſter of the Solitaries. Moreover, theſe ſort of People, who retired from the Towns to lead a private Life in Solitude, could not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without ſome Rules; wherefore they enacted certain Laws, unto which they would ſubmit: and altho' we do not know whether they made then Vows of Poverty, Chaſtity, and Obedience, they fail'd not to practiſe them all; for, as to that of Poverty, they ſaw it was ſet forth in the Goſpel as a ſtate of Perfection; in regard to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, 'tis ſuppoſed they could not live in a body without Superiors, whom they were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to obey; finally, as they had entirely quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Commerce of the World, it ſeems their Condition engaged them to live ſeparated from Women. Thus, when they receiv'd any one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Society, it was ſufficient to repreſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him once, without any worſhip, what manner they lived; if, after that, he embraced their ſort of living, he was obliged to conform himſelf to the reſt, without having occaſion to make any Vows. And our Author obſerves, that altho' the Religious <hi>Maronites</hi> made none, yet they lived in perfect Continence, and that they went alone up and down, and abſented themſelves many days from their Monaſtery, without having the leaſt ill ſpoken of them.</p>
               <p>Their Habit alſo was very mean and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Profeſſion, for they clad themſelves after the manner of Peaſants and Labourers. The Author attributes to the Religious <hi>Maronites</hi> only a Bonnet and a pitiful Coat, that deſcends down only to the Girdle, but it is ſuppoſed that they wear beſides that a Drawers, according to the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abic</hi> Faſhion, which cover alſo their Legs; he
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:199363:70"/>explains himſelf well when he ſaith thoſe Monks have not a long Veſt, like unto that of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Europeans.</hi> In effect, theſe long Habits would be incommodious for theſe People to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in: One may conſult what <hi>Caſſien</hi> and others have writ touching the Habits of the Ancient Monks. As it hath always been the Cuſtom in the <hi>Levant</hi> for to learn ſome Trade, and that Perſons of Quality alſo are not exempted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo ought not we to be aſtoniſh'd that theſe Solitaries, who had no Employs in the Towns, labour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with their Hands for to get their Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood: but I cannot approve, that a Man who might be profitable to the Publick in ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable matter, ſhould remain all day ſhut up in Solitude, for to make Lanthorns and Sabots. In the mean time, altho' Hand labour hath not been ſo in uſe amongſt the Monks of <hi>Europe,</hi> becauſe the greateſt part of their Monaſteries have been endow'd with Yearly Revenues, yet they have not totally neglected it; for, to give them their due, ſome have imploy'd themſelves in a Labour much more profitable, to wit, to write Books, and make ſeveral Tranſcriptions of them, ſo that we are beholden to them for a great part of thoſe we have extant amongſt us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:199363:71"/>
               <head>Remarks upon the Seventeenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>WE ſhall make no further Obſervations, than to explain that which regards the Election of the Patriarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> to wit, if it depends really upon the People, and how. 'Tis certain that the Election of Biſhops, and alſo Prieſts, was done formerly by the People; but as there happen'd ſometimes great Diſorders at theſe ſorts of Elections, they were oblig'd to change that Diſcipline; the Thirtieth Canon of the Council of <hi>Laodicea</hi> forbids them; but if good heed be given to the Words of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, it ſeems, that that Prohibition regards but the inferiour ſort. In effect the People have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted ſtill at this Election long after the Ordinance of that Council. As to the Election of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> the People have a great ſhare therein, for it depends upon the Body of the Republick, who ought to acknowledge him that hath been elected, otherwiſe the Election were null: But as the Eccleſiaſticks hold the firſt rank in the State, ſo they contribute much to the Election; their manner is thus. Twelve of the principal Prieſts, who in ſome faſhion repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſacred College of the Apoſtles, aſſemble in the Monaſtery of <hi>Cannubin,</hi> where they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Election of a new Patriarch, by way of Scrutiny, and when they are all agreed, then
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:199363:71"/>the Republick which is aſſembled, that is the Eccleſiaſticks and the People, give their Conſent to that Election.</p>
               <p>This ſort of Election is much like unto that which was ſometimes obſerved at the Election of the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which is ſpoken of in the Annals of <hi>Eutychius;</hi> nevertheleſs, as 'tis impoſſible all the Voices ſhould concurr to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Scrutiny, they have a ſecond man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding, which is a kind of Compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that is, that theſe dozen Prieſts choſe three by Lot, and that theſe three make a Patriarch, which is alſo elected by two Voices, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the People confirm that Election by their Conſent. But beſides this, ſince the <hi>Maronites</hi> have been united to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Patriarch is obliged to receive the Pope's Bulls of Confirmation, conformable to the Rules of the New Right of that Church.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:72"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS printed for</hi> Abel Roper, <hi>at the</hi> Black Boy <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>THE ancient and preſent ſtate of <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy;</hi> containing a Geographical, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical and Political account of all thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Territories under the Juriſdiction of the preſent Czar; with Sculptures and a new Map; by <hi>J. C.</hi> M. D. Fellow of the Royal Society, and a Member of the College of Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Poland,</hi> in ſeveral Letters to Perſons of Quality: giving an account of the ancient and preſent ſtate of that Kingdom, Hiſtorical, Geographical, Phyſical, Political, and Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>viz.</hi> it's origin and extent, with a deſcription of its Towns and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Religion, Learning, Language, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Habits, Manners, Riches, Trade, and Military affairs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vol. I. By <hi>Bern. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> M. D. Fellow of the Royal Society, and Member of the College of Phyſicians, who in his Travels in that Country collected theſe Memoirs from the <hi>beſt Authors</hi> and his own Obſervations. Publiſh'd by the care and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Savage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A true Hiſtory of the ſeveral Deſigns and Conſpiracies againſt his Majeſty's ſacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Government, as they were continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried on from 1688 to 1697: containing matters extracted from original Papers on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Witneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>R. K.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:73"/>
            <p>Marriage-Ceremonies; or the Ceremonies uſed in Marriages in all parts of the world: Very diverting, eſpecially to the Ladies. By Seignior <hi>Gaya.</hi> Tranſlated from the Italian. The ſecond Edition; to which is added ſome Remarks upon Marriage, written by Mr. <hi>Tho. Brown.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Books printed for</hi> R. Baſſet, <hi>at the</hi> Mitre <hi>within</hi> Temple-bar <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>THe Life of the learned Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> Doctor of the Civil Laws, principal Secretary of State to King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> wherein are diſcover'd many ſingular matters relating to the ſtate of Learning, the Reformation of Religion, and the Tranſactions of the Kingdom during his time, in all which he had a great and happy influence.</p>
            <p>The Innocent Miſtreſs; a Comedy, as it is now acted at the new Theatre in <hi>Little Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colns-Inn-Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deceiver deceiv'd; a Comedy, as it is acted by His Majeſty's Servants at the New Theatre. Both written by Mrs. <hi>Pix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Love's Reward, or the Unnatural Mother; a Tragi-Comedy, acted at the Theatre in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-Fields:</hi> written by Madam —</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199363:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
